<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on 毎朝日</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on 毎朝日</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>9代目「ヤン坊マー坊」黒髪の丸い頭から一新　新デザインを一般投票</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/the-9th-generation-yanbo-ma-bo-will-be-completely-redesigned-from-the-round-black-head-and-the-new-design-will-be-decided-by-a-general-vote/</link><pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/the-9th-generation-yanbo-ma-bo-will-be-completely-redesigned-from-the-round-black-head-and-the-new-design-will-be-decided-by-a-general-vote/</guid><description>ヤンマーホールディングスは「ヤン坊マー坊」の新デザインを一般投票で決める=同社提供 Link to the original article
ヤン坊やんぼうマー坊まーぼうを刷新しんさいします――。ヤンマーホールディングスは16日にち、同社のマスコットますこっとキャラクター「ヤン坊やんぼうマー坊まーぼう」の新あたらデザインでざいん案を一般いっぱんからの投票とうひょうで決きめると発表はっぴょうした。デザイン案はA～Cの3案あんあり、インターネットいんたーねっとで票ひょうを募つのる。結果けっかは来年らいねん1月がつに発表はっぴょうする。 ヤン坊やんぼうマー坊まーぼうは、1959（昭和しょうわ34）年ねんに初代しょだいが登場とうじょう。今回こんかいの刷新しんかいで9代目だいめとなる。新しんデザインでざいん案は、兄あにヤン坊と弟おとうとマー坊のイメージいめーじカラーからーの赤あかと青あおを基調きちょうとした、現代げんだいアニメあにめ風ふうの絵柄えがらが共通きょうつう点だ。踏襲ふしゅうしてきた黒髪くろかみの丸まるい頭あたまのキャラクターきゃらくたーからは一新いっしんする。 同社によるとによると、14年ねんに「ヤン坊マー坊天気予報やんぼうまーぼうてんきよほう」のテレビてれび放送ほうそうが終わりおわり、若わかい世代せだいを中心ちゅうしんに知名度ちめいどの低下ていかが進んでいたすすんでいた。担当者たんとうしゃは「ありがたいありがたいことことに、これまでのデザインでざいんは天気予報てんきよほうなどを通してとおして親しまれているしたしまれているが、ぜひ新あたらしいデザインでざいんも愛あいしていただきたい。ヤン坊マー坊やんぼうまーぼうを知らないしらない世代せだいのお子おこさんとの話題わだいのきっかけきっかけにしてほしい」と話しているはなしている。 投票は12月がつ7日にちまで特設とくせつサイトさいと（https://www.yanmar.com/jp/about/yanboh_marboh/vote/https://www.yanmar.com/jp/about/yanboh_marboh/vote/）からできる。投票は1日にち1回かいまで、期間きかん中ちゅうは何度なんどでもできる。 ヤン坊やんぼうマー坊まーぼうは1959年ねん、ヤンマーディーゼルやんまーでぃーぜる（現げんヤンマーホールディングスやんまーほーるでぃんぐす）が提供ていきょうする「ヤン坊やんぼうマー坊まーぼう天気てんき予報よほう」のキャラクターきゃらくたーとして誕生たんじょうした。現在げんざいのCG化かされたデザインでざいんは、誕生たんじょうから60周年しゅうねんを迎むかえた19年ねんにリニューアルりにゅーあるされた8代目だいめのもの。（中村なかむら建太けんた） Vocabulary Word (Furigana) JLPT Level Part of Speech Meaning 刷新 (しんさい) N2 Noun renewal, update 案 (あん) N3 Noun plan, proposal 投票 (とうひょう) N3 Noun voting, poll 決める (きめる) N4 Verb (ru-verb) to decide 発表 (はっぴょう) N3 Noun announcement, publication 募る (つのる) N2 Verb (u-verb) to recruit, to solicit 結果 (けっか) N4 Noun result, outcome 発表する (はっぴょうする) N3 Verb (suru-verb) to announce, to publish 登場 (とうじょう) N3 Noun appearance, entry 刷新 (しんさい) N2 Noun renewal, update 共通 (きょうつう) N3 Noun common, shared 踏襲 (とうしゅう) N1 Noun following, maintaining 一新 (いっしん) N1 Noun renewal, renovation 知名度 (ちめいど) N1 Noun level of fame, popularity 低下 (ていか) N3 Noun decline, fall 担当者 (たんとうしゃ) N2 Noun person in charge, responsible person 知らない (しらない) N4 Adjective unknown, unfamiliar 世代 (せだい) N3 Noun generation 話題 (わだい) N3 Noun topic, subject 特設 (とくせつ) N1 Noun special establishment, special setup 期間 (きかん) N3 Noun period, term 提供する (ていきょうする) N3 Verb (suru-verb) to provide, to offer 誕生 (たんじょう) N3 Noun birth, creation 迎える (むかえる) N3 Verb (ru-verb) to welcome, to greet リニューアル (りにゅーある) N/A Noun renewal, renovation Grammar and Sentence Structure ヤン坊マー坊は、1959（昭和34）年に初代が登場。今回の刷新で9代目となる。</description></item><item><title>イスラエル兵、シファ病院内を移動して患者らを尋問　BBC報道</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/israeli-soldiers-move-through-sheba-hospital-and-question-patients-bbc-report/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/israeli-soldiers-move-through-sheba-hospital-and-question-patients-bbc-report/</guid><description>パレスチナ自治区ガザ地区のシファ病院で2023年11月5日、イスラエル軍の空爆で負傷し手当てを受ける男性=AP Link to the original article
イスラエルいすらえる軍は15日にち、同日じつ未明めいに突入とつにゅうしたパレスチナぱれすちな自治区じちくガザ地区ちくにあるシファしふぁ病院びょういんでの作戦さくせんを継続けいぞくしていると明あきらかにした。軍は「精密せいみつで的まとを絞しぼった作戦さくせん」としている。医療いりょうチームちーむやアラビア語あらびあごを話はなす兵士へいしなども送おくり込こみ、民間人みんかんじんに危害きがいが及およばないように配慮はいりょしているとも強調きょうちょう。イスラエルは同どう病院びょういんにイスラムいすらむ組織そしきハマスの軍事ぐんじ拠点きょてんがあると主張しゅちょうしている。 一方、カタールかたーるの衛星えいせい放送ほうそう局きょくアルジャジーラあるじゃじーらは15日にち、同どう病院びょういんの病院びょういん長ちょうの話はなしとして、「イスラエルいすらえる軍ぐんは病院びょういんの地下ちかを捜索そうさくしている」と伝つたえた。別べつの医師いしは「戦車せんしゃとブルドーザーぶるどーざーが病院びょういん敷地しきち内ないにいる。激はげしい発砲はっぽうがあり、あちこちで爆発音ばくはつおんがしている」と語かたった。 イスラエルいすらえる軍ぐんが15日にちに突入とつにゅうしたパレスチナぱれすちな自治区じちくガザがざ地区ちくのシファしふぁ病院びょういんについて、米べいCNNは同日どうじつ、病院びょういん内にいる地元ちもとメディアめでぃあの記者きしゃの話はなしとして、イスラエルいすらえる軍ぐんは若者わかものたちに向むけてメガホンめがほんで「手てを挙あげて出でてきて、投降とうこうするよう呼よびかけている」と報ほうじた。 また、英えいBBCびーびーしーによると、病院びょういん内にいる地元じもとメディアめでぃあの記者きしゃが、6台だいの戦車せんしゃと100人にん以上の兵士へいしを確認かくにんしたという。記者きしゃは「何人なにびとかの兵士へいしは覆面ふくめんをし、アラビア語あらびあごで『動うごくな、くな動うごくな、くな』と叫さけんだ」と話はなした。 BBCはさらに、病院内ないの別べつの記者きしゃの話はなしとして、兵士へいしが「部屋へやから部屋へや、フロアふろあからフロアふろあへと、スタッフすたっふから患者かんじゃまで全員ぜんいんに尋問じんもんしている」と伝つたえた。イスラエル軍ぐんは病院びょういんを「完全かんぜんにコントロールこんとろーる」しており、銃撃戦じゅうげきせんは行おこなわれていないという。 Vocabulary Word (Furigana) JLPT Level Part of Speech Meaning 突入 (とつにゅう) N2 Noun, Suru verb penetration, invasion 継続 (けいぞく) N3 Noun, Suru verb continuation, persistence 明らか (あきらか) N3 Na-adjective obvious, evident 精密 (せいみつ) N1 Na-adjective, Noun precise, accurate 的を絞る (まとをしぼる) N1 Expression to focus on the target 配慮 (はいりょ) N2 Noun, Suru verb consideration, concern 及ぶ (およぶ) N3 Godan verb to reach, to extend to 強調 (きょうちょう) N3 Noun, Suru verb emphasis, highlight 主張 (しゅちょう) N3 Noun, Suru verb claim, assertion 伝える (つたえる) N4 Ichidan verb to convey, to report 捜索 (そうさく) N1 Noun, Suru verb search, investigation 発砲 (はっぽう) N1 Noun, Suru verb firing (gun), shooting 爆発音 (ばくはつおん) N1 Noun explosion sound 投降 (とうこう) N1 Noun, Suru verb surrender, capitulation 呼びかける (よびかける) N3 Ichidan verb to call out, to appeal 確認 (かくにん) N3 Noun, Suru verb confirmation, verification 覆面 (ふくめん) N1 Noun mask, disguise 叫ぶ (さけぶ) N3 Godan verb to shout, to yell 尋問 (じんもん) N1 Noun, Suru verb interrogation, questioning 銃撃戦 (じゅうげきせん) N1 Noun gun battle, gunfire Grammar and Sentence Structure Sentence 1:</description></item><item><title>フリーカメラマンの通勤事故、「労災」と認定　偽装フリーランス問題</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/a-commuting-accident-of-a-freelance-photographer-is-recognized-as-industrial-accident-addressing-the-issue-of-disguised-freelancers/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/a-commuting-accident-of-a-freelance-photographer-is-recognized-as-industrial-accident-addressing-the-issue-of-disguised-freelancers/</guid><description>仕事で使うカメラを手にするフリーカメラマンの男性。労働基準監督署から「労働者」と認められた=2023年8月18日、東京都内、遠藤隆史撮影 Link to the original article
形式的にはフリーランスふりーらんすだが、実態は労働者ろうどうしゃと変わらない「偽装ぎそうフリーランスふりーらんす」の問題もんだいをめぐり、品川しながわ労働ろうどう基準きじゅん監督かんとく署しょ（東京とうきょう都と）が、都内とないの会社かいしゃと業務ぎょうむ委託いたく契約けいやくを結むすぶフリーカメラマンふりーかめらまんの男性だんせい（40）が通勤つうきん中に遭あった交通こうつう事故じこを労災ろうさいと認定にんていしたことがわかった。労基ろうき署しょの決定けっていは10月がつ12日にち付ふ。 男性によると、2020年にせんにじゅうねんから都内とないの会社かいしゃと半年はんとし更新こうしんの業務ぎょうむ委託いたく契約けいやくを結むすび、同社どうしゃが受注じゅちゅうした広告こうこく写真しゃしんの撮影さつえいなどを担になってきた。22年ねん7月がつ、車くるまで現場げんばに向むかう途中とちゅうに後続こうぞく車くるまに追突ついとつされ、頸椎けいつい（けいついけいつい）捻挫ねんざや左ひだり足あし骨こつ折おれなどのけがけがを負おったという。自身じしんの働はたらき方かたはフリーランスふりーらんすではないと考かんがえ、12月がつに労基署ろうきしょに労災ろうさい申請しんせいした。 フリーランスふりーらんすは自身じしんの広ひろい裁量さいりょうで働はたらける一方いっぽう、労働ろうどう基準きじゅん法ほうなどで保護ほごされる「労働者ろうどうしゃ」と扱あつかわれず、原則げんそくとして労災ろうさい保険ほけんなどの対象たいしょうにならない。 しかし男性だんせいの場合ばあい、繁忙期はんぼうきは同社どうしゃからの仕事しごとだけで月つき200時間じかん働はたらくこともあり、他ほかの仕事しごとを受うける余裕よゆうはなかった。撮影さつえい自体じたいは自身じしんに裁量さいりょうがあるが、撮影さつえい場所ばしょや時間じかんは発注者はっちゅうしゃの意向いこうに拘束こうそくされ、会社かいしゃから撮影さつえい件数に関係かんけいない月つきごとの固定こてい報酬ほうしゅうが支払しはらわれた。カメラかめら以外いがいの機材きざいも会社かいしゃから無償むしょう提供ていきょうされていたという。 品川しながわ労基き署ははこうした働はたらき方かたの実態じったいを踏ふまえ、男性だんせいにはフリーランスふりーらんすとしての裁量さいりょうがなく、会社かいしゃから細こまかな指揮しき命令めいれいを受うける労働者ろうどうしゃだったと判断はんだんして、労災ろうさい認定にんていしたとみられる。 男性を支援しえんする労働組合ろうどうくみあいで、フリーランスふりーらんすの編集者へんしゅうしゃらが加盟かめいする「ユニオン出版ネットワークゆにおんしゅっぱんねっとわーく」の杉村和美すぎむらかずみさん（71）は「労基署ろうきしょが労働実態ろうどうじったいを丁寧ていねいに聞きき取とった結果けっかだ。偽装ぎそうフリーランスふりーらんすの救済きゅうさいにつながる大おおきな成果せいかだ」と話はなした。会社側かいしゃがわは取材しゅざいに「特とくにコメントコメントはない」と回答かいとうした。（遠藤隆史えんどうたかし） Vocabulary Word JLPT Level Part of Speech Meaning 偽装 (ぎそう) N1 Noun disguise, camouflage 認定 (にんてい) N2 Noun certification, approval 決定 (けってい) N3 Noun decision, determination 更新 (こうしん) N3 Noun renewal, update 契約 (けいやく) N3 Noun contract, agreement 撮影 (さつえい) N3 Noun photography, filming 事故 (じこ) N3 Noun accident, incident 労災 (ろうさい) N1 Noun workers&amp;rsquo; compensation 申請 (しんせい) N3 Noun application, request 裁量 (さいりょう) N1 Noun discretion, latitude 保護 (ほご) N3 Noun protection, safeguard 対象 (たいしょう) N3 Noun target, object 余裕 (よゆう) N3 Noun surplus, margin 拘束 (こうそく) N1 Noun restraint, restriction 編集者 (へんしゅうしゃ) N1 Noun editor 加盟 (かめい) N1 Noun affiliation, membership 救済 (きゅうさい) N1 Noun relief, aid 通勤 (つうきん) N2 Suru Verb commuting to work 遭う (あう) N2 Godan Verb to encounter, to meet with 認める (みとめる) N3 Ichidan Verb to recognize, to acknowledge 結ぶ (むすぶ) N3 Godan Verb to tie, to bind 担う (になう) N1 Godan Verb to carry, to bear 負う (おう) N1 Godan Verb to bear, to take on 考える (かんがえる) N4 Ichidan Verb to think, to consider 扱う (あつかう) N3 Godan Verb to handle, to deal with 拘わる (かかわる) N2 Godan Verb to be involved in, to be concerned with 踏まえる (ふまえる) N1 Ichidan Verb to be based on, to take into account 判断する (はんだんする) N3 Suru Verb to judge, to determine 聞き取る (ききとる) N1 Godan Verb to listen carefully, to hear out 救う (すくう) N2 Godan Verb to save, to rescue つながる N3 Godan Verb to be connected, to lead to Grammar and Sentence Structure 形式的にはフリーランスだが、実態は労働者と変わらない「偽装フリーランス」の問題をめぐり、品川労働基準監督署（東京都）が、都内の会社と業務委託契約を結ぶフリーカメラマンの男性（40）が通勤中に遭った交通事故を労災と認定したことがわかった。</description></item><item><title>「明らかに異常」「情けない」　副大臣辞任の神田氏、地元からも批判</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/clearly-abnormal-pathetic-vice-minister-kanda-who-resigned-criticized-even-in-his-hometown/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/clearly-abnormal-pathetic-vice-minister-kanda-who-resigned-criticized-even-in-his-hometown/</guid><description>辞任を表明した神田憲次財務副大臣=2023年11月13日午後3時27分、東京都千代田区の財務省、東谷晃平撮影 Link to the original article
過去かこの税金ぜいきん滞納たいのうと差し押さしおさえなどが問題もんだいとなっていた自民党じみんとう衆院しゅういん議員ぎいんで財務ざいむ副大臣ふくだいじんの神田かんだ憲次けんじ氏し（60）=愛知あいち5区く=が13日にち、副大臣ふくだいじんを辞任じにんした。愛知あいち県けん内ないからは厳きびしい声こえが相次あいついだ。 「国民こくみんに納税のうぜいの義務ぎむをお願おねがいし、それを執行しっこうする任にんにあたるあたるものとして許ゆるされざること。4回かいも滞納たいのうしたというのは明あきらかに異常いじょうで、意図的いとてきだったと捉そくえられても仕方しかたない」 愛知県あいちけんの大村秀章おおむらひであき知事ちじはこの日ひの記者会見きしゃかいけんで財務ざいむ副大臣ふくだいじんとしての職務しょくむについて触ふれ、こう述のべた。大村知事ちじは9日にちに財務ざいむ省しょうで神田かんだ氏と面会めんかいし、中部ちゅうぶ空港くうこう第2滑走路かっそうろの整備せいびに向むけた協力きょうりょくを要請ようせいする予定よていだったが、急きゅうきょ中止ちゅうしになった。前日ぜんじつに財務ざいむ省しょうからキャンセルきゃんせるの連絡れんらくを受うけたと明あきかし、「理由りゆうは聞きいていない。報道ほうどうが流ながれたあとだったので仕方しかたがないのかなと（思おもった）」とも話はなした。 名古屋市のの河村かわむらたかしたかし市長しちょうは13日にち、記者団きしゃだんに対たいし「しがみつきしがみつきたかったんだろうけど、辞やめないといけないに決きまっている」と述のたまべた。 河村市長かわむらしちょうは神田氏かんだしが税金ぜいきんを4回かい滞納たいのうしていたことについて「商売しょうばいで失敗しっぱいして滞納たいのうすることはあるが、4回かい定期的ていきてきに滞納たいのうしていることは説明せつめいしないといけない。本当ほんとうのことを言いったらどうだ」と話はなしした。 自民党じみんとう愛知あいち県けん連れん会長の丹羽にわ秀樹ひでき衆院しゅういん議員は「誠まことに遺憾いかん。本人ほんにんがしっかり説明せつめい責任せきにんを果はたすべきだ」と取材しゅざいに話はなした。 ある自民じみん県議けんぎは「財務ざいむ副ふく大臣だいじんが税金ぜいきん滞納たいのうとは、情なさけない限かぎりだ。『身体検査しんたいけんさ』が機能きのうしていないのではないか」と話はなしした。 神田氏かんだしは文春ぶんしゅんオンラインおんらいんの報道ほうどうを受うけ、9日にち、参院さんいん財政ざいせい金融きんゆう委員会いいんかいで、自身じしんが代表だいひょう取締役とりしまりやくの会社かいしゃが保有ほゆうする土地とちと建物たてものが固定資産税こていしさんぜいの滞納たいのうで過去かこに4度ど、差さし押おさえを受うけていたことを明あきらかにしている。（三宅みやけ梨紗子りさこ、寺沢てらさわ知海ともみ、松島まつしま研人けんと） Vocabulary Word JLPT Level Part of Speech Meaning 滞納 (たいのう) N2 Noun delinquency 問題 (もんだい) N5 Noun problem 辞任 (じにん) N1 Noun resignation 職務 (しょくむ) N2 Noun duties 記者 (きしゃ) N3 Noun reporter 記者会見 (きしゃかいけん) N1 Noun press conference 知事 (ちじ) N3 Noun governor 市長 (しちょう) N4 Noun mayor 記者団 (きしゃだん) N1 Noun press corps 滞納する (たいのうする) N2 Verb (する) to default 聞く (きく) N5 Verb (う-verb) to ask, to hear 話す (はなす) N5 Verb (う-verb) to speak 対する (たいする) N2 Verb (する) to face, to confront 捉える (とらえる) N2 Verb (る-verb) to perceive 仕方がない (しかたがない) N3 Adjective it can&amp;rsquo;t be helped 思う (おもう) N5 Verb (う-verb) to think 辞める (やめる) N5 Verb (る-verb) to quit 決まる (きまる) N4 Verb (る-verb) to be decided 話す (はなす) N5 Verb (う-verb) to speak 話す (はなす) N5 Verb (う-verb) to speak 話す (はなす) N5 Verb (う-verb) to speak 話す (はなす) N5 Verb (う-verb) to speak 話す (はなす) N5 Verb (う-verb) to speak 話す (はなす) N5 Verb (う-verb) to speak 話す (はなす) N5 Verb (う-verb) to speak 話す (はなす) N5 Verb (う-verb) to speak 話す (はなす) N5 Verb (う-verb) to speak 話す (はなす) N5 Verb (う-verb) to speak 話す (はなす) N5 Verb (う-verb) to speak 話す (はなす) N5 Verb (う-verb) to speak Grammar and Sentence Structure 「4回も滞納したというのは明らかに異常で、意図的だったと捉えられても仕方ない」</description></item><item><title>執拗なクレーム「かえってクマとの共存妨げる」　学会が緊急声明</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/persistent-complaint-hinders-coexistence-with-bears-prompts-urgent-statement-from-the-academic-society/</link><pubDate>Sun, 12 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/persistent-complaint-hinders-coexistence-with-bears-prompts-urgent-statement-from-the-academic-society/</guid><description>ツキノワグマの出没に注意を呼びかける看板=秋田県北秋田市 Link to the original article
北海道ほっかいどうと本州ほんしゅうで相次あいつぐクマくまの出没しゅつぼつと被害ひがいについて、「野生やせい生物せいぶつと社会しゃかい」学会がっかいは12日にち、要因よういんや対策たいさくなどに関するかんする緊急声明せいめいを出だした。自治体じちたいなどに電話でんわをしつこくかけて捕獲ほかくへの抗議こうぎを続つづけるような行為こういについては「かえって共存きょうぞんを妨さまたげる」として、対策たいさくの必要性ひつようせいへの理解りかいを求もとめた。 環境かんきょう省しょうのまとめでは、2023年度ねんどは10月がつ末時点じてんでヒグマひぐまとツキノワグマつきのわぐまによる人身じんしん被害ひがいは180人にんで、統計とうけいを取とり始はじめて以来いらい最多さいた。死者ししゃも5人にんに上のぼり、その後ごも被害ひがいが続つづいている。 声明ではこの秋あきの大量たいりょう出没しゅつぼつについて「直接ちょくせつの要因よういんは、ブナぶな科か堅果かんか類るい（どんぐりどんぐり）の大凶作だいきょうさく」としつつ、これまで数年すうねんおきに大量たいりょう出没しゅつぼつはあり、その規模きぼも大おおきくなってきたと指摘してき。過去かこ10年ねんほどの間あいだに個体数こたいすうが増ふえたり、分布ぶんぷ域いきが広ひろがったりして、市街地しがいちの近ちかくにすむクマくまも増ふえ、集落しゅうらくの放置ほうちされたカキかきなどに味あじをしめたことや、00年ねん以降は捕獲ほかくが抑おさえられてきたことも大おおきいとした。 被害ひがいを防ふせぐにはまず、市街地しがいち周辺しゅうへんでの捕獲ほかくを進すすめることや、不要ふような果樹かじゅを伐採ばっさいしてクマくまを引ひきつけるエサえさを取とり除のぞくことが必要ひつようだとした。その上うえで中ちゅう・長期ちょうき的には、人ひととのトラブルとらぶるを減へらしつつ、クマくまも個体群こたいぐんが維持いじできるような分布範囲ぶんぷはんい、個体数こたいすうに向むけた管理かんりや、管理かんりや被害ひがいの予測よそくに必要ひつようなデータでーたの蓄積ちくぞくといった対策たいさくを早急そうきゅうに検討けんとうするよう求もとめた。 また、対策たいさくにあたるあたる人ひとたちへの配慮はいりょも要望ようぼう。一部では、捕獲ほかくに関わったかかわった行政ぎょうせいの窓口まどぐちなどに大量たいりょうのクレームくれーむや中傷ちゅうしょうのような抗議こうぎが寄せられているよせられていることも報じられているほうじられている。 声明は、クマくまについて「付き合い方つきあいかたを間違まちがえれば人命じんめいを奪うばうこともあり、一定いってい数すうの捕獲ほかくは欠かかせない」とし、「関係者かんけいしゃへの配慮はいりょの無ない電話でんわや執拗しつよう（しつようしつよう）なクレームくれーむは、関係者かんけいしゃの努力どりょくをくじき、かえってクマくまとの共存きょうぞんを妨さまたげる結果けっかを招まねく」と訴うったえた。 緊急きんきゅう声明せいめいをまとめまとめた同学会どうがっかい行政ぎょうせい部会ぶかい長ちょうの横山よこやま真弓まゆみ・兵庫ひょうご県立けんりつ大だい教授きょうじゅ（野生やせい動物どうぶつ管理かんり学がく）は「中傷ちゅうしょうで傷きずついている職員しょくいんらも少すくなくないと聞きき、危機きき感かんを覚おぼえている。対策たいさくの現場げんばでは、共存きょうぞんに向むけた苦渋くじゅうの選択せんたくが行おこなわれていることを理解りかいして欲ほしい。人ひとをしっかりしっかり守まもって初はじめてクマくまも守まもれる」と話はなしした。 緊急きんきゅう声明せいめいは学会がっかいのページぺーじ（http://wildlife-humansociety.org/わいるど・ひゅーまんそさいえてぃー・どっと・おーるぐ）から読よめる。（小坪こつぼ遊ゆう） Vocabulary Word (Furigana) JLPT Level Part of Speech Meaning 出没 (しゅつぼつ) N1 Noun appearance, occurrence 被害 (ひがい) N3 Noun damage, harm 要因 (よういん) N2 Noun cause, factor 対策 (たいさく) N2 Noun countermeasure, solution 緊急 (きんきゅう) N2 Noun emergency 声 (こえ) N4 Noun voice 捕獲 (ほかく) N1 Noun capture, capture 抗議 (こうぎ) N2 Noun protest, objection 共存 (きょうそん) N1 Noun coexistence 理解 (りかい) N3 Noun understanding 人身 (じんしん) N1 Noun personal injury 死者 (ししゃ) N2 Noun deceased person, casualty 要する (ようする) N2 Verb (Godan) to require, to demand 指摘 (してき) N2 Verb (Suru) to point out, to indicate 増える (ふえる) N4 Verb (Ichidan) to increase, to grow 広がる (ひろがる) N3 Verb (Godan) to spread, to extend 味をしめる (あじをしめる) N1 Verb (Godan) to get a taste for, to develop a liking for 抑える (おさえる) N3 Verb (Ichidan) to suppress, to control 防ぐ (ふせぐ) N3 Verb (Godan) to prevent, to protect 進める (すすめる) N3 Verb (Ichidan) to advance, to promote 伐採 (ばっさい) N1 Verb (Suru) logging, felling 引きつける (ひきつける) N2 Verb (Ichidan) to attract, to draw 取り除く (とりのぞく) N3 Verb (Godan) to remove, to take away 維持 (いじ) N2 Verb (Suru) maintenance, preservation 向ける (むける) N3 Verb (Ichidan) to turn towards, to dedicate to 管理 (かんり) N3 Verb (Suru) management, control 蓄積 (ちくせき) N1 Verb (Suru) accumulation, storing up 検討 (けんとう) N2 Verb (Suru) consideration, examination 配慮 (はいりょ) N2 Noun consideration, thoughtfulness 傷つく (きずつく) N2 Verb (Godan) to get hurt, to be wounded 聞く (きく) N4 Verb (Godan) to hear, to listen 覚える (おぼえる) N4 Verb (Ichidan) to remember, to memorize 理解 (りかい) N3 Noun understanding Grammar and Sentence Structure Sentence 1:</description></item><item><title>歌手の大橋純子さん死去　73歳、「シルエット・ロマンス」</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/singer-junko-ohashi-dies-at-73-known-for-silhouette-romance/</link><pubDate>Sat, 11 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/singer-junko-ohashi-dies-at-73-known-for-silhouette-romance/</guid><description>大橋純子さん=2007年撮影 Link to the original article
「シルエット・ロマンスしるえっと・ろまんす」などのヒットひっと曲きょくで知しられる歌手かしゅの大橋純子おおはし・じゅんこ（おおはし・じゅんこおおはし・じゅんこ）さんが9日にち、死去しきょした。73歳さいだった。食道しょくどうがんの再発さいはつで3月がつから活動かつどうを休止きゅうししていた。通夜つやは15日にち午後ごご6時じ、葬儀そうぎは16日にち午後ごご1時じから、東京とうきょう都と港区みなとく芝公園しばこうえん4の7の35の増上寺ぞうじょうじで。 北海道ほっかいどう夕張市ゆうばりし出身しゅっしん。1974年ねんにデビューでびゅうし、77年ねんに「大橋純子おおはしじゅんこ＆美乃家みのやセントラル・ステイションせんとらる・すていしょん」として出だした「シンプル・ラブしんぷる・らぶ」がヒットひっと。その後も「たそがれたそがれマイ・ラブらぶ」（78年ねん）や、日本にほんレコードれこーど大賞たいしょう最優秀さいゆうしゅう歌唱かしょう賞しょうを受賞じゅしょうした「シルエット・ロマンスしるえっと・ろまんす」（81年ねん）など、力強ちからづよく伸のびやかな歌声うたごえで脚光かっこうを浴あびた。 Vocabulary Word (Furigana) JLPT Level Part of Speech Meaning 知られる (しられる) N3 Verb to be known 死去する (しきょする) N1 Verb to pass away 再発する (さいはつする) N2 Verb to relapse 休止する (きゅうしする) N1 Verb to suspend 通夜 (つや) N2 Noun wake 葬儀 (そうぎ) N2 Noun funeral 出身 (しゅっしん) N3 Noun origin デビューする N3 Verb to debut 伸びやかな (のびやかな) N1 Adjective flexible 脚光を浴びる (きゃっこうをあびる) N1 Verb to be in the limelight ヒット (ひっと) N3 Noun hit 力強い (ちからづよい) N3 Adjective powerful 美しい (うつくしい) N5 Adjective beautiful 暗い (くらい) N5 Adjective dark 暖かい (あたたかい) N5 Adjective warm 高い (たかい) N5 Adjective high 低い (ひくい) N5 Adjective low 速い (はやい) N5 Adjective fast 遅い (おそい) N5 Adjective slow 新しい (あたらしい) N5 Adjective new 古い (ふるい) N5 Adjective old 静かな (しずかな) N5 Adjective quiet 美味しい (おいしい) N5 Adjective delicious 早い (はやい) N5 Adjective early 遠い (とおい) N5 Adjective far 近い (ちかい) N5 Adjective close 早く (はやく) N5 Adverb quickly 静かに (しずかに) N5 Adverb quietly 美しく (うつくしく) N5 Adverb beautifully Grammar and Sentence Structure 通夜は15日午後6時、葬儀は16日午後1時から、東京都港区芝公園4の7の35の増上寺で。</description></item><item><title>宝塚歌劇団員死亡、遺族側が会見　長時間労働とパワハラが原因と主張</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/a-member-of-the-takarazuka-revue-has-died-and-the-bereaved-family-claims-in-a-press-conference-that-the-cause-was-long-working-hours-and-power-harassment/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/a-member-of-the-takarazuka-revue-has-died-and-the-bereaved-family-claims-in-a-press-conference-that-the-cause-was-long-working-hours-and-power-harassment/</guid><description>記者会見する遺族代理人の川人博弁護士（左）と井上耕史弁護士=2023年11月10日午後3時2分、東京都千代田区、片田貴也撮影 Link to the original article
宝塚歌劇団たからづかかげきだん（兵庫県ひょうごけん宝塚市たからづかし）の劇団員げきだんいんの女性じょせい（25）が9月末に死亡しぼうした問題で、遺族いぞくの代理人だいりにん弁護士べんごしが10日、東京都とうきょうと内で記者会見きしゃかいけんを開ひらいた。死亡の原因げんいんが過度かどな長時間ちょうじかん労働ろうどうとパワーハラスメントぱわーはらすめんとだったとして、歌劇団かげきだんと運営うんえいする阪急電鉄はんきゅうでんてつに対たいして事実じじつに基もとづく謝罪しゃざいと適切てきせつな補償ほしょうを求もとめていくことを明あきらかにした。 女性じょせいは9月がつ30日にち朝、宝塚市たからづかしの自宅じたくマンションまんしょんの敷地しきち内で倒たおれて亡なくなっているところを発見はっけんされた。兵庫県警けい宝塚署しょは自殺じさつの可能性かのうせいが高たかいとみている。 弁護士べんごしによると、女性じょせいは入団にゅうだん7年目ねんめで、下級生かきゅうせいの責任者せきにんしゃの長ちょうの役割やくわりを担になっていた。8人にんいた同期生どうきせいは退団たいだんなどで2人にんにまで減へっており、下級生かきゅうせいのまとめ役まとめやくとしても極きわめて過重かじゅうな業務ぎょうむだったという。 公演こうえんの稽古けいこなどで、亡なくなるまでの約やく1カ月間かげつかんの時間外じかんがい労働ろうどう時間が250時間じかんを超こえていたと指摘してき。また、2021年ねん8月がつに上級生じょうきゅうせいからヘアアイロンへああいろんを額ひたいに当あてられ、やけどやけどを負おったほか、上級生じょうきゅうせいから何度なんども暴言ぼうげんを受うけるなどパワハラぱわはらがあったと主張しゅちょうした。 会見かいけんでは「常軌じょうきを逸いっした長時間労働ちょうじかんろうどうにより、娘むすめを過度かどの過労かろう状態じょうたいにおきながら、見みて見みぬ振ふりをしてきた劇団げきだんが責任せきにんを認みとめ謝罪しゃざいすること、パワハラぱわはらを行おこなった上級生じょうきゅうせいが責任せきにんを認みとめ謝罪しゃざいすることを求もとめる」などとした遺族いぞくのコメントコメントが配くばられた。 歌劇団かげきだんは女性じょせいの死亡しぼうを受うけて今年ことし10月がつ、外部がいぶの弁護士べんごしらでつくる調査ちょうさチームを発足ほっそくさせ、女性じょせいの劇団げきだん内での状況じょうきょうや亡なくなるに至いたった背景はいけいについて内部ないぶへの聞きき取とり調査ちょうさをすると表明ひょうめいした。女性じょせいをめぐっては、週刊しゅうかん文春ぶんしゅんが今年ことし2月がつ、先輩せんぱいの劇団げきだん員いんから「いじめ」を受うけたとする記事きじを掲載けいさい。一方いっぽう、こうした事実じじつについて歌劇団かげきだん側がわは「『いじめ』と認みとめられる事実じじつはなかった」と認識にんしきしているとしていた。（楢崎ならさき貴司たかし） 9く月がつ末にに死亡ぼうした宝たから塚づか歌劇げき団劇けき団員いんの女じょ性せい（25）の遺い族ぞくの代だい理り人にん弁べん護ご士しが開ひらいたいた会見けんを受うけて、歌か劇げき団と事じ業ぎょう主しゅの阪はん急きゅう電でん鉄てつはそれぞれコメントを出だした。 歌劇団かげきだんは「宝塚歌劇団たからづかかげきだん」として大変重く受け止めており、ご遺族に対して誠実に対応して参りたい。今後、外部弁護士による調査結果をふまえて真摯しんしに対応して参る所存です」とコメント。阪急電鉄も「阪急電鉄としても、大変重く受け止めております」とコメントした。 Vocabulary Word JLPT Level Part of Speech Meaning 死亡 (しぼう) N3 Noun death 遺族 (いぞく) N2 Noun bereaved family 代理人 (だいりにん) N2 Noun agent, representative 弁護士 (べんごし) N3 Noun lawyer 記者 (きしゃ) N3 Noun reporter 会見 (かいけん) N3 Noun press conference 過度 (かど) N1 Noun excess, immoderation 長時間 (ちょうじかん) N2 Noun long hours 労働 (ろうどう) N3 Noun labor, work パワーハラスメント N1 Noun power harassment 事実 (じじつ) N3 Noun fact, truth 基づく (もとづく) N2 Verb (godan) to be based on 謝罪 (しゃざい) N2 Noun apology 適切 (てきせつ) N2 Noun appropriate 補償 (ほしょう) N2 Noun compensation 倒れる (たおれる) N3 Verb (ichidan) to collapse, to fall 発見 (はっけん) N3 Noun discovery 自殺 (じさつ) N3 Noun suicide 代わりに (かわりに) N2 Adverb instead, in place of 責任者 (せきにんしゃ) N2 Noun person in charge 役割 (やくわり) N3 Noun role, function 担う (になう) N2 Verb (godan) to take on, to bear 退団 (たいだん) N1 Noun leaving an organization 業務 (ぎょうむ) N2 Noun business, duties 稽古 (けいこ) N2 Noun practice, training 指摘 (してき) N2 Noun pointing out, identification 暴言 (ぼうげん) N1 Noun verbal abuse 配る (くばる) N2 Verb (godan) to distribute 過労 (かろう) N1 Noun overwork 状況 (じょうきょう) N3 Noun situation, circumstances 聞き取り (ききとり) N2 Noun interviewing, questioning 認める (みとめる) N2 Verb (ichidan) to acknowledge, to admit 認識 (にんしき) N2 Noun recognition, awareness 調査 (ちょうさ) N3 Noun investigation, survey 真摯 (しんし) N1 Adjective (な) sincere, earnest 対応 (たいおう) N2 Noun response, coping 所存 (しょぞん) N1 Noun intention, belief 受け止める (うけとめる) N2 Verb (ichidan) to take in, to accept Grammar and Sentence Structure また、2021年8月に上級生からヘアアイロンを額に当てられ、やけどを負ったほか、上級生から何度も暴言を受けるなどパワハラがあったと主張した。 Grammatical points:</description></item><item><title>「議員の職務が忙しくて」　神田財務副大臣、税金滞納問題で答弁</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/because-the-duties-of-a-member-of-the-diet-are-busy-kanda-the-vice-minister-of-finance-responded-to-the-issue-of-tax-delinquency/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/because-the-duties-of-a-member-of-the-diet-are-busy-kanda-the-vice-minister-of-finance-responded-to-the-issue-of-tax-delinquency/</guid><description>参院財政金融委員会で、共産党の小池晃書記局長の質問に答弁する神田憲次財務副大臣=2023年11月9日午後2時18分、岩下毅撮影 Link to the original article
自民党じみんとう衆院しゅういん議員ぎいんの神田憲次かんだけんじ財務ざいむ副大臣ふくだいじん（60）の会社かいしゃが過去かこに地方税ちほうぜいを滞納たいのうし差し押さえさしおさえを受けうけていた問題もんだいで、神田かんだ氏は9日にち午後ごご、参院さんいん財政ざいせい金融きんゆう委員会いいんかいで「議員ぎいんの職務しょくむが忙いそがしくなる中なかで、郵便物ゆうびんもつを見みることが遅おくれた」「督促状とくそくじょうをあまたある書類しょるいの中なかから発見はっけんした時ときには納付のうふした」などと答弁とうべんした。 神田かんだ氏はこの日午前の質疑で、自身が代表取締役となっている会社の土地と建物が固定資産税の滞納により過去に4度、差し押さえを受けていたことを明らかにしている。8日に文春オンラインが報じた内容を認めたものだ。 午後ごごの質疑しつぎでは、共産党きょうさんとうの小池晃こいけあきら氏が追及ついきゅう。繰り返し差し押さえさしおさえを受うけている点てんから「忘わすれたとか間違まちがいで済すむ話はなしではない。確信犯かくしんはん的に納税のうぜいをしなかったと見みられても仕方しかたがない」とただすと、「議員ぎいんの職務しょくむが忙いそがしくなる中なかで、郵便物ゆうびんぶつを見みることなく時間じかんが徒過とかしてしまった。結果けっかとして郵便物ゆうびんぶつを見みることが遅おくれ、という経緯いきさつで差し押さえさしおさえを受うけているという事実じじつが発覚はっかくした」などと説明せつめいした。 小池氏こいけしは「国会議員こっかいぎいんだから忙しくて見なかった。そんな言い訳が通用すると思っているのか。国会議員こっかいぎいんだからこそ、納税のうぜいの義務ぎむを真っ先に果たさなければいけないのではないか」と批判した。（松山尚幹まつやまなおみき） Vocabulary Word (Furigana) JLPT Level Part of Speech Meaning 神田 (かんだ) N/A Noun kanda 憲次 (けんじ) N/A Noun kenji 財務 (ざいむ) N/A Noun finance 副大臣 (ふくだいじん) N/A Noun vice minister 会社 (かいしゃ) N/A Noun company 過去 (かこ) N/A Noun past 地方税 (ちほうぜい) N/A Noun local tax 滞納 (たいのう) N/A Noun non-payment 差し押さえ (さしおさえ) N/A Noun seizure 問題 (もんだい) N/A Noun problem 受ける (うける) N/A Verb (ru-verb) to receive 答弁 (とうべん) N/A Noun answer 代表 (だいひょう) N/A Noun representative 取締役 (とりしまりやく) N/A Noun director 土地 (とち) N/A Noun land 建物 (たてもの) N/A Noun building 固定資産税 (こていしさんぜい) N/A Noun fixed asset tax 明らかにする (あきらかにする) N/A Verb (suru-verb) to reveal 質疑 (しつぎ) N/A Noun questioning 追及 (ついきゅう) N/A Noun pursuit 繰り返し (くりかえし) N/A Adverb repeatedly 確信犯的 (かくしんはんてき) N/A Adjective deliberate 納税 (のうぜい) N/A Noun tax payment 結果 (けっか) N/A Noun result 経緯 (けいい) N/A Noun details 発覚 (はっかく) N/A Noun discovery 批判 (ひはん) N/A Noun criticism 義務 (ぎむ) N/A Noun obligation 真っ先に (まっさきに) N/A Adverb first of all Grammar and Sentence Structure 「議員の職務が忙しくなる中で、郵便物を見ることが遅れた」などと答弁した。</description></item><item><title>ガザ戦闘は「人道的休止」を　G7外相会合が共同声明へ</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/the-gaza-conflict-will-be-included-in-the-joint-statement-of-the-g7-foreign-ministers-meeting-as-a-humanitarian-pause/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/the-gaza-conflict-will-be-included-in-the-joint-statement-of-the-g7-foreign-ministers-meeting-as-a-humanitarian-pause/</guid><description>先進7カ国（G7）外相会合に臨む（中央奥から時計回りに）上川陽子外相、カナダのジョリー外相、フランスのコロナ外相、イタリアのタヤーニ外相、欧州連合のボレル外交安保上級代表、英国のクレバリー外相、ドイツのベアボック外相、米国のブリンケン国務長官=2023年11月8日午前9時42分、外務省飯倉公館、代表撮影 Link to the original article
主要しゅよう7カ国かこく（G7）外相がいしょう会合は8日にち、東京とうきょうでの2日間にちかんの日程にっていを終おえ、イスラムいすらむ組織そしきハマスとイスラエルいすらえるの軍事ぐんじ衝突しょうとつによるパレスチナぱれすちな自治区じちくガザ地区ちくの人道じんどう状況じょうきょうの悪化あっかを受うけ、戦闘せんとうの「人道的じんどうてき休止きゅうし」を求もとめる共同きょうどう声明せいめいを発表はっぴょうする。 議長ぎちょうとして記者会見きしゃかいけんした上川陽子うえかわ ようこ外相がいしょうによると、G7外相がいしょうは「人質ひとじちの即時そくじ解放かいほう」や「ガザがざの人道じんどう危機ききに対処たいしょするための緊急きんきゅう行動こうどう」の必要性ひつようせいで一致いっち。イスラエルと独立どくりつしたパレスチナぱれすちな国家こっかが共存きょうぞんする「2国家こっか解決かいけつ」に向けむけた取り組みとりくみなどを確認かくにんした。 ロシアろしあによるウクライナうくらいな侵攻こうをめぐっては「結束けっそくして厳きびしい対たいロろ制裁せいさいや強きょう力りょくなウクライナうくらいな支援に取とり組くむ姿勢しせいは不変ふへん」とした。 海洋かいよう進出しんしゅつや軍備ぐんび増強ぞうきょうを進めるすすめる中国ちゅうごくに対しては「率直そっちょくに関与かんよし、我々われわれの懸念けねんを直接ちょくせつ表明ひょうめいすることが重要じゅうよう」と指摘してきしつつ、「グローバルぐろーばるな課題かだいや共通きょうつうの関心かんしん部分ぶぶんについて協働きょうどうする必要ひつようがある」との立場たちばを確認かくにんした。 北きた朝ちょう鮮せんによるによるミサイルみさいる発はっ射しゃややロシアろしあへのへの武ぶ器き供きょう与よを「を「強きょうくく非ひ難なん」ししたた。。日に本ほんがが重じゅう視しするする拉ら致ち問もん題だいについては「については「G7G7各かく国こくからから即そく時じ解かい決けつにに向むけたけた支し持じがが改あらためてめて表ひょう明めいさされたれた」と」とししたた。 上川うえかわ外相は共同声明について「G7として従来以上に結束し、連携して様々な課題に対応できるよう、精力的に取り組んだ結果だ」と語った。（長崎ながさき潤一郎） Vocabulary Word JLPT Level Part of Speech Meaning 終える (おえる) N3 Verb to finish 悪化する (あっかする) N3 Verb to worsen 求める (もとめる) N3 Verb to seek 発表する (はっぴょうする) N3 Verb to announce 受ける (うける) N3 Verb to receive 確認する (かくにんする) N3 Verb to confirm 進める (すすめる) N3 Verb to advance 指摘する (してきする) N3 Verb to point out 表明する (ひょうめいする) N3 Verb to express 非難する (ひなんする) N3 Verb to criticize 重視する (じゅうしする) N3 Verb to prioritize 支持する (しじする) N3 Verb to support 語る (かたる) N3 Verb to speak 結束する (けっそくする) N2 Verb to unite 取り組む (とりくむ) N2 Verb to tackle 厳しい (きびしい) N3 い-adjective strict, severe 緊急 (きんきゅう) N2 Noun emergency 即時 (そくじ) N2 Noun immediate 人道的 (じんどうてき) N1 な-adjective humanitarian 独立した (どくりつした) N2 Verb to be independent 共存する (きょうぞんする) N2 Verb to coexist 重要 (じゅうよう) N3 Noun important 直接 (ちょくせつ) N3 Noun directly 確認 (かくにん) N3 Noun confirmation 姿勢 (しせい) N2 Noun stance, attitude 軍事 (ぐんじ) N2 Noun military 戦闘 (せんとう) N2 Noun battle 人質 (ひとじち) N2 Noun hostage 連携 (れんけい) N2 Noun cooperation 課題 (かだい) N2 Noun issue, task Grammar and Sentence Structure 上川陽子外相によると、G7 外相は「人質の即時解放」や「ガザの人道危機に対処するための緊急行動」の必要性で一致。</description></item><item><title>インドの首都、大気汚染でかすむ　WHO基準の100倍近くの日も</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/india-s-capital-is-shrouded-in-air-pollution-with-some-days-exceeding-who-standards-by-nearly-100-times/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/india-s-capital-is-shrouded-in-air-pollution-with-some-days-exceeding-who-standards-by-nearly-100-times/</guid><description>大気汚染が悪化しているインドの首都ニューデリー中心部で、オートリキシャ（三輪タクシー）が通行する先にかすんで見えるインド門=2023年11月7日朝、石原孝撮影 Link to the original article
約やく2千せん万人にんが暮くらすインドインドの首都しゅとニューデリーニューデリーで、大気たいき汚染おせんが深刻しんこく化している。周辺しゅうへん地域ちいきでの野焼のやききや工場こうじょうなどの排ガスはいガスの影響えいきょうで、あたりが白しろく霧きりのようにかすむ日ひが続つづいている。 首都しゅと中心部ちゅうしんぶにある大統領官邸だいとうりょうかんていやインド門いんどもん付近では7日、もやがかかり、数百すうひゃくメートルめーとる先の景色けしきが見みえにくくなっていた。専門家せんもんかはマスクますくの着用ちゃくようなどを促うながしているが、ジョギングじょぎんぐや散歩さんぽをする人ひとで着用ちゃくようしている人ひとはほとんどいなかった。 世界せかい保健ほけん機関きかん（WHO）は、有害ゆうがいな微小びしょう粒子りゅうし状じょう物質ぶっしつPM2・5の濃度のうどについて、年間ねんかん平均へいきん1立方りっぽうメートルめーとる当たり5マイクログラムまいくろぐらむになるよう求もとめている。ただ、現地げんちメディアめでぃあは11月がつに入はいり、「デリーでりーの濃度のうどは、WHO基準きじゅんの100倍ばい近ちかくに上のぼる日ひが出でた」と報ほうじている。 地元じもと政府は大気たいき汚染おせんの悪化あっかや健康けんこう被害ひがいを防ふせぐため、10日にちまで小学校しょうがっこうへの通学つうがくを停止ていしした。建設けんせつ工事こうじの停止ていしや自動車じどうしゃの走行そうこう制限せいげんなども実施じっししているが、効果こうかは限定げんてい的だと言いわれている。 国際こくさい人権じんけん団体だんたいのアムネスティ・インターナショナルあむねすてぃ・いんたーなしょなるは6日、「人々ひとびとの生命せいめいと健康けんこうに対たいする人権じんけんを侵害しんがいする恐おそれがある」などとする声明せいめいを出だし、政府せいふなどに対たいして抜本的ばっぽんてきな改善策かいぜんさくを求もとめた。（ニューデリーにゅーでりー=石原いしはら孝） Vocabulary Word (Furigana) JLPT Level Part of Speech Meaning 深刻 (しんこく) N3 な-adjective serious 影響 (えいきょう) N3 noun influence 続く (つづく) N4 godan verb to continue 中心部 (ちゅうしんぶ) N3 noun downtown area 官邸 (かんてい) N1 noun official residence 近く (ちかく) N4 noun vicinity 見えにくい (みえにくい) N3 い-adjective hard to see 専門家 (せんもんか) N2 noun specialist 着用 (ちゃくよう) N2 noun wearing 散歩 (さんぽ) N4 noun walk 促す (うながす) N2 godan verb to urge 世界 (せかい) N5 noun world 保健 (ほけん) N3 noun health 機関 (きかん) N2 noun organization 有害 (ゆうがい) N2 な-adjective harmful 濃度 (のうど) N2 noun concentration 平均 (へいきん) N3 noun average 求める (もとめる) N3 ichidan verb to seek 基準 (きじゅん) N3 noun standard 停止 (ていし) N3 noun suspension 建設 (けんせつ) N3 noun construction 効果 (こうか) N3 noun effect 限定的 (げんていてき) N1 な-adjective limited 国際 (こくさい) N4 noun international 人権 (じんけん) N3 noun human rights 侵害 (しんがい) N1 noun violation 恐れ (おそれ) N3 noun fear 声明 (せいめい) N2 noun statement 抜本的 (ばっぽんてき) N1 な-adjective fundamental 改善策 (かいぜんさく) N2 noun improvement plan Grammar and Sentence Structure Difficult Sentences 専門家はマスクの着用などを促しているが、ジョギングや散歩をする人で着用している人はほとんどいなかった。 ただ、現地メディアは11月に入り、「デリーの濃度は、WHO基準の100倍近くに上る日が出た」と報じている。 地元政府は大気汚染の悪化や健康被害を防ぐため、10日まで小学校への通学を停止した。 Explanation 専門家はマスクの着用などを促しているが、ジョギングや散歩をする人で着用している人はほとんどいなかった。</description></item><item><title>筒香、来季も米国でプレー　代理人ウルフ氏が明言</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/tsubakuro-will-continue-to-play-in-the-united-states-next-season-agent-mr-wolf-declares/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/tsubakuro-will-continue-to-play-in-the-united-states-next-season-agent-mr-wolf-declares/</guid><description>筒香嘉智 Link to the original article
【スコッツデールすこっつでーる（米べいアリゾナありぞな州）共同きょうどう】今季米べい大リーグりーぐ、ジャイアンツじゃいあんつ傘下のマイナーまいなーでプレーぷれーした筒香嘉智つつがよしの代理人だいりにんウルフうるふ氏が７日にち、アリゾナありぞな州スコッツデールすこっつでーるで取材しゅざいに応おうじ「筒香つつがは日本にほん球界きゅうかいには戻もどらない。来らい春しゅんのキャンプきゃんぷ招待しょうたい選手せんしゅとして、どこかの球団きゅうだんと比較的ひかくてき早はやいうちにマイナーまいなー契約けいやくを結むすべると確信かくしんしている」と来季らいきも米べい国こくでプレーぷれーする見通みとおしを明あきらかにした。 ウルフうるふ氏は、パドレスぱどれすのダルビッシュだるびっしゅ有の代理人も務める。今季終盤に右肘の炎症で離脱したが「状態は良好だ。投球動作を含めた練習を数週間後にはこなす予定だ」と来季開幕へ経過は順調であると語った。（共同） Vocabulary Word (Furigana) JLPT Level Part of Speech Meaning 今季 (こんき) N3 Noun this season 米 (べい) N3 Noun America 大リーグ (だいりーぐ) N3 Noun Major League 傘下 (さんか) N1 Noun under the umbrella マイナー (まいなー) N3 Noun minor league プレー (ぷれー) N3 Verb play 代理人 (だいりにん) N2 Noun agent 取材 (しゅざい) N2 Noun coverage; report 応じる (おうじる) N2 Verb respond 戻る (もどる) N4 Verb return 招待 (しょうたい) N3 Noun invitation 選手 (せんしゅ) N4 Noun player 比較的 (ひかくてき) N2 Adverb relatively 早い (はやい) N5 Adjective early 結ぶ (むすぶ) N4 Verb conclude 確信 (かくしん) N2 Noun conviction 明らかにする (あきらかにする) N2 Verb make clear 離脱 (りだつ) N1 Noun withdrawal 状態 (じょうたい) N3 Noun condition 良好 (りょうこう) N2 Adjective good 投球 (とうきゅう) N1 Noun pitching 動作 (どうさ) N2 Noun movement 含める (ふくめる) N3 Verb include 練習 (れんしゅう) N4 Noun practice 開幕 (かいまく) N2 Noun opening game 経過 (けいか) N2 Noun progress 順調 (じゅんちょう) N2 Adjective favorable 語る (かたる) N3 Verb speak 離脱 (りだつ) N1 Noun withdrawal Grammar and Sentence Structure Sure, here are the three sentences from the article along with explanations:</description></item><item><title>ビートルズの27年ぶり「新曲」ついに発売　「ナウ・アンド・ゼン」</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/the-beatles-first-new-song-in-27-years-finally-released-now-and-then/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/the-beatles-first-new-song-in-27-years-finally-released-now-and-then/</guid><description>11月2日発売予定の「NOW　AND　THEN」 Link to the original article
ビートルズびーとるずの「最後さいごの曲きょく」とされる「ナウ・アンド・ゼンなう・あんど・ぜん」が日本にほん時間じかん2日にち午後ごご11時じにデジタルでじたる配信はいしんで発売はつばいされた。3日にちにはアナログあなろぐ盤ばんも発売はつばいされ、ミュージックビデオみゅーじっくびでおも公開こうかいされる予定よてい。1970年ねん解散かいさんのビートルズびーとるずの名義めいぎで新あたらたな曲きょくが発売はつばいされるのは27年ねんぶりとなる。 「ナウなう・アンド・ゼンぜん」（NowAndThen、『時々ときどき』の意）は「時々ときどき君が恋しくなる」といった詞で、大切たいせつな人への断たちき切れない思いを吐露とろする曲。62年ねんのデビューでびゅー曲「ラヴらぶ・ミー・ドゥ」との両りょうA面めんでの発売はつばいとなった。 ジョンじょん・レノンれのんが生前せいぜんに残のこしたデモでも音源おんげんをもとに、最新さいしん技術ぎじゅつでレノンれのんの声こえをクリアくりあによみがえらせよみがえらせ、現在げんざいのポール・マッカートニーぽーる・まっかーとにーさんやリンゴ・スターりんご・すたーさんの演奏えんそう、ジョージ・ハリソンじょーじ・はりそん（2001年ねん死去しきょ）が95年ねんに録音ろくおんしたギターぎたーなどと合あわせた「新曲しんきょく」として、発売前はつばいまえから話題わだいを呼よんでいた。（野城のしろ千穂ちほ） Vocabulary Word JLPT Level Part of Speech Meaning デジタル (でじたる) N3 Noun digital 配信 (はいしん) N3 Noun distribution 発売 (はつばい) N3 Noun release アナログ (あなろぐ) N3 Noun analog 盤 (ばん) N3 Noun disc 公開 (こうかい) N3 Noun public release 予定 (よてい) N3 Noun plan 解散 (かいさん) N3 Noun dissolution 名義 (めいぎ) N3 Noun name 新た (あらた)な N3 Adjective new 恋 (こい)しい N3 い-adjective dear 吐露 (とろ)する N3 Verb confess デビュー (でびゅー)曲(きょく) N3 Noun debut song 両 (りょう)A 面(めん) N3 Noun double A-side 生前 (せいぜん)に N3 Adverb before one&amp;rsquo;s death 残 (のこ)す N3 Verb leave behind 音源 (おんげん) N3 Noun sound source クリアに N3 Adverb clearly よみがえらせる N3 Verb revive 演奏 (えんそう)する N3 Verb perform 録音 (ろくおん)する N3 Verb record ギター N3 Noun guitar 合 (あ)わせる N3 Verb combine 前 (まえ)から N3 Adverb from before 話題 (わだい) N3 Noun topic 呼 (よ)ぶ N3 Verb call ビートルズ N2 Noun The Beatles 最後 (さいご)の N2 Adjective last 曲 (きょく) N2 Noun song 日本時間 (にほんじかん) N2 Noun Japan time 午後 (ごご) N2 Noun afternoon 11 時 (じ) N2 Noun 11 o&amp;rsquo;clock アンド N2 Noun and 27 年 (にじゅうななねん)ぶり N2 Noun after 27 years 時々 (ときどき) N2 Adverb sometimes 君 (きみ) N2 Noun you 恋 (こい)しい N2 い-adjective dear 詞 (ことば) N2 Noun lyrics 大切 (たいせつ)な N2 な-adjective important 人 (ひと) N2 Noun person 断 (た)ち切(き)れない N2 い-adjective inseparable 思 (おも)い N2 Noun feelings 吐露 (とろ)する N2 Verb confess ラヴ・ミー・ドゥ N2 Noun Love Me Do 両 (りょう)A 面(めん) N2 Noun double A-side 発売 (はつばい)前(まえ) N2 Noun before release ジョン・レノン N1 Noun John Lennon 生前 (せいぜん)に N1 Adverb before one&amp;rsquo;s death 残 (のこ)す N1 Verb leave behind デモ音源 (おんげん) N1 Noun demo sound source 最新 (さいしん)技術(ぎじゅつ) N1 Noun latest technology レノンの声 (こえ) N1 Noun Lennon&amp;rsquo;s voice クリアに N1 Adverb clearly よみがえらせる N1 Verb revive ポール・マッカートニー N1 Noun Paul McCartney リンゴ・スター N1 Noun Ringo Starr 演奏 (えんそう)する N1 Verb perform ジョージ・ハリソン N1 Noun George Harrison 死去 (しきょ)する N1 Verb pass away 録音 (ろくおん)する N1 Verb record ギター N1 Noun guitar 合 (あ)わせる N1 Verb combine 新曲 (しんきょく) N1 Noun new song 発売前 (はつばいまえ) N1 Noun before release 話題 (わだい) N1 Noun topic 呼 (よ)ぶ N1 Verb call Grammar and Sentence Structure Sentence 1: ジョン・レノンが生前に残したデモ音源をもとに、最新技術でレノンの声をクリアによみがえらせ、現在のポール・マッカートニーさんやリンゴ・スターさんの演奏、ジョージ・ハリソン（2001 年死去）が 95 年に録音したギターなどと合わせた「新曲」として、発売前から話題を呼んでいた。</description></item><item><title>せき止め、たん切り薬の増産、24社に要請　厚労相「まだ足りない」</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/the-production-of-cough-suppressants-and-expectorants-is-being-increased-and-the-ministry-of-health-labour-and-welfare-has-requested-24-companies-to-do-so-stating-that-it-is-still-not-enough/</link><pubDate>Sat, 04 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/the-production-of-cough-suppressants-and-expectorants-is-being-increased-and-the-ministry-of-health-labour-and-welfare-has-requested-24-companies-to-do-so-stating-that-it-is-still-not-enough/</guid><description>せき止め薬と去痰（きょたん）薬の増産要請を受ける製薬企業の幹部ら=2023年11月7日、東京・霞が関、藤谷和広撮影 Link to the original article
供給きょうきゅう不足が続くせき止せきどめめ薬くすりやたんを切たんをきる去痰きょたん（きょたんきょたん）薬くすりについて、厚生労働省こうせいろうどうしょうは7日にち、製薬せいやく企業きぎょう24社しゃに増産ぞうさんを要請ようせいした。武見敬三けいぞう厚労相こうろうそうは製薬せいやく企業きぎょうの幹部かんぶと省内しょうないで面会めんかい、今冬こんふゆの感染症かんせんしょうの流行りゅうこうに備そなえ、安定あんてい供給きょうきゅうに向むけた「あらゆる手立てだててを講こうじていただくことを改あらためてお願ねがいしたい」と呼よびかけた。 厚労省こうろうしょうは10月がつにも主要しゅよう8社しゃに対し、増産ぞうさんを要請ようせい。他ほかの医薬品いやくひんの製造せいぞうラインらいんからの融通ゆうつうや在庫ざいこの放出ほうしゅつにより9月がつ末時点じてんから1割わり以上の供給きょうきゅう増ぞうとなる見込みこみだ。だが、医療現場いりょうげんばなどから「薬くすりがまだ足たりない」との声こえが寄よせられており、今冬こんふゆに新型しんがたコロナころなや季節性きせつせいインフルエンザいんふるえんざなどの流行りゅうこうが拡大かくだいするおそれおそれがあることから、幅広はばひろい企業きぎょうを対象たいしょうに改あらためて増産ぞうさんを要請ようせいした。企業きぎょう側がわからは「医薬品いやくひん供給きょうきゅうの責任せきにんを果はたたすために、要請ようせいを踏ふまえできる限かぎりの増産ぞうさんを検討けんとうする」「行政ぎょうせいからの支援しえんもお願ねがいしたい」との意見いけんが出でたという。 政府せいふが2日にちに閣議かくぎ決定けっていした総合そうごう経済けいざい対策たいさくでは、さらなる増産ぞうさんに対応たいおうする企業きぎょうへの支援しえんや、来年度らいねんどの薬価やっか改定かいていでの対忾たいおうを検討けんとうすることが盛もりり込こまれた。（藤谷ふじたに和広かずひろ） Vocabulary Word (Furigana) JLPT Level Part of Speech Meaning 供給 （きょうきゅう） N3 Noun supply, provision 不足 （ふそく） N3 Noun shortage, deficiency 続く （つづく） N4 Verb (godan) to continue, to last せき止める N1 Verb (ru-verb) to dam up, to block 薬 （くすり） N4 Noun medicine たんを切る N1 Verb (ru-verb) to cut phlegm 去痰 （きょたん） N1 Noun expectorant 厚生労働省 （こうせいろうどうしょう） N1 Noun Ministry of Health, Labour and Welfare 製薬企業 （せいやくきぎょう） N1 Noun pharmaceutical company 増産 （ぞうさん） N2 Noun increased production 要請 （ようせい） N2 Noun request, appeal 武見敬三 （たけみけいぞう） N/A Name Keizo Takemi 厚労相 （こうろうそう） N/A Abbreviation Minister of Health, Labour and Welfare 幹部 （かんぶ） N2 Noun management, executive 面会 （めんかい） N2 Noun meeting, interview 感染症 （かんせんしょう） N1 Noun infectious disease 流行 （りゅうこう） N3 Noun trend, prevalence 備える （そなえる） N3 Verb (ru-verb) to prepare, to equip 安定 （あんてい） N3 Noun stability, equilibrium あらゆる N2 Adjective all, every 手立て （てだて） N1 Noun measure, means 講じる （こうじる） N1 Verb (ru-verb) to take measures, to devise 改めて （あらためて） N2 Adverb again, afresh お願い （おねがい） N4 Noun request, favor 10 月 （じゅうがつ） N5 Noun October 主要 （しゅよう） N2 Noun main, principal 融通 （ゆうずう） N1 Noun flexibility, adaptability 在庫 （ざいこ） N2 Noun stock, inventory 放出 （ほうしゅつ） N1 Noun release, emission 見込む （みこむ） N2 Verb (ru-verb) to anticipate, to expect Grammar and Sentence Structure Difficult Sentences 武見敬三厚労相は製薬企業の幹部と省内で面会、今冬の感染症の流行に備え、安定供給に向けた「あらゆる手立てを講じていただくことを改めてお願いしたい」と呼びかけた。</description></item><item><title>ネット上のプライバシーどう守る　小泉進次郎氏ら超党派の議連発足</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/how-to-protect-privacy-online-cross-party-parliamentary-group-launched-including-shunjiro-koizumi/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/how-to-protect-privacy-online-cross-party-parliamentary-group-launched-including-shunjiro-koizumi/</guid><description>超党派議連の会長に就任した自民党の小泉進次郎元環境相=2023年11月2日午前11時9分、国会内、藤原慎一撮影 Link to the original article
インターネットいんたーねっと空間くうかんにおけるプライバシーぷらいばしーのあり方ありかたについて考かんがえる超党派ちょうとうはの議員連盟ぎいんれんめいが2日にち、国会こっかい内で初会合しょかいごうを開ひらいた。公人こうじんや著名人ちょめいじんだけでなく、一般いっぱんの人ひとのプライバシーぷらいばしーが侵害しんがいされるケースけーすがネット上で相次あいついでおり、対応策たいおうさくの検討けんとうを急いそぐとしている。 「ネットしゃかい社会しゃかいにおけるプライバシーぷらいばしーの在あり方かたを考かんがえる議員ぎいん連盟れんめい」の初しょ会合かいごうには与野党よやとうから約やく40人にんが参加さんか。議連ぎれん会長かいちょうの小泉進次郎こいずみしんじろう元もと環境かんきょう相しょうは「正当せいとうな批判ひはんとプライバシーぷらいばしー（の侵害しんがい）が混在こんざいしている」と挨拶あいさつし、一定いっていの規制きせいが必要ひつようとの見解けんかいを示しめした。規制きせいによっては憲法けんぽうが保障ほしょうする表現ひょうげんの自由じゆうが侵おかされる可能性かのうせいもあり、参加さんか者には規制きせいに慎重しんちょうな意見いけんがある。 議連ぎれん顧問こもんには小渕優子こぶちゆうこ・自民党じみんとう選挙対策委員長せんきょたいさくいいんちょうと泉健太いずみけんた・立憲民主党りっけんみんしゅとう代表だいひょうが就ついた。（藤原慎一ふじわらしんいち） Vocabulary Word (Furigana) JLPT Level Part of Speech Meaning 考える (かんがえる) N5 Verb (Ichidan) to think 開く (ひらく) N5 Verb (Godan) to open 侵害する (しんがいする) N3 Verb (する) to violate 相次ぐ (あいつぐ) N3 Verb (Godan) to occur one after another 対応策 (たいおうさく) N3 Noun countermeasure 急ぐ (いそぐ) N4 Verb (Godan) to hurry 在り方 (ありかた) N4 Noun way of being 考える (かんがえる) N4 Verb (Ichidan) to think 侵害される (しんがいされる) N4 Verb (Passive) to be violated 混在する (こんざいする) N4 Verb (する) to coexist 保障する (ほしょうする) N3 Verb (する) to guarantee 侵される (おかされる) N3 Verb (Passive) to be invaded 参加する (さんかする) N3 Verb (する) to participate あいさつする N3 Verb (する) to greet 示す (しめす) N3 Verb (Godan) to indicate 保障する (ほしょうする) N3 Verb (する) to guarantee 侵される (おかされる) N3 Verb (Passive) to be invaded 参加する (さんかする) N3 Verb (する) to participate 示す (しめす) N3 Verb (Godan) to indicate 保障する (ほしょうする) N3 Verb (する) to guarantee 侵される (おかされる) N3 Verb (Passive) to be invaded 参加する (さんかする) N3 Verb (する) to participate 示す (しめす) N3 Verb (Godan) to indicate 保障する (ほしょうする) N3 Verb (する) to guarantee 侵される (おかされる) N3 Verb (Passive) to be invaded 参加する (さんかする) N3 Verb (する) to participate 示す (しめす) N3 Verb (Godan) to indicate 保障する (ほしょうする) N3 Verb (する) to guarantee 侵される (おかされる) N3 Verb (Passive) to be invaded 参加する (さんかする) N3 Verb (する) to participate 示す (しめす) N3 Verb (Godan) to indicate 保障する (ほしょうする) N3 Verb (する) to guarantee 侵される (おかされる) N3 Verb (Passive) to be invaded 参加する (さんかする) N3 Verb (する) to participate 示す (しめす) N3 Verb (Godan) to indicate Grammar and Sentence Structure 「正当な批判とプライバシー（の侵害）が混在している」とあいさつし、一定の規制が必要との見解を示した。 1.</description></item><item><title>最高賞に急逝のチベット監督作「雪豹」、監督賞「正欲」　東京映画祭</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/tibetan-director-s-film-snow-leopard-which-was-awarded-the-top-prize-and-director-s-award-positive-desire-at-the-tokyo-film-festival-passed-away-suddenly/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/tibetan-director-s-film-snow-leopard-which-was-awarded-the-top-prize-and-director-s-award-positive-desire-at-the-tokyo-film-festival-passed-away-suddenly/</guid><description>最高賞の東京グランプリに選ばれた「雪豹」=東京国際映画祭提供 Link to the original article
第36さんじゅうろく回東京国際映画祭とうきょうこくさいえいがさいは1日ついたち、クロージングセレモニーくろーじんぐせれもにーが東京都とうきょうと千代田区ちよだくのTOHOシネマズ日比谷とうほうしねまずひびやで開ひらかれた。最高賞さいこうしょうの東京グランプリとうきょうぐらんぷりには、中国ちゅうごくの高地こうちの村むらを舞台ぶたいに希少動物きしょうどうぶつのユキヒョウゆきひょうをめぐる人間模様にんげんもようをコミカルこみかるに温あたたかく描かいたペマ・ツェテン監督ぺまつぇてんかんとくの「雪豹ゆきひょう」が選えらばれた。ツェテン監督は今年ことし5月ごがつに急逝きゅうせいしている。 他の主な受賞は次の通り。審査委員特別賞しんさいいいんとくべつしょう=「タタミ」（ザル・アミールざるあみーる、ガイ・ナッティブがいなってぃぶ監督）▽監督賞かんとくしょう=岸善幸きしよしゆき（「正欲しょうよく」）▽女優賞じょゆうしょう=ザル・アミールざるあみーる（「タタミたたみ」）▽男優賞だんゆうしょう=ヤスナ・ミルターマスブやすなみるたーますぶ（「ロクサナろくさな」）▽芸術貢献賞げいじゆつこうけんしょう=「ロングショットろんぐしょっと」（ガオ・ポンがおぽん監督）▽観客賞かんきゃくしょう=「正欲しょうよく」（岸善幸きしよしゆき監督） Vocabulary Word (Furigana) JLPT Level Part of Speech Meaning 開かれる (ひらかれる) N3 verb (ichidan) to be held, to be opened 選ばれる (えらばれる) N3 verb (ichidan) to be chosen 描く (かく) N3 verb (godan) to draw, to depict 急逝する (きゅうせいする) N1 verb (irregular) to pass away 受賞する (じゅしょうする) N2 verb (suru) to win a prize 選ぶ (えらぶ) N2 verb (godan) to choose 舞台 (ぶたい) N2 noun stage 描いた (かいた) N2 verb (godan) drew, depicted 温かく (あたたかく) N2 adverb warmly 急逝している (きゅうせいしている) N1 verb (irregular) is passing away 受賞 (じゅしょう) N1 noun winning a prize 選ばれた (えらばれた) N1 verb (ichidan) was chosen 描いた (かいた) N1 verb (godan) drew, depicted 温かく (あたたかく) N1 adverb warmly 開かれた (ひらかれた) N1 verb (ichidan) was held, was opened 舞台 (ぶたい) N1 noun stage 急逝 (きゅうせい) N1 noun passing away 主な (おもな) N3 adjective (な) main, principal 審査委員特別賞 (しんさいいんとくべつしょう) N1 noun special jury prize 監督賞 (かんとくしょう) N1 noun director&amp;rsquo;s award 女優賞 (じょゆうしょう) N1 noun actress award 男優賞 (だんゆうしょう) N1 noun actor award 芸術貢献賞 (げいじゅつこうけんしょう) N1 noun artistic contribution award 観客賞 (かんきゃくしょう) N1 noun audience award 希少動物 (きしょうどうぶつ) N1 noun rare animal 人間模様 (にんげんもよう) N1 noun human drama コミカルに (こみかるに) N1 adverb comically 高地 (こうち) N1 noun highland 雪豹 (ゆきひょう) N1 noun snow leopard 東京国際映画祭 (とうきょうこくさいえいがさい) N1 noun Tokyo International Film Festival 最高賞 (さいこうしょう) N1 noun highest award クロージングセレモニー (くろーじんぐせれもにー) N1 noun closing ceremony Grammar and Sentence Structure ツェテン監督は今年5月に急逝している。</description></item><item><title>「柿食えば……」首相、奈良の柿を試食し恒例の1句　所信表明を引用</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/if-you-eat-persimmons-the-prime-minister-tasted-nara-s-persimmons-and-quoted-the-traditional-one-line-poem-in-his-policy-speech/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/if-you-eat-persimmons-the-prime-minister-tasted-nara-s-persimmons-and-quoted-the-traditional-one-line-poem-in-his-policy-speech/</guid><description>「奈良の柿」PRレディらの表敬訪問を受け、柿を試食する岸田文雄首相=2023年11月1日午後5時43分、首相官邸、岩下毅撮影 Link to the original article
岸田文雄きしだ ふみお首相しゅしょうは1日、官邸かんていで奈良県ならけんの柿かき生産者せいさんしゃらの表敬訪問ひょうけいほうもんを受うけ、同県産どうけんさんの柿かき「平核無ひらたねなし」を試食ししょくした。毎年恒例まいとしこうれいの秋あきの味覚みかくに合あわせた俳句はいくも披露ひろうした。 首相になってになって3度目どめの柿かきの試食ししょくに「俳句はいくを作つくるのが恒例こうれいというのがずっと頭あたまにあって、悩なやんでいた」と話はなし、「柿食かきくえばよりよい明日あすへ奈良ならのまち」と詠よんだ。臨時りんじ国会こっかいで「日本にほん国民こくみんが『明日あすは今日きょうより良よくなる』と信しんじられる時代じだいを実現じつげんする」と訴うったえた所信表明演説しょしんひょうめいえんぜつを引用いんようした。 首相は、昨年さくねんの表敬訪問ひょうけいほうもんの際さいには「柿かき食ええば観光かんこう復活ふっかつ奈良ならのまち」、一昨年おととしは「柿かき食ええばコロナころな打ちち勝つつ奈良のまちならのまち」と詠よんでいる。（木佐貫きさぬき将司まさし） Vocabulary Word (Furigana) JLPT Level Part of Speech Meaning 岸田 (きしだ) N/A Proper noun Kishida (surname) 文雄 (ふみお) N/A Proper noun Fumio (given name) 首相 (しゅしょう) N/A Noun Prime Minister 1日 (ついたち) N/A Noun 1st day of the month 官邸 (かんてい) N/A Noun Official residence 奈良県 (ならけん) N/A Proper noun Nara Prefecture 柿 (かき) N/A Noun Persimmon 柿生産者 (かきせいさんしゃ) N/A Noun Persimmon producer 表敬訪問 (ひょうけいほうもん) N/A Noun Courtesy visit 受ける (うける) N/A Verb (ichidan) To receive 同県 (どうけん) N/A Noun The same prefecture 産 (さん) N/A Suffix Production 平核無 (ひらたねなし) N/A Noun Seedless persimmon 試食 (ししょく) N/A Noun Tasting 毎年 (まいとし) N/A Noun Every year 恒例 (こうれい) N/A Noun Customary 秋 (あき) N/A Noun Autumn 味覚 (みかく) N/A Noun Taste 合わせる (あわせる) N/A Verb (ichidan) To match 俳句 (はいく) N/A Noun Haiku 披露する (ひろうする) N/A Verb (irregular) To present 首相 (しゅしょう) N/A Noun Prime Minister なる (なる) N/A Verb (irregular) To become 3度目 (さんどめ) N/A Noun Third time 作る (つくる) N/A Verb (godan) To make 恒例 (こうれい) N/A Noun Customary 頭 (あたま) N/A Noun Head 悩む (なやむ) N/A Verb (godan) To worry 柿食えば (かきくえば) N/A Phrase If you eat persimmons よりよい (よりよい) N/A Adjective (い-adjective) Better 明日 (あす) N/A Noun Tomorrow 奈良 (なら) N/A Proper noun Nara (city) まち (まち) N/A Noun Town 詠む (よむ) N/A Verb (godan) To compose (poetry) 臨時国会 (りんじこっかい) N/A Noun Extraordinary Diet session 日本国民 (にほんこくみん) N/A Noun Japanese people 信じる (しんじる) N/A Verb (godan) To believe 時代 (じだい) N/A Noun Era 実現する (じつげんする) N/A Verb (suru) To realize 訴える (うったえる) N/A Verb (godan) To appeal 所信表明演説 (しょしんひょうめいえんぜつ) N/A Noun Policy speech 引用する (いんようする) N/A Verb (suru) To quote 昨年 (さくねん) N/A Noun Last year 際 (さい) N/A Suffix On the occasion of 観光 (かんこう) N/A Noun Sightseeing 復活 (ふっかつ) N/A Noun Revival 一昨年 (おととし) N/A Noun The year before last コロナ (ころな) N/A Noun Corona (short for coronavirus) 打ち勝つ (うちかつ) N/A Verb (godan) To overcome 木佐貫 (きさぬき) N/A Proper noun Kisanuki (surname) 将司 (しょうじ) N/A Proper noun Shoji (given name) Grammar and Sentence Structure Sentence 1: 「柿食えばよりよい明日へ奈良のまち」と詠んだ。</description></item><item><title>木原防衛相「私は衆院議員。参院で発言控える」　教育勅語の持論巡り</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/defense-minister-kihara-i-am-a-member-of-the-house-of-representatives-i-will-refrain-from-making-statements-in-the-house-of-councillors-regarding-his-personal-views-on-the-imperial-rescript-on-education/</link><pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/defense-minister-kihara-i-am-a-member-of-the-house-of-representatives-i-will-refrain-from-making-statements-in-the-house-of-councillors-regarding-his-personal-views-on-the-imperial-rescript-on-education/</guid><description>参院予算委員会で、立憲民主党の杉尾秀哉氏の質問に答弁する木原稔防衛相=2023年10月31日午後3時37分、国会内、上田幸一撮影 Link to the original article
木原稔きはら みのる防衛相ぼうえいしょうは31日の参院さんいん予算委員会よさんいいんかいで、過去かこの教育勅語きょういくちょくごに関かんする自身じしんの発言はつげんについて認識にんしきを問とわれ、「10年以上ねんいじょう前まえの、大臣だいじん就任しゅうにん前まえの政治家せいじかとしての発言はつげん。閣僚かくりょうの立場たちばでお答こたえすることは控ひかえたい」などと述のべ、審議しんぎが紛糾ふんきゅうする一幕ひとまくがあった。立憲民主党りっけんみんしゅとうの杉尾秀哉すぎお ひでや氏しの質問しつもんに答こたえた。 木原きはら氏は2012年2月に自身のホームページに「教育勅語きょういくちょっこの廃止はいしで道義大国どうぎだいこく日本の根幹こんかんを失うしなってしまいました」「日本人にほんじんが自主憲法じしゅけんぽうを創つくることこそが真しんの主権回復しゅけんかいふく」などと記載きさい。杉尾すぎお氏は「持論じろんに変かわりはないか」とただした。 木原きはら氏は「衆院議員しゅういんぎいんとしての私わたしの発言はつげんを、参院さんいんの予算委員会よさんいいんかいで私わたしがお話はなししすることも含ふくめ、閣僚かくりょうの立場たちばでお答こたえすることは差さし控ひかえたい」と語かたった。審議しんぎが紛糾ふんきゅうすると「起草者きそうしゃが私わたしの地元じもと・熊本くまもとの偉人いじんでもあり、そういう観点かんてんから教育勅語きょういくちょくごについてはそういう評価ひょうかをしている」と説明せつめいした。 また杉尾氏すぎおしが、「大臣だいじんの議員会館ぎいんかいかんの部屋へやには、教育勅語きょういくちょっこが額がくに入いれて飾かざってあっあったそうだが、今いまもそうか」と尋たずねると、「今いまの時点じてんでは飾かざっていない」と述のべた。 教育勅語きょういくちょくごは戦後せんご、日本国憲法にほんこくけんぽうと相いれないあいいれないとして、国会こっかいで排除はいじょ・失効しっこうが決議けつぎされている。（小林圭こばやしけい） Vocabulary Word (Furigana) JLPT Level Part of Speech Meaning 防衛 (ぼうえい) N3 Noun defense 参院 (さんいん) N3 Noun House of Councillors 予算委員会 (よさんいいんかい) N3 Noun budget committee 過去 (かこ) N4 Noun past 教育勅語 (きょういくちょくご) N1 Noun Imperial Rescript on Education 発言 (はつげん) N3 Noun statement 認識 (にんしき) N3 Noun recognition 10年以上前 (じゅうねんいじょうまえ) N2 Noun more than 10 years ago 大臣 (だいじん) N3 Noun minister 就任前 (しゅうにんまえ) N2 Noun before taking office 政治家 (せいじか) N3 Noun politician 閣僚 (かくりょう) N2 Noun cabinet member 立憲民主党 (りっけんみんしゅとう) N2 Noun Constitutional Democratic Party 質問 (しつもん) N4 Noun question 自身 (じしん) N3 Noun oneself 発言 (はつげん) N3 Noun statement 過去 (かこ) N4 Noun past 教育勅語 (きょういくちょくご) N1 Noun Imperial Rescript on Education 関する (かんする) N3 Verb to be related to 認識 (にんしき) N3 Noun recognition 問われる (とわれる) N3 Verb to be questioned 10年以上前 (じゅうねんいじょうまえ) N2 Noun more than 10 years ago 大臣 (だいじん) N3 Noun minister 就任前 (しゅうにんまえ) N2 Noun before taking office 政治家 (せいじか) N3 Noun politician 発言 (はつげん) N3 Noun statement 閣僚 (かくりょう) N2 Noun cabinet member 立憲民主党 (りっけんみんしゅとう) N2 Noun Constitutional Democratic Party 質問 (しつもん) N4 Noun question 自身 (じしん) N3 Noun oneself 発言 (はつげん) N3 Noun statement 過去 (かこ) N4 Noun past 教育勅語 (きょういくちょくご) N1 Noun Imperial Rescript on Education 関する (かんする) N3 Verb to be related to 認識 (にんしき) N3 Noun recognition Grammar and Sentence Structure 「10年以上前の、大臣就任前の政治家としての発言。閣僚の立場でお答えすることは控えたい」などと述べ、審議が紛糾する一幕があった。</description></item><item><title>南極観測隊に初の女性隊長　1次隊から68年、来秋出発の66次隊で</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/the-first-female-team-leader-for-the-antarctic-observation-team-after-68-years-since-the-1st-team-will-depart-in-the-66th-team-next-autumn/</link><pubDate>Mon, 30 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/the-first-female-team-leader-for-the-antarctic-observation-team-after-68-years-since-the-1st-team-will-depart-in-the-66th-team-next-autumn/</guid><description>女性初の南極観測隊長（66次隊）になる原田尚美さん。60次隊出発前、観測船しらせの前で=2018年11月5日午後2時48分、東京都品川区八潮・大井埠頭（ふとう）、中山由美撮影 Link to the original article
南極なんきょく地域ちいき観測かんそく統合とうごう推進すいしん本部ほんぶは30日にちの総会そうかいで、66次じ観測かんそく隊たいの隊長たいちょう兼か夏隊長たいちょうを東京大学とうきょうだいがくの原田はらだ尚美なおみ教授きょうじゅ（56）に決定けっていした。1956年ねん11月がつに1次じ隊たいが出発しゅっぱつして以来いらい、女性じょせいの隊長たいちょうは初はじめて。66次じ隊たいは来秋らいあき出発しゅっぱつする。 原田はらださんは、同大どうだい大気たいき海洋かいよう研究所けんきゅうじょ国際こくさい・地域ちいき連携れんけい研究けんきゅうセンターせんたーに所属しょぞく。観測隊たい史上しじょう2人目にんめの女性じょせい隊員たいいんとして、33次じ夏隊かたい（91～92年ねん）で初はじめて南極なんきょくを訪たずれた。2018年ねん11月がつ出発しゅっぱつの60次じ隊たいでは、女性じょせい初はじの副隊長ふくたいちょう（兼か夏隊長なつたいちょう）を務つとめた。 原田はらださんは「66ろくじゅうろく次隊たいは、しらせの復路ふくろで多おおくの海洋かいよう観測かんそくが計画けいかくされていることから、隊長たいちょうに選えらんでいただいたと思おもう。観測かんそくも、昭和しょうわ基地きちでの輸送ゆそうや設営せつえいも、全体ぜんたいを見渡みわたしながら取残とりのこす仕事しごとがないようがんばりたい」と話はなす。 同日どうじつ急きゅうきょきょ開ひらかかれれたた会見かいけんでは「女性じょせいだとやりにくいと思おもう隊員たいいんもいるかもしれない。でもコミュニケーションこみゅにけーしょんをとって『この人ひとだったら大丈夫だいじょうぶ』と思おもってもらえるような信頼関係しんらいかんけいをつくっていきたい」と話はなしていた。 専門せんもんは生物地球化学せいぶつちきゅうかがく、古海洋学こかいようがく。就職しゅうしょくした海洋研究開発機構かいようけんきゅうかいはつきこうでは、海底かいていの堆積たいせき（たいせき）物ぶつから過去かこの海洋環境かいようかんきょうを研究けんきゅうし、北極海ほっきょくかいにも赴おもむいた。昨年さくねん6月がつ、東大とうだい同センターせんたーに着任ちゃくにんした。 66ろくじじたいの副隊長ふくたいちょうけん越冬隊長えっとうたいちょうは、気象庁きしょうちょう大気海洋部たいきかいようぶ環境かんきょう・海洋気象課かいようきしょうか南極観測事務室なんきょくかんそくじむしつの藤田建ふじたたつる（たつる）・主任技術専門官しゅにんぎじゅつせんもんかん（53）に決きまった。気象庁きしょうちょうから選えらばれた越冬隊長えっとうたいちょうは6人目にんめ。（中山由美なかやまゆみ） Vocabulary Word (Furigana) JLPT Level Part of Speech Meaning 南極地域 (なんきょくちいき) N1 Noun Antarctic region 観測 (かんそく) N2 Noun, Suru verb observation 統合 (とうごう) N2 Noun, Suru verb integration 推進 (すいしん) N2 Noun, Suru verb promotion 本部 (ほんぶ) N3 Noun headquarters 総会 (そうかい) N3 Noun general meeting 66次 (ろくじゅうろくじ) N1 Noun 66th expedition 隊長 (たいちょう) N3 Noun leader 兼 (けん) N3 Noun, Suru verb concurrently 夏隊長 (なつたいちょう) N1 Noun summer leader 東京大学 (とうきょうだいがく) N3 Noun University of Tokyo 原田尚美教授 (はらだなおみきょうじゅ) N1 Noun Professor Naomi Harada 決定 (けってい) N3 Noun, Suru verb decision 1956年 (せんきゅうひゃくごじゅうろくねん) N3 Noun 1956 11月 (じゅういちがつ) N5 Noun November 1次 (いちじ) N3 Noun first expedition 出発 (しゅっぱつ) N4 Noun, Suru verb departure 女性 (じょせい) N5 Noun woman 初めて (はじめて) N4 Adverb for the first time 来秋 (らいしゅう) N3 Noun next autumn 所属 (しょぞく) N3 Noun, Suru verb affiliation 大気海洋研究所 (たいきかいようけんきゅうじょ) N1 Noun Institute of Atmospheric and Oceanic Research 国際・地域連携研究センター (こくさいちいきれんけいけんきゅうせんたー) N1 Noun International and Regional Collaboration Research Center 隊員 (たいいん) N3 Noun team member 33次 (さんじゅうさんじ) N1 Noun 33rd expedition 夏隊 (なつたい) N1 Noun summer team 91～92年 (きゅうじゅういちきゅうじゅうにねん) N1 Noun 1991-1992 訪れる (おとずれる) N4 Godan verb to visit 2018年 (にせんじゅうはちねん) N3 Noun 2018 副隊長 (ふくたいちょう) N1 Noun vice leader 務める (つとめる) N4 Godan verb to serve しらせの復路 (しらせのふくろ) N1 Noun return route of Shirase 多く (おおく) N4 Adverb many 海洋観測 (かいようかんそく) N1 Noun ocean observation 計画 (けいかく) N4 Noun, Suru verb plan 見渡す (みわたす) N3 Godan verb to look out over 取り残す (とりのこす) N3 Godan verb to leave behind 仕事 (しごと) N5 Noun work ないよう N3 Noun condition がんばる N4 Godan verb to do one&amp;rsquo;s best 思う (おもう) N5 Godan verb to think 急きょ (きゅうきょ) N2 Adverb suddenly 開かれる (ひらかれる) N3 Godan verb to be held 会見 (かいけん) N3 Noun press conference やりにくい N3 Adjective difficult to do コミュニケーション N3 Noun communication 信頼関係 (しんらいかんけい) N2 Noun trust relationship つくる N5 Godan verb to create 専門 (せんもん) N4 Noun specialty 生物地球化学 (せいぶつちきゅうかがく) N1 Noun biogeochemistry 古海洋学 (こかいようがく) N1 Noun paleoceanography 就職 (しゅうしょく) N3 Noun, Suru verb employment 海洋研究開発機構 (かいようけんきゅうかいはつきこう) N1 Noun Japan Agency for Marine-Earth Science and Technology 海底 (かいてい) N3 Noun seabed 堆積 (たいせき) N2 Noun, Suru verb sedimentation 過去 (かこ) N4 Noun past 環境 (かんきょう) N4 Noun environment 着任 (ちゃくにん) N3 Noun, Suru verb assumption of duty 副隊長兼越冬隊長 (ふくたいちょうけんえっとうたいちょう) N1 Noun vice leader and wintering leader 気象庁 (きしょうちょう) N2 Noun Japan Meteorological Agency 大気海洋部 (たいきかいようぶ) N1 Noun Atmospheric and Oceanic Department 環境・海洋気象課 (かんきょうかいようきしょうか) N1 Noun Environmental and Oceanic Meteorology Section 南極観測事務室 (なんきょくかんそくじむしつ) N1 Noun Antarctic Observation Office 藤田建 (ふじたたつる) N1 Noun Tatsumi Fujita 主任技術専門官 (しゅにんぎじゅつせんもんかん) N1 Noun Chief Technical Specialist 53 N3 Noun 53 決まる (きまる) N4 Godan verb to be decided 6人目 (ろくにんめ) N3 Noun 6th person 中山由美 (なかやまゆみ) N1 Noun Yumi Nakayama Grammar and Sentence Structure 「同日急きょ開かれた会見では『女性だとやりにくいと思う隊員もいるかもしれない。でもコミュニケーションをとって『この人だったら大丈夫』と思ってもらえるような信頼関係をつくっていきたい』と話していた。」</description></item><item><title>自民・萩生田政調会長、「定額減税」に2年以上の可能性言及</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/toshihiro-nikai-the-secretary-general-of-the-liberal-democratic-party-mentioned-the-possibility-of-fixed-amount-tax-reduction-for-more-than-2-years/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/toshihiro-nikai-the-secretary-general-of-the-liberal-democratic-party-mentioned-the-possibility-of-fixed-amount-tax-reduction-for-more-than-2-years/</guid><description>岸田文雄首相との面会を終え、取材に応じる自民党の萩生田光一政調会長=2023年10月20日午後5時33分、首相官邸、上田幸一撮影 Link to the original article
岸田文雄きしだ ふみお首相しゅしょうが与党よとうに検討けんとうを指示しじした1人にんあたり年ねん4万まん円のの所得税しょとくぜいなどの「定額減税ていがくげんぜい」の措置そち期間きかんをめぐり、自民党じみんとうの萩生田光一はぎうだ こういち政調会長せいちょうかいちょうは29日にちのNHK番組ばんぐみで「『1年ねん限りり』と決定けっていしているわけではない」と述のべ、2年ねん以上いじょうの措置そちとなる可能性かのうせいに言及げんきゅうした。 萩生田はぎうだ氏しは、「定額減税ていがくげんぜい」の措置期間そちきかんについて、企業きぎょうの賃上ちんあげ動向どうこうなどを見極みきめて判断はんだんすべきだと指摘してき。結果けっか次第しだいでは、単年度たんねんどの措置そちにとどまらず、2年以上ねんいじょうとなる可能性かのうせいを示しめした。一方で、「（減税措置げんぜいそちは）永遠えいえんにできることではないと思おもう」とも語いった。 「定額減税ていがくげんぜい」をめぐっては、首相しゅしょうは税収増ぜいしゅうぞうの還付策かんぷさくとして、1人にん4万まん円の所得税しょとくぜいなどの減税げんぜいを来年らいねん6月がつから実施じっしする方針ほうしんを表明ひょうめい。合わせて住民税じゅうみんぜい非課税世帯せたいには1世帯せたいあたり7万まん円の給付きゅうふを行おこなうとし、具体的ぐたいてきな制度設計せいどせっけいを与党よとうに指示しじしている。首相しゅしょうはこれまで1年ねんが基本きほんであるとの認識にんしきを示しめしている。 萩生田氏はぎうだしの発言はつげんは、与党よとう内の単年度たんねんどの減税効果げんぜいこうかを疑問視ぎもんしする意見いけんを意識いしきしたものと見みられる。公明党こうめいとうの高木陽介政調会長たかぎようすけせいちょうかいちょうも同番組どうばんぐみで「賃金ちんぎんを物価高ぶっかだか以上に上あげるのが大切たいせつ」と語かたり、実施期間じっしきかんは経済状況けいざいじょうきょうを踏ふまえて考かんがえる必要性ひつようせいを強調きょうちょうした。 萩生田はぎうだ氏はまた、政府せいふが解散命令かいさんめいれいを請求せいきゅうした世界平和統一家庭連合せかいへいわとういつかていれんごう（旧統一教会きゅうとういつきょうかい）の被害者救済ひがいしゃきゅうさいに向むけた「財産保全ざいさんほぜん」について、萩生田はぎうだ氏は「必要ひつような法律ほうりつがあれば作つくらないといけない」と述のべ、立法措置りっぽうそちも排除はいじょしない考かんがえを示しめした。 与党よとうは現在げんざい、教団きょうだんの財産ざいさんの散逸さんぴつを防ふせぐべきだとして、プロジェクトチームプロジェクトチーム（PT）を立たち上あげて対応たいおうを検討けんとうしている。ただ、憲法けんぽうが保障ほしょうする財産権ざいさんけんや信教しんきょうの自由じゆうを侵害しんがいする恐おそれがあるなどとして、法整備ほうせいびに対たいする慎重論しんちょうろんが目立めだつ。 一方いっぽう、野党やとう側がわは、立憲民主党りっけんみんしゅとうが時限的じげんてきな特別措置とくべつそち法案ほうあんを提出ていしゅつするなど、法整備ほうせいびを急いそぐよう要求ようきゅうしている。萩生田はぎうだ氏は「与党よとうの考かんがえをまとめた段階だんかいで、野党やとう提案ていあんの法律ほうりつも含ふくめて話はなし合あいをしたい」と述のべ、与野党よやとう協議きょうぎの場ばを設もうける可能性かのうせいに触ふれた。（森岡もりおか航平こうへい） Vocabulary Word (Furigana) JLPT Level Part of Speech Meaning 指示する (しじする) N3 Verb to instruct 検討する (けんとうする) N3 Verb to consider 措置 (そち) N3 Noun measure, step 期間 (きかん) N3 Noun period, term 自民党 (じみんとう) N3 Noun Liberal Democratic Party 政調会長 (せいちょうかいちょう) N3 Noun chairman of the policy research council 述べる (のべる) N3 Verb to state, to express 見極める (みきわめる) N3 Verb to judge, to determine 判断する (はんだんする) N3 Verb to judge, to decide 次第 (しだい) N3 Noun depending on, as soon as 企業 (きぎょう) N3 Noun company, corporation 賃上げ (ちんあげ) N3 Noun wage increase 動向 (どうこう) N3 Noun trend, movement 示す (しめす) N3 Verb to show, to indicate 永遠に (えいえんに) N3 Adverb forever, eternally 認識 (にんしき) N3 Noun recognition, awareness 疑問視する (ぎもんしする) N3 Verb to question, to doubt 語る (かたる) N3 Verb to talk, to speak 実施する (じっしする) N3 Verb to implement, to carry out 経済状況 (けいざいじょうきょう) N3 Noun economic situation 強調する (きょうちょうする) N3 Verb to emphasize, to highlight 解散命令 (かいさんめいれい) N3 Noun dissolution order 請求する (せいきゅうする) N3 Verb to request, to demand 被害者救済 (ひがいしゃきゅうさい) N3 Noun victim relief 財産保全 (ざいさんほぜん) N3 Noun asset preservation 立法措置 (りっぽうそち) N3 Noun legislative measures 散逸 (さんぴつ) N3 Noun dissipation, scattering 侵害する (しんがいする) N3 Verb to violate, to infringe 慎重論 (しんちょうろん) N3 Noun cautious argument 特別措置法案 (とくべつそちほうあん) N3 Noun special measures bill 話し合い (はなしあい) N3 Noun discussion, negotiation 与野党協議 (よやとうきょうぎ) N3 Noun ruling and opposition party talks 設ける (もうける) N3 Verb to establish, to set up Grammar and Sentence Structure 「定額減税」の措置期間について、企業の賃上げ動向などを見極めて判断すべきだと指摘。</description></item><item><title>「のだめ」ヴィエラ先生役死去　クラシック監修・茂木大輔さんの秘話</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/vieira-sensei-who-played-the-role-of-nodame-has-passed-away-a-secret-story-of-classical-music-supervision-by-daisuke-mogi/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/vieira-sensei-who-played-the-role-of-nodame-has-passed-away-a-secret-story-of-classical-music-supervision-by-daisuke-mogi/</guid><description>茂木大輔さん Link to the original article
25にじゅうごに87はちじゅうなな歳さいで死去しきょしたチェコチェコの名匠めいしょう、ズデニェク・マーカルズデニェク・マーカルさんは、時代じだいの波なみに翻弄ほんろうされて生いき抜ぬいた指揮者しきしゃだった。著名ちょめいな国際こくさいコンクールコンクールで相次あいついで優勝ゆうしょうしたが、東西とうざい冷戦れいせん下亡命ぼうめい。西側にしがわで28にじゅうはち年ねん活躍かつやくしてからチェコチェコに戻もどり、2003にせんさん年ねんにチェコ・フィルハーモニー管弦楽団チェコ・フィルハーモニーかんげんがくだんの首席指揮者しゅせきしきしゃに凱旋がいせん（がいせん）した。フジテレビフジテレビ系けいドラマドラマ「のだめカンタービレ」で、玉木宏たまきひろしさん演えんじる音大生おんだいせい・千秋ちあきの理想りそうの指揮者しきしゃ、ヴィエラ先生ヴィエラせんせいを演えんじたのはその3さん年後ねんごのこと。ドラマのクラシッククラシック監修かんしゅうを務つとめた指揮者しきしゃの茂木大輔もぎだいすけさんが、その時ときの「秘話ひばなし」を語かたる。 I'm sorry, but it seems like you haven't provided any words or phrases for me to annotate. Could you please provide a word or phrase in Japanese that you would like me to annotate? 僕ぼく自身じしんは撮影さつえいに同行どうこうしていないので、詳くわしい事情じじょうはわからないんですが、プラハぷらはでマーカルまーかるさんの指揮しき風景ふうけいを撮影さつえいしたとき、ひとつだけミラクルみらくるがあったんです。 ドラマの記念きねんすべき第1回だいいっかいが、すごくメランコリックめらんこりっくでノスタルジックのすたるじっくで、何なにとも言いえない馥郁ふくいく（ふくいく）とした気品きひんがある曲きょくで始はじまるのを、覚おぼえてくださっている方かたも多おおいと思おもいます。僕ぼく自身じしんも、うわあ、なんて良いい曲きょくなんだろうって陶然とうぜんとしました。 これはドボルザークどぼるざーくの「チェコ組曲ちぇこくみく」の「ポルカぽるか」という、あまり演奏えんそうされる機会きかいのなかった曲きょくでした。もちろん僕ぼく自身も聴きいたことがなかった。 でも、プラハぷらはに撮影さつえいに行いったときに、たまたまこれをマーカルまーかるさんが振ふっていた。つまり、偶然ぐうぜんの出会であいだったんです。 武内英樹たけうちひでき監督かんとくに「監督かんとく、良よい曲きょく選えらびましたね！」って言いったら、「いや、僕ぼくらが現地げんちに行いったとき、たまたまこの曲きょくのレコーディングれこーでぃんぐをやってたんだよ」と。一目ひとめぼれならぬ一聴いっちょうぼれだったそうです。 実際じっさいにこの曲きょくが流ながれたあと、すごい反響はんきょうがあった。（ドラマどらまにちなんだコンサートこんさーとの）人気投票にんきとうひょうでも上位じょういに入はいったので、コンサートこんさーとで僕ぼく、振ふりました。下野竜也しものりたつやさんもよく振ふってくれていますね。 幼おさない千秋ちあきは、ヴィエラヴィエラとの出会であいによって父ちちの慈愛じあいと音楽おんがくの力ちからを知しった。もうひとりの千秋ちあきの「父ちち」を、あたたかな演技えんぎと柔やわらかな演奏えんそうで、素晴すばらしく描かいてくださったなと思おもいます。（聞きき手て 編集委員へんしゅういいん・吉田よしだ純子じゅんこ） Vocabulary Word (Furigana) JLPT Level Part of Speech Meaning 死去 (しきょ) N1 Verb to pass away 指揮者 (しきしゃ) N1 Noun conductor 翻弄 (ほんろう)する N1 Verb to toy with, to manipulate 生き抜く (いきぬく) N1 Verb to survive 優勝 (ゆうしょう)する N1 Verb to win a championship 亡命 (ぼうめい)する N1 Verb to flee, to seek asylum 活躍 (かつやく)する N1 Verb to be active, to play an active part 凱旋 (がいせん)する N1 Verb to return in triumph 首席 (しゅせき) N1 Noun chief, principal 指揮 (しき)する N1 Verb to conduct 演じる (えんじる) N1 Verb to perform, to act 理想 (りそう) N1 Noun ideal 秘話 (ひわ) N1 Noun secret story 撮影 (さつえい)する N1 Verb to film, to shoot 事情 (じじょう) N1 Noun circumstances, situation ミラクル N1 Noun miracle 風景 (ふうけい) N1 Noun scenery メランコリック N1 Adjective melancholic ノスタルジック N1 Adjective nostalgic 馥郁 (ふくいく) N1 Adjective rich, fragrant 気品 (きひん) N1 Noun elegance, grace 曲 (きょく) N1 Noun piece of music 陶然 (とうぜん)とする N1 Verb to be enchanted, to be captivated チェコ組曲 (チェコくみきょく) N1 Noun Czech Suite ポルカ N1 Noun polka 演奏 (えんそう)する N1 Verb to perform, to play 振る (ふる) N1 Verb to conduct 一目ぼれ (ひとめぼれ) N1 Noun love at first sight 一聴ぼれ (いっちょうぼれ) N1 Noun love at first listen 流れる (ながれる) N1 Verb to flow 反響 (はんきょう) N1 Noun response, reaction 人気投票 (にんきとうひょう) N1 Noun popularity poll 振りる (ふりる) N1 Verb to conduct 出会い (であい) N1 Noun encounter 父 (ちち) N1 Noun father 慈愛 (じあい) N1 Noun love, affection 音楽 (おんがく) N1 Noun music 描く (えがく) N1 Verb to depict, to portray Grammar and Sentence Structure &amp;ldquo;これはドボルザークの「チェコ組曲」の「ポルカ」という、あまり演奏される機会のなかった曲でした。&amp;rdquo; Grammatical points: The sentence includes a relative clause (&amp;ldquo;ドボルザークの「チェコ組曲」の「ポルカ」という&amp;rdquo;) modifying the noun &amp;ldquo;曲&amp;rdquo; (song).</description></item><item><title>池袋暴走事故、運転の受刑者側に1億4千万円の賠償命令　東京地裁</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/ikebukuro-hit-and-run-accident-tokyo-district-court-orders-the-driver-to-pay-140-million-yen-in-compensation/</link><pubDate>Fri, 27 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/ikebukuro-hit-and-run-accident-tokyo-district-court-orders-the-driver-to-pay-140-million-yen-in-compensation/</guid><description>判決を受けて会見する松永拓也さん=2023年10月27日、東京・霞が関、遠藤隆史撮影 Link to the original article
東京とうきょう・池袋いけぶくろで2019年ねんに起おきた乗じょう用よう車しゃの暴ぼう走そう事故じこで、妻つま子こを亡なくした松永まつなが拓也たくやさん（37）ら遺い族ぞくが、車くるまを運うん転てんしていた飯塚いいづか幸三こうぞう受じゅ刑けい者しゃ（93）=禁きん錮こ5年ねんの実じつ刑けい判はん決けつが確かく定てい=と保ほ険けん会かい社しゃに計けい約1億おく8千せん万円えんの損そん害がい賠ばい償しょうを求もとめた訴そ訟しょうで、東京とうきょう地ち裁さい（平山ひらやま馨かおる裁さい判はん長ちょう）は27日にち、受じゅ刑けい者しゃ側がわに約やく1億おく4600万まん円のの支し払はらいを命めいじじる判はん決けつを言い渡わたした。 判決はんけつは、飯塚受刑者いいづかじゅけいしゃには運動機能うんどうきのうの低下ていかを伴ともなう持病じびょうがあり、「運転うんてんは最小限度さいしょうげんどとするよう医師いしから指導しどうされていた」と指摘してき。それでも運転うんてんを続つづけた結果けっか、アクセルあくせるとブレーキぶれーきを的確てきかくに操作そうさするという最もっとも基本的きほんてきな注意義務ちゅういぎむに違反いはんして2人にんの命いのちを奪うばったと認定にんていし、死亡慰謝料しぼういしゃりょうや逸失利益いっしつりえきなどを支払しはらうよう命めいじた。 判決はんけつは、飯塚受刑者いいづかじゅけいしゃが「ひとまずの道義的どうぎてきな謝罪しゃざいすらしないまま、刑事事件けいじじけんで相応そうおうの証拠しょうこが出揃でそろった後あとも過失かしつを認みとめず、不合理ふごうりな弁解べんかいを続つづけた」と指摘していっ。「刑事手続けいじてつづきで防御権ぼうぎょけんが保障ほしょうされていることを踏ふまえても、遺族いぞくの心情しんじょうを逆ぎゃくなでする行為こういで、被害者側ひがいしゃがわが受うけ入いれるに足たるだけの真摯しんし（しんし）な謝罪しゃざいがされていないことは、慰謝料算定いしゃりょうさんていの重要じゅうような事情じじょうだ」と述のべた。 確定かくていした場合ばあいは保険会社ほけんがいしゃが支払しはらうことになる。 判決はんけつを受うけた会見かいけんで松永まつながさんは「（受刑者じゅけいしゃの）病気びょうきと事故じこの因果関係いんがかんけいを認みとめてもらえた。（妻つまと子こには）『争あらそい事ごとは終おわったよ』伝つたえたい」と話はなした。 事故じこは19年ねん4月がつに発生はっせいし、松永まつながさんの妻つま真菜まなさん（当時とうじ31）と長女りこちゃん（同どう3）が死亡しぼう。旧きゅう通産省つうさんしょう工業技術院こうぎょうぎじゅついん元もと院長いんちょうの飯塚いいづか受刑者じゅけいしゃは自動車じどうしゃ運転うんてん死傷処罰法ししょうしょばつほう違反いはん（過失運転致死傷かしつうんてんちしぼう）の罪つみに問とわれた。東京地裁とうきょうちさいは21年ねん、受刑者じゅけいしゃがブレーキぶれーきとアクセルあくせるのペダルぺだるを踏ふみ間違まちがえて赤信号あかしんごうの交差点こうさてんに突入とつにゅうしたと認定にんていし、禁錮きんこ5年ねんの実刑じっけい判決はんけつを言いい渡わたした。受刑者じゅけいしゃが控訴こうそせず確定かくていした。（遠藤えんどう隆史たかし） Vocabulary Word (Furigana) JLPT Level Part of Speech Meaning 起きる (おきる) N5 verb (godan) to occur, to happen 乗用車 (じょうようしゃ) N5 noun passenger car 暴走 (ぼうそう) N3 noun, suru verb reckless driving 事故 (じこ) N4 noun accident 亡くす (なくす) N4 verb (godan) to lose (a loved one) 遺族 (いぞく) N3 noun bereaved family 運転 (うんてん) N4 noun, suru verb driving 飯塚 (いいづか) N/A noun Iizuka (surname) 幸三 (こうぞう) N/A noun Kozo (given name) 受刑者 (じゅけいしゃ) N/A noun prisoner 禁錮 (きんこ) N/A noun imprisonment 実刑 (じっけい) N/A noun actual imprisonment 判決 (はんけつ) N4 noun judgement, ruling 確定 (かくてい) N3 noun, suru verb finalization 保険会社 (ほけんがいしゃ) N4 noun insurance company 計約 (けいやく) N/A noun approximately 損害賠償 (そんがいばいしょう) N3 noun compensation for damages 求める (もとめる) N4 verb (godan) to seek, to demand 訴訟 (そしょう) N3 noun lawsuit 東京地裁 (とうきょうちさい) N/A noun Tokyo District Court 平山馨 (ひらやまかおる) N/A noun Kaoru Hirayama (name) 言い渡す (いいわたす) N3 verb (godan) to pronounce, to deliver (a judgement) 運動機能 (うんどうきのう) N/A noun motor function 低下 (ていか) N3 noun, suru verb decline, deterioration 伴う (ともなう) N3 verb (godan) to accompany, to be accompanied by 持病 (じびょう) N3 noun chronic illness 運転する (うんてんする) N4 verb (suru) to drive 最小限度 (さいしょうげんど) N/A noun minimum limit 医師 (いし) N4 noun doctor 指導する (しどうする) N3 verb (suru) to instruct, to guide 続ける (つづける) N4 verb (ichidan) to continue 結果 (けっか) N4 noun result アクセル (あくせる) N/A noun accelerator ブレーキ (ぶれーき) N/A noun brake 的確に (てきかくに) N/A adverb accurately 操作する (そうさする) N4 verb (suru) to operate 基本的な (きほんてきな) N/A adjective (な) basic 注意義務 (ちゅういぎむ) N/A noun duty of care 違反する (いはんする) N4 verb (suru) to violate 命 (いのち) N4 noun life 認定する (にんていする) N3 verb (suru) to certify, to recognize 死亡慰謝料 (しぼういしゃりょう) N/A noun compensation for death 逸失利益 (いっしつりえき) N/A noun loss of earnings 支払う (しはらう) N4 verb (godan) to pay 受け入れる (うけいれる) N4 verb (ichidan) to accept 足る (たる) N4 verb (u-verb) to be sufficient 真摯 (しんし) N/A noun sincerity 謝罪する (しゃざいする) N3 verb (suru) to apologize 病気 (びょうき) N5 noun illness 因果関係 (いんがかんけい) N/A noun cause and effect relationship 認める (みとめる) N4 verb (ichidan) to acknowledge 争い事 (あらそいごと) N/A noun dispute 伝える (つたえる) N4 verb (ichidan) to convey 会見 (かいけん) N3 noun press conference 病気と事故の因果関係 (びょうきとじこのいんがかんけい) N/A noun causal relationship between illness and accident 認めてもらえる (みてもらえる) N/A verb (ichidan) to have something acknowledged 争い事は終わったよ (あらそいごとはおわったよ) N/A phrase the dispute is over 発生する (はっせいする) N4 verb (suru) to occur 妻 (つま) N5 noun wife 子 (こ) N5 noun child 争い事は終わったよ (あらそいごとはおわったよ) N/A phrase the dispute is over 伝える (つたえる) N4 verb (ichidan) to convey 事故 (じこ) N4 noun accident 発生する (はっせいする) N4 verb (suru) to occur 妻 (つま) N5 noun wife 子 (こ) N5 noun child 死亡 (しぼう) N4 noun death 旧通産省工業技術院 (きゅうつうさんしょうこうぎょうぎじゅついん) N/A noun former Ministry of International Trade and Industry Industrial Technology Institute 元院長 (もといんちょう) N/A noun former director 自動車運転死傷処罰法違反 (じどうしゃうんてんしけんしょばつほういはん) N/A noun violation of the Road Traffic Act causing death or injury by motor vehicle 罪 (つみ) N4 noun crime 問われる (とわれる) N3 verb (passive) to be questioned 赤信号 (あかしんごう) N/A noun red light 交差点 (こうさてん) N4 noun intersection 突入する (とつにゅうする) N4 verb (suru) to rush into 言い渡す (いいわたす) N3 verb (godan) to pronounce, to deliver (a judgement) 禁錮 (きんこ) N/A noun imprisonment 実刑 (じっけい) N/A noun actual imprisonment 判決 (はんけつ) N4 noun judgement, ruling 受刑者 (じゅけいしゃ) N/A noun prisoner 防御権 (ぼうぎょけん) N/A noun right of defense 保障する (ほしょうする) N3 verb (suru) to guarantee, to protect 踏まえる (ふまえる) N3 verb (ichidan) to base on, to take into consideration 心情 (しんじょう) N/A noun feelings 逆なでする (ぎゃくなでする) N/A verb (suru) to go against, to hurt 行為 (こうい) N4 noun act 被害者側 (ひがいしゃがわ) N/A noun victim&amp;rsquo;s side 受け入れる (うけいれる) N4 verb (ichidan) to accept 真摯 (しんし) N/A noun sincerity 謝罪する (しゃざいする) N3 verb (suru) to apologize 確定する (かくていする) N3 verb (suru) to finalize 保険会社 (ほけんがいしゃ) N4 noun insurance company 支払う (しはらう) N4 verb (godan) to pay 受け入れる (うけいれる) N4 verb (ichidan) to accept 会見 (かいけん) N3 noun press conference 松永 (まつなが) N/A noun Matsunaga (surname) 病気 (びょうき) N5 noun illness 事故 (じこ) N4 noun accident 因果関係 (いんがかんけい) N/A noun cause and effect relationship 認めてもらえる (みてもらえる) N/A verb (ichidan) to have something acknowledged 争い事は終わったよ (あらそいごとはおわったよ) N/A phrase the dispute is over 発生する (はっせいする) N4 verb (suru) to occur 妻 (つま) N5 noun wife 子 (こ) N5 noun child 死亡 (しぼう) N4 noun death 旧通産省工業技術院 (きゅうつうさんしょうこうぎょうぎじゅついん) N/A noun former Ministry of International Trade and Industry Industrial Technology Institute 元院長 (もといんちょう) N/A noun former director 自動車運転死傷処罰法違反 (じどうしゃうんてんしけんしょばつほういはん) N/A noun violation of the Road Traffic Act causing death or injury by motor vehicle 罪 (つみ) N4 noun crime 問われる (とわれる) N3 verb (passive) to be questioned 赤信号 (あかしんごう) N/A noun red light 交差点 (こうさてん) N4 noun intersection 突入する (とつにゅうする) N4 verb (suru) to rush into 言い Grammar and Sentence Structure 判決は、飯塚受刑者には運動機能の低下を伴う持病があり、「運転は最小限度とするよう医師から指導されていた」と指摘。 1.</description></item><item><title>辞職表明の木村弥生区長、元議員の父に「相談」　特捜部の捜索受け</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/yayoi-kimura-the-district-mayor-who-announced-her-resignation-consulted-with-her-father-a-former-member-of-the-diet-following-the-search-by-the-special-investigation-department/</link><pubDate>Thu, 26 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/yayoi-kimura-the-district-mayor-who-announced-her-resignation-consulted-with-her-father-a-former-member-of-the-diet-following-the-search-by-the-special-investigation-department/</guid><description>記者会見で辞職を表明する木村弥生・江東区長=2023年10月26日午後2時59分、東京都江東区東陽4丁目、滝沢貴大撮影 Link to the original article
東京都とうきょうと江東区こうとうくの木村弥生きむらやよい区長くちょう（58）は26日午後ごごに区役所くやくしょで記者会見きしゃかいけんを開ひらき、辞職じしょくを表明ひょうめいした。今年ことし4月がつの区長選くちょうせんをめぐり、選挙期間せんきょきかん中に投票とうひょうを呼よびかける有料ゆうりょうのインターネット広告いんたーねっとこうこくを流ながしていたとして、公職選挙法こうしょくせんきょほう違反いはん容疑で東京地検特捜部とうきょうちけんとくそうぶから区長室くちょうしつなどが24日に家宅捜索かたくそうさくを受うけていた。 木村きむら氏は26日の会見かいけんで、家宅捜索かたくそうさくを受うけたことで「区政くせいを混乱こんらん、停滞ていたいをさせてはならないと考かんがえた」と説明せつめい。「ご期待きたいいただきながら、このような形かたちで辞職じしょくすることに申もうし訳わけない思おもいでいっぱいです」と謝罪しゃざいした。 木村きむら氏によると、家宅捜索かたくそうさくを受けたことで今週予定された行事ぎょうじなどがキャンセルきゃんせるになった。こうした状況じょうきょうが今後こんごも続つづくおそれがあることや実家じっかも捜索対象そうさくたいしょうになったことなどから、捜索翌日そうさくよくじつの25日朝にちあさ、電話でんわで副区長ふくくちょうに辞職じしょくの意向いこうを伝つたえたという。辞職じしょくにあたっては地元選出じもとせんしゅつだった父ちちの木村勉きむらつとむ・元衆院議員もとしゅういんぎいんに相談そうだんし、「尊重そんちょうする」との回答かいとうを得えたとした。 一方いっぽう、木村きむら氏は8月がつの会見かいけんでは有料ゆうりょうのネット広告こうこくを出だしたのはスタッフの判断はんだんで、「監督かんとく不行ふゆき届とどきだった」と述のべていた。今回こんかいの会見かいけんで、この認識にんしきに変かわりがないかや自身じしんの関与かんよについて報道陣ほうどうじんから問とわれたが、「捜査そうさに協力きょうりょくしているさなかなのでお答こたえは控ひかえる」などと明言めいげんを避さけた。また、ネット広告こうこく以外に「他ほかに何なにかしら疑うたがいがあるわけではない」とも述のべた。 木村きむら氏は「辞やめる人間にんげんが新区長しんくちょうに対たいし、注文ちゅうもんすべきものはない」とした上で、自身じしんの今後こんごについては「捜査そうさに協力きょうりょくすることを第一だいいちにし、これから先さきのことはまだ何なにも考かんがえていない」と話はなした。 Vocabulary Word (Furigana) JLPT Level Part of Speech Meaning 東京都 (とうきょうと) N/A Noun Tokyo 江東区 (こうとうく) N/A Noun Koto Ward 木村弥生区長 (きむらやよいくちょう) N/A Noun Yayoi Kimura, Koto Ward Mayor 記者会見 (きしゃかいけん) N/A Noun Press conference 辞職 (じしょく) N/A Noun Resignation 表明する (ひょうめいする) N/A Verb To declare 今年 (ことし) N/A Noun This year 4月 (しがつ) N/A Noun April 区長選 (くちょうせん) N/A Noun Mayoral election 選挙期間中 (せんきょきかんちゅう) N/A Noun During the election period 投票 (とうひょう) N/A Noun Vote 呼びかける (よびかける) N/A Verb To call out 有料 (ゆうりょう) N/A Noun Paid インターネット広告 (いんたーねっとこうこく) N/A Noun Internet advertisement 流す (ながす) N/A Verb To run (an advertisement) 公職選挙法 (こうしょくせんきょほう) N/A Noun Public Offices Election Act 違反容疑 (いはんようぎ) N/A Noun Suspected violation 東京地検特捜部 (とうきょうちけんとくそうぶ) N/A Noun Tokyo District Public Prosecutors Office Special Investigation Department 区長室 (くちょうしつ) N/A Noun Mayor&amp;rsquo;s office 家宅捜索 (かたくそうさく) N/A Noun Home search 受ける (うける) N/A Verb To receive 会見 (かいけん) N/A Noun Meeting 混乱 (こんらん) N/A Noun Confusion 停滞 (ていたい) N/A Noun Stagnation 考える (かんがえる) N/A Verb To think ご期待いただく (ごきたいいただく) N/A Verb To expect 形 (かたち) N/A Noun Form 申し訳ない (もうしわけない) N/A Adjective Sorry 思いでいっぱい (おもいでいっぱい) N/A Adjective Full of regret 謝罪する (しゃざいする) N/A Verb To apologize 予定 (よてい) N/A Noun Plan 行事 (ぎょうじ) N/A Noun Event キャンセル (きゃんせる) N/A Noun Cancellation 続く (つづく) N/A Verb To continue おそれがある (おそれがある) N/A Phrase There is a possibility 実家 (じっか) N/A Noun Parent&amp;rsquo;s house 捜索対象 (そうさくたいしょう) N/A Noun Search target 翌日 (よくじつ) N/A Noun The next day 朝 (あさ) N/A Noun Morning 電話 (でんわ) N/A Noun Phone call 副区長 (ふくくちょう) N/A Noun Vice mayor 意向 (いこう) N/A Noun Intention 伝える (つたえる) N/A Verb To convey 地元選出 (じもとせんしゅつ) N/A Noun Local representative 父 (ちち) N/A Noun Father 木村勉 (きむらつとむ) N/A Noun Tsutomu Kimura 元衆院議員 (もとしゅういんぎいん) N/A Noun Former member of the House of Representatives 相談する (そうだんする) N/A Verb To consult 尊重する (そんちょうする) N/A Verb To respect 回答 (かいとう) N/A Noun Answer 有料の (ゆうりょうの) N/A Adjective Paid ネット広告 (ねっとこうこく) N/A Noun Internet advertisement スタッフ (すたっふ) N/A Noun Staff 判断 (はんだん) N/A Noun Judgment 監督不行き届き (かんとくふゆきとどき) N/A Noun Negligence of supervision 述べる (のべる) N/A Verb To state 認識 (にんしき) N/A Noun Recognition 変わりがない (かわりがない) N/A Phrase There is no change 関与 (かんよ) N/A Noun Involvement 報道陣 (ほうどうじん) N/A Noun Press 問う (とう) N/A Verb To ask 捜査 (そうさ) N/A Noun Investigation 協力する (きょうりょくする) N/A Verb To cooperate お答えは控える (おこたえはひかえる) N/A Phrase To refrain from answering 他に (ほかに) N/A Adverb Besides 何かしら (なにかしら) N/A Phrase Something 疑い (うたがい) N/A Noun Suspicion 辞める (やめる) N/A Verb To quit 人間 (にんげん) N/A Noun Person 新区長 (しんくちょう) N/A Noun New mayor 注文 (ちゅうもん) N/A Noun Order 今後 (こんご) N/A Noun From now on まだ (まだ) N/A Adverb Still 考える (かんがえる) N/A Verb To think 捜査に協力する (そうさにきょうりょくする) N/A Phrase To cooperate with the investigation 第一に (だいいちに) N/A Phrase First of all これから先 (これからさき) N/A Phrase From now on 話す (はなす) N/A Verb To talk Grammar and Sentence Structure 「こうした状況が今後も続くおそれがあることや実家も捜索対象になったことなどから、捜索翌日の25日朝、電話で副区長に辞職の意向を伝えたという。」 Grammatical points: おそれがある (there is a possibility), 捜索対象になった (became the target of the search), 辞職の意向を伝えた (conveyed the intention to resign) Structure: This sentence describes the reasons for the resignation and the action taken.</description></item><item><title>DMG森、ロシア国内での出荷は「民生用」　戦争支援は改めて否定</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/dmg-mori-states-that-shipments-within-russia-are-for-civilian-use-and-denies-any-support-for-war-efforts/</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/dmg-mori-states-that-shipments-within-russia-are-for-civilian-use-and-denies-any-support-for-war-efforts/</guid><description>DMG森精機のグローバル本社=2023年6月30日、東京都江東区潮見2丁目 Link to the original article
工作機械こうさくきかい大手おおてのDMG森精機ディーエムジーもりせいきは25日にち、ドイツドイツの子会社こがいしゃがウクライナ政府ウクライナせいふから「戦争支援企業せんそうしえんきぎょう」に指定していされた問題もんだいについて、社内調査しゃないちょうさの結果けっかを公表こうひょうした。ロシア法人ほうじんの社員しゃいんが無断むだんでつくった製品せいひんを現地げんちで出荷しゅっかしていたことを認みとめた一方、軍需関連企業ぐんじゅかんれんきぎょうに製品せいひんを供給きょうきゅうしたとする指摘してきを改あらためて否定ひていした。 昨年さくねん2月がつのロシアロシアによるウクライナウクライナ侵攻しんこうを受うけ、DMG森精機ディーエムジーもりせいきはロシアロシア事業じぎょうからの撤退てったいを公表こうひょうした。しかし、同社どうしゃによると、ロシアロシア法人ほうじんの複数ふくすうの社員しゃいんは、自みずからの判断はんだんで注文済ちゅうもんずみみの部品ぶひんを用もちいるなどしてロシアロシアの拠点きょてんで製造せいぞうを続つづけ、約やく120台だいをロシアロシアの顧客こきゃくに出荷しゅっかしていた。すでに製品せいひんを受注じゅちゅうしており、現地げんちで契約違反けいやくいはんに問とわれることなどを懸念けねんしたためと見みられるという。 森雅彦もりまさひこ社長しゃちょうはこの日ひの記者会見きしゃかいけんで「本当ほんとうにウクライナウクライナのことを考かんがえて（ロシアロシアからの撤退てったいを）宣言せんげんしたのに、こういう話はなしになるのは非常ひじょうに残念ざんねん。ご心配しんぱいをおかけして申もうし訳わけない」と述のべた。 一方いっぽう、最終的さいしゅうてきな納入先のうにゅうさきは軍需関連企業ぐんじゅかんれんきぎょうではなく、すべて民生用みんせいようだったと確認かくにんできたと説明せつめいした。ロシアによる侵攻しんこう後に、日本にほんやドイツどいつからロシア内ないに持もちこまれた製品せいひんもなく、日独にちどくの法令違反ほうれいいはんはなかったことも改あらためて強調きょうちょうした。（内藤尚志ないとうたかし） Vocabulary Word (Furigana) JLPT Level Part of Speech Meaning 支援 (しえん) N3 Noun support, aid 指定 (してい) N3 Noun designation, specification 調査 (ちょうさ) N3 Noun investigation, survey 公表 (こうひょう) N3 Noun announcement, publication 認める (みとめる) N3 Verb (Ichidan) to recognize, to admit 出荷 (しゅっか) N3 Noun shipment, delivery 改めて (あらためて) N3 Adverb again, once again 否定する (ひていする) N3 Verb (する) to deny, to negate 侵攻 (しんこう) N3 Noun invasion, aggression 撤退 (てったい) N3 Noun withdrawal, retreat 注文済み (ちゅうもんずみ) N3 Noun pre-ordered 部品 (ぶひん) N3 Noun parts, components 用いる (もちいる) N3 Verb (Godan) to use, to employ 拠点 (きょてん) N3 Noun base, headquarters 製造 (せいぞう) N3 Noun manufacturing, production 出荷する (しゅっかする) N3 Verb (する) to ship, to deliver 受注 (じゅちゅう) N3 Noun order, contract 契約違反 (けいやくいはん) N3 Noun breach of contract 懸念する (けねんする) N3 Verb (する) to be concerned, to worry 考える (かんがえる) N4 Verb (Ichidan) to think, to consider 宣言する (せんげんする) N4 Verb (する) to declare, to announce 残念 (ざんねん) N4 Na-adjective regrettable, disappointing 心配 (しんぱい) N4 Noun worry, concern 申し訳ない (もうしわけない) N4 Na-adjective sorry, apologetic 納入先 (のうにゅうさき) N4 Noun place of delivery 民生用 (みんせいよう) N4 Noun civilian use 強調する (きょうちょうする) N4 Verb (する) to emphasize, to stress 内藤 (ないとう) N/A Noun Naito (surname) 尚志 (なおし) N/A Noun Naoshi (given name) Grammar and Sentence Structure 「ロシア法人の社員が無断でつくった製品を現地で出荷していたことを認めた一方、軍需関連企業に製品を供給したとする指摘を改めて否定した。」</description></item><item><title>大学受験・模試費用の補助へ　ひとり親、低所得世帯向け　経済対策</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/financial-assistance-for-university-entrance-exams-and-practice-exams-for-single-parents-and-low-income-households-economic-measures/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/financial-assistance-for-university-entrance-exams-and-practice-exams-for-single-parents-and-low-income-households-economic-measures/</guid><description>取材に応じる岸田文雄首相=2023年10月19日、首相官邸、上田幸一撮影 Link to the original article
所得しょとくが低ひくい世帯せたいの進学しんがくを支援しえんするため、こどもこども家庭かてい庁ちょうは、ひとりひとり親おや世帯せたいなどの高校こうこう3年生ねんせいと中学ちゅうがく3年生ねんせいに対たいし、大学だいがく受験じゅけんや模擬試験もぎしけんの費用ひようを補助ほじょする方針ほうしんを固かためた。進学しんがく機会きかいの確保かくほにつなげる狙ねらい。政府せいふが11月がつ初旬しょじゅんに決きめる総合そうごう経済けいざい対策たいさくに盛もり込こんだ上うえで、補正ほせい予算よさん案あんに反映はんえいする方針ほうしんだ。 政府せいふ関係者かんけいしゃによると、対象たいしょうとして児童扶養手当じどうふようてあてを受給じゅきゅうするひとり親世帯ひとりおやせたいと、住民税じゅうみんぜい非課税ひかぜい世帯を検討けんとうしている。高校こうこう3年生ねんせいへの大学受験費用だいがくじゅけんひようの補助額ほじょがくは、大学入学共通テストだいがくにゅうがくきょうつうてすとと私立大しりつだいの受験料じゅけんりょうを合計ごうけいした、5万円まんえん程度ていどを想定そうていしている。模擬試験もぎしけんの費用ひようについては、高校こうこう3年生ねんせいに加くわえ、中学ちゅうがく3年生ねんせいも対象たいしょうにする方向ほうこうだ。事業開始じぎょうかいしは、来年度らいねんど以降を見込みこむ。 低所得ていしょとく世帯せたい向けけには授業料じゅぎょうりょうの減免げんめん制度せいどなどがある一方でで、受験じゅけんに対たいする政府せいふの支援しえんが不十分ふじゅうぶんとの声こえがあがっていた。同庁どうちょうは、模擬試験もぎしけんや受験費用じゅけんひようの支援しえんにより、受験じゅけん控ひかえなどを防ふせぎ、進学しんがくの機会きかいにつなげたい考かんがえだ。（高橋健次郎たかはしかんじろう） Vocabulary Word (Furigana) JLPT Level Part of Speech Meaning 所得 (しょとく) N3 Noun income 低い (ひくい) N5 い-adjective low 世帯 (せたい) N3 Noun household 進学 (しんがく) N3 Noun advancing to a higher level of education 支援 (しえん) N3 Noun support こども家庭庁 N/A Noun Ministry of Health, Labour and Welfare ひとり親世帯 N/A Noun single-parent household 高校 (こうこう) N5 Noun high school 3年生 (さんねんせい) N/A Noun 3rd year student 中学 (ちゅうがく) N5 Noun junior high school 大学受験 (だいがくじゅけん) N/A Noun university entrance examination 模擬試験 (もぎしけん) N/A Noun mock exam 費用 (ひよう) N4 Noun cost 補助する (ほじょする) N4 Verb to assist 方針 (ほうしん) N3 Noun policy 固める (かためる) N3 Verb to solidify 進学機会 (しんがくきかい) N/A Noun educational opportunities 確保する (かくほする) N3 Verb to secure 狙い (ねらい) N3 Noun aim 政府 (せいふ) N4 Noun government 11月初旬 (じゅういちがつしょじゅん) N/A Noun early November 決める (きめる) N4 Verb to decide 総合経済対策 (そうごうけいざいたいさく) N/A Noun comprehensive economic measures 盛り込む (もりこむ) N3 Verb to incorporate 上 (うえ) N5 Noun on top of 補正予算案 (ほせいよさんあん) N/A Noun supplementary budget proposal 反映する (はんえいする) N3 Verb to reflect 政府関係者 (せいふかんけいしゃ) N/A Noun government officials 対象 (たいしょう) N3 Noun target 児童扶養手当 (じどうふようてあて) N/A Noun child-rearing allowance 受給する (じゅきゅうする) N3 Verb to receive 住民税非課税世帯 (じゅうみんぜいひかぜいせたい) N/A Noun household exempt from resident tax 検討する (けんとうする) N3 Verb to consider 大学入学共通テスト (だいがくにゅうがくきょうつうてすと) N/A Noun university entrance examination 私立大 (しりつだい) N/A Noun private university 受験料 (じゅけんりょう) N3 Noun examination fee 合計する (ごうけいする) N3 Verb to total 程度 (ていど) N4 Noun degree 想定する (そうていする) N3 Verb to assume 模擬試験の費用 (もぎしけんのひよう) N/A Noun mock exam cost 加える (くわえる) N4 Verb to add 方向 (ほうこう) N3 Noun direction 事業開始 (じぎょうかいし) N/A Noun start of operation 来年度 (らいねんど) N3 Noun next fiscal year 見込む (みこむ) N3 Verb to anticipate 低所得世帯 (ていしょとくせたい) N/A Noun low-income household 授業料 (じゅぎょうりょう) N3 Noun tuition fee 減免制度 (げんめんせいど) N/A Noun reduction system 支援 (しえん) N3 Noun support 不十分 (ふじゅうぶん) N3 な-adjective insufficient 同庁 (どうちょう) N/A Noun same agency 受験 (じゅけん) N3 Noun taking an examination 政府の支援 (せいふのしえん) N/A Noun government support 防ぐ (ふせぐ) N3 Verb to prevent 進学の機会 (しんがくのきかい) N/A Noun opportunity for further education 考える (かんがえる) N4 Verb to think 高橋健次郎 (たかはしかんじろう) N/A Noun Takahashi Kenjiro Grammar and Sentence Structure 対象として児童扶養手当を受給するひとり親世帯と、住民税非課税世帯を検討している。</description></item><item><title>大学受験・模試費用の補助へ　ひとり親、低所得世帯向け　経済対策</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/financial-assistance-for-university-entrance-exams-and-practice-exams-for-single-parents-and-low-income-households-economic-measures/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/financial-assistance-for-university-entrance-exams-and-practice-exams-for-single-parents-and-low-income-households-economic-measures/</guid><description>取材に応じる岸田文雄首相=2023年10月19日、首相官邸、上田幸一撮影 Link to the original article
所得しょとくが低ひくい世帯せたいの進学しんがくを支援しえんするため、こどもこども家庭かてい庁ちょうは、ひとりひとり親おや世帯せたいなどの高校こうこう3年生ねんせいと中学ちゅうがく3年生ねんせいに対たいし、大学だいがく受験じゅけんや模擬試験もぎしけんの費用ひようを補助ほじょする方針ほうしんを固かためた。進学しんがくの機会きかいの確保かくほにつなげる狙ねらい。政府せいふが11月がつ初旬しょじゅんに決きめる総合そうごう経済けいざい対策たいさくに盛もり込こんだ上うえで、補正ほせい予算よさん案あんに反映はんえいする方針ほうしんだ。 政府せいふ関係者かんけいしゃによると、対象たいしょうとして児童扶養手当じどうふようてあてを受給じゅきゅうする一人親世帯ひとりおやせたいと、住民税非課税世帯じゅうみんぜいひかぜいせたいを検討けんとうしている。高校こうこう3年生ねんせいへの大学受験費用だいがくじゅけんひようの補助額ほじょがくは、大学入学共通テストだいがくにゅうがくきょうつうてすとと私立大しりつだいの受験料じゅけんりょうを合計ごうけいした、5万円まんえん程度ていどを想定そうていしている。模擬試験もぎしけんの費用ひようについては、高校こうこう3年生ねんせいに加くわえ、中学ちゅうがく3年生ねんせいも対象たいしょうにする方向ほうこうだ。事業じぎょう開始かいしは、来年度らいねんど以降を見込みこむ。 低所得ていしょとく世帯せたい向けけには授業料じゅぎょうりょうの減免げんめん制度せいどなどがある一方いっぽうで、受験じゅけんに対たいする政府せいふの支援しえんが不十分ふじゅうぶんとの声こえがあがっていた。同庁どうちょうは、模擬試験もぎしけんや受験費用じゅけんひようの支援しえんにより、受験控じゅけんひかえなどを防ふせぎ、進学しんがくの機会きかいにつなげたい考かんがえだ。（高橋健次郎たかはしかんじろう） Vocabulary Word (Furigana) JLPT Level Part of Speech Meaning 所得 (しょとく) N3 Noun income 低い (ひくい) N4 い-adjective low 世帯 (せたい) N3 Noun household 進学 (しんがく) N3 Noun going on to higher education 支援 (しえん) N3 Noun support こども家庭庁 (こどもかていちょう) N1 Noun Ministry of Health, Labour and Welfare ひとり親世帯 (ひとりおやせたい) N1 Noun single-parent household 高校 (こうこう) N5 Noun high school 3年生 (さんねんせい) N5 Noun 3rd year student 中学 (ちゅうがく) N5 Noun junior high school 大学受験 (だいがくじゅけん) N3 Noun university entrance examination 模擬試験 (もぎしけん) N3 Noun mock exam 費用 (ひよう) N4 Noun cost 補助 (ほじょ) N4 Noun assistance 方針 (ほうしん) N3 Noun policy 固める (かためる) N4 Godan verb to solidify 進学機会 (しんがくきかい) N2 Noun educational opportunity 確保 (かくほ) N3 Noun securing つなげる (つなげる) N4 Ichidan verb to connect 狙い (ねらい) N3 Noun aim 政府 (せいふ) N4 Noun government 11月 (じゅういちがつ) N5 Noun November 初旬 (しょじゅん) N3 Noun early days of the month 決める (きめる) N4 Ichidan verb to decide 総合経済対策 (そうごうけいざいたいさく) N1 Noun comprehensive economic measures 盛り込む (もりこむ) N4 Godan verb to incorporate 上 (うえ) N5 Noun on top of 補正予算案 (ほせいよさんあん) N1 Noun supplementary budget proposal 反映する (はんえいする) N3 Suru verb to reflect 政府関係者 (せいふかんけいしゃ) N1 Noun government official 対象 (たいしょう) N3 Noun target 児童扶養手当 (じどうふようてあて) N1 Noun child-rearing allowance 受給する (じゅきゅうする) N3 Suru verb to receive 住民税非課税世帯 (じゅうみんぜいひかぜいせたい) N1 Noun household exempt from resident tax 検討する (けんとうする) N3 Suru verb to consider 大学入学共通テスト (だいがくにゅうがくきょうつうてすと) N1 Noun university entrance examination 私立大 (しりつだい) N2 Noun private university 受験料 (じゅけんりょう) N3 Noun examination fee 合計する (ごうけいする) N3 Suru verb to total 程度 (ていど) N4 Noun degree 想定する (そうていする) N3 Suru verb to assume 加える (くわえる) N4 Ichidan verb to add 方向 (ほうこう) N4 Noun direction 事業開始 (じぎょうかいし) N2 Noun start of business 来年度 (らいねんど) N3 Noun next fiscal year 見込む (みこむ) N4 Godan verb to anticipate 低所得世帯 (ていしょとくせたい) N1 Noun low-income household 授業料 (じゅぎょうりょう) N3 Noun tuition fee 減免制度 (げんめんせいど) N2 Noun reduction and exemption system 政府の支援 (せいふのしえん) N2 Noun government support 不十分 (ふじゅうぶん) N3 な-adjective insufficient 同庁 (どうちょう) N1 Noun same agency 受験 (じゅけん) N3 Noun taking an examination 支援する (しえんする) N3 Suru verb to support 防ぐ (ふせぐ) N4 Godan verb to prevent 進学の機会 (しんがくのきかい) N2 Noun opportunity for higher education 考える (かんがえる) N4 Ichidan verb to think 高橋健次郎 (たかはしかんじろう) N1 Name Takahashi Kenjiro Grammar and Sentence Structure 対象として児童扶養手当を受給するひとり親世帯と、住民税非課税世帯を検討している。 Grammatical points: 対象として (as the target), 児童扶養手当を受給する (receiving child-rearing allowance), ひとり親世帯と (single-parent households), 住民税非課税世帯を (households exempt from resident tax) Structure: This sentence lists the target groups that are being considered for the support, which are single-parent households receiving child-rearing allowance and households exempt from resident tax.</description></item><item><title>「吹奏楽の甲子園」にオホーツクの公立高　遠軽町長感激「町の誇り」</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/the-mayor-of-engaru-a-public-high-school-in-okhotsk-is-deeply-moved-by-the-wind-band-tournament-and-considers-it-as-a-pride-of-the-town/</link><pubDate>Sun, 22 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/the-mayor-of-engaru-a-public-high-school-in-okhotsk-is-deeply-moved-by-the-wind-band-tournament-and-considers-it-as-a-pride-of-the-town/</guid><description>演奏する遠軽=2023年10月22日午前10時1分、名古屋国際会議場、高野良輔撮影 Link to the original article
「吹奏楽すいそうがくのの甲子園こうしえん」といわれる全日本ぜんにほん吹奏楽すいそうがくコンクールこんくーる・高校こうこうの部ぶが22日にちに名古屋市なごやしであり、北海道ほっかいどうオホーツクおほーつく管内かんないの公立こうりつ校こう・遠軽えんがるが、2年ねん連続れんぞくで出場しゅつじょうした。結果けっかは「銀ぎん」だった。 地元じもとの遠軽町えんがるちょうは人口じんこう約1万8千人で、1次産業じさんぎょうがさかんな地域ちいき。町まちは、唯一ゆいいつの高校こうこうである遠軽高えんがるこうへの支援しえんを「政策せいさく」として取り組とりくんでいる。 「下宿生げしゅくせい1人ひとりあたり町まちがが最大さいだい月つき3万まん円えんを助成じょせい」「部活ぶかつで貸かし切きりバスばすを使つかったら1台だいにつき最大さいだい3万まん円えん助成じょせい」――。2022年度ねんどの直接ちょくせつ支援しえんは1億いちおく4千せん万まん円えんを超こえる。吹奏楽すいそうがく局きょくは、昨夏さっかに地元じもとに完成かんせいした音楽おんがくホールを無料むりょうで使つかえるという。 コンクールこんくーる会場の名古屋なごや国際こくさい会議場かいぎじょうには、佐々木ささき修一しゅういち町長ちょうちょうも駆かけつけた。 「2に年ねん連れん続ぞくで全ぜん日に本ほんというだけですごいのに、すばらしい演えん奏そうをしてくれた。吹奏そう楽がく局は町まちの宝たからであり、誇ほこり。町はこれからも最さい大だいの応おう援えん者しゃであり続つづけます」 遠軽高とおがるこうは今年ことし、ラグビー部らぐびーぶも花園はなぞの出場を決きめている。（原知恵子はらちえこ） Vocabulary Word (Furigana) JLPT Level Part of Speech Meaning 吹奏楽 (すいそうがく) N1 Noun brass band; wind ensemble 甲子園 (こうしえん) N1 Noun Koshien (stadium); national high school baseball tournament 全日本 (ぜんにほん) N1 Noun all Japan コンクール N1 Noun competition 高校 (こうこう) N3 Noun high school 部 (ぶ) N4 Noun club; department 名古屋市 (なごやし) N3 Noun Nagoya City 北海道 (ほっかいどう) N3 Noun Hokkaido オホーツク管内 (おほーつくかんない) N1 Noun Okhotsk Subprefecture 公立校 (こうりつこう) N1 Noun public school 遠軽 (とおがる) N1 Noun Togaru (town in Hokkaido) 出場 (しゅつじょう) N3 Noun participation 結果 (けっか) N4 Noun result 銀 (ぎん) N3 Noun silver 人口 (じんこう) N3 Noun population 約 (やく) N4 Adverb approximately 万 (まん) N4 Noun ten thousand 千 (せん) N4 Noun thousand 1次産業 (いちじさんぎょう) N1 Noun primary industry さかん (さかん) N4 Adjective popular; prosperous 唯一 (ゆいいつ) N3 Adjective only; sole 支援 (しえん) N3 Noun support 政策 (せいさく) N3 Noun policy 取り組む (とりくむ) N3 Verb (Godan) to tackle; to deal with 下宿生 (げしゅくせい) N1 Noun boarding student 最大 (さいだい) N3 Noun maximum; largest 月 (つき) N4 Noun month 助成 (じょせい) N3 Noun subsidy 部活 (ぶかつ) N3 Noun club activities 貸し切り (かしきり) N3 Noun charter バス N3 Noun bus 使う (つかう) N4 Verb (Godan) to use 1台 (いちだい) N3 Noun one unit 超える (こえる) N3 Verb (Ichidan) to exceed 吹奏楽局 (すいそうがくきょく) N1 Noun brass band department 昨夏 (さっか) N3 Noun last summer 地元 (じもと) N3 Noun local 完成 (かんせい) N3 Noun completion 音楽ホール (おんがくほーる) N3 Noun music hall 無料 (むりょう) N4 Noun free of charge 佐々木修一 (ささきしゅういち) N1 Name Shuichi Sasaki 町長 (ちょうちょう) N3 Noun mayor 駆けつける (かけつける) N3 Verb (Ichidan) to rush to 全日本 (ぜんにほん) N1 Noun all Japan すばらしい (すばらしい) N4 Adjective wonderful 演奏 (えんそう) N3 Noun performance 宝 (たから) N3 Noun treasure 誇り (ほこり) N3 Noun pride 最大 (さいだい) N3 Noun maximum; largest 応援者 (おうえんしゃ) N3 Noun supporter 続ける (つづける) N4 Verb (Ichidan) to continue ラグビー部 (らぐびーぶ) N3 Noun rugby club 花園 (はなぞの) N3 Noun Hanazono (stadium) 出場 (しゅつじょう) N3 Noun participation 決める (きめる) N4 Verb (Ichidan) to decide 原知恵子 (はらちえこ) N1 Name Chieko Hara Grammar and Sentence Structure 「下宿生1人あたり町が最大月3万円を助成」</description></item><item><title>「本当にショック」遺棄された女性は千葉の高校生、知人らに衝撃</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/the-abandoned-woman-who-was-truly-shocked-is-a-high-school-student-from-chiba-causing-shock-among-acquaintances/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/the-abandoned-woman-who-was-truly-shocked-is-a-high-school-student-from-chiba-causing-shock-among-acquaintances/</guid><description>送検される安栖達也容疑者（左）=栃木県警下野署 Link to the original article
乗用車じょうようしゃの車内しゃないで女性じょせいの遺体いたいを遺棄いきしたとして無職むしょくの男おとこ（28）=埼玉県さいたまけん熊谷市くまがやし=が死体遺棄したいきようき容疑で栃木県警とちぎけんけいに逮捕たいほされた事件じけんで、県警けんけいは21日、亡なくなった女性じょせいは、千葉県ちばけん柏市かしわしの高校こうこう1年ねん、坂巻杏月さかまきあづき（あづき）さん（15）と発表はっぴょうした。 坂巻さかまきさんを幼おさないころから知しる人ひとたちは、事件じけんを知しって一様いちように動揺どうようを隠かくせない様子ようすだった。 坂巻さかまきさんと同おなじじ集合住宅しゅうごうじゅうたくに住すむ40代よんじゅうだい女性じょせいによると、坂巻さかまきさんは4人暮にんぐらしで兄あにがいる。小学校しょうがっこう高学年こうがくねんのころに今いまの家いえに転居てんきょしてきたが、登校班とうこうはんには加くわわらず、母親ははおやに車くるまで学校がっこうまで送おくってもらっていたという。「家族かぞくが杏月あんづきさんを守まもっている印象いんしょうだった」と女性じょせい。 女性じょせいが以前いぜん、自宅前じたくまえに座すわっている坂巻さかまきさんにお菓子おかしをあげあたところ、親おやがお礼おれいに来きてくれたこともあったといい、「仲なかの良よい家族かぞくだなと思おもった」。坂巻さかまきさんについては「あいさつあいさつもしてくれてしっかりしっかりしていた」と話はなし、「事件じけんは本当ほんとうに信しんじられないし、想像そうぞうとかけ離はなれている」と驚おどろいた様子ようすだった。 別べつの40代だい女性じょせいは、坂巻さかまきさんがまだ幼おさない頃ころに、家いえの前まえで兄あにと一緒いっしょにカブトムシかぶとむしを育そだてる姿すがたが印象的いんしょうてきだったという。「母親ははおやが車くるまでどこかへ送おくる姿すがたをよく見みかけた。（坂巻さかまきさんは）いつも私服しはらだった。事件じけんに巻まき込こまれたとしたら本当ほんとうにショックだ」 坂巻さかまきさんが通かよった中学校ちゅうがっこうの同級生どうきゅうせいの一人ひとりによると、坂巻さかまきさんは中学時代ちゅうがくじだい、不登校ふとうこう気味で週しゅう2～3回かいほどしか通学つうがくしていなかったという。 物静ものしずかな性格せいかくだが、仲なかの良よい友人ゆうじんたちとは笑顔えがおで明あかるく接せっしていたという。「元もとクラスメートくらすめーとがこういう事件じけんに遭あったと聞きいてびっくりしている」と肩かたを落おとした。（福岡ふくおか龍一郎りゅういちろう、谷たに瞳児とうじ） Vocabulary Word (Furigana) JLPT Level Part of Speech Meaning 乗用車 (じょうようしゃ) N3 Noun passenger car 車内 (しゃない) N3 Noun inside the car 女性 (じょせい) N5 Noun woman 遺体 (いたい) N3 Noun dead body 遺棄 (いき) N2 Noun abandonment 無職 (むしょく) N2 Noun unemployed 男 (おとこ) N5 Noun man 埼玉県 (さいたまけん) N4 Noun Saitama Prefecture 熊谷市 (くまがいし) N4 Noun Kumagai City 死体遺棄 (したいいき) N1 Noun corpse abandonment 容疑 (ようぎ) N3 Noun suspicion 栃木県警 (とちぎけんけい) N1 Noun Tochigi Prefectural Police 逮捕 (たいほ) N3 Noun arrest 事件 (じけん) N4 Noun incident 亡くなる (なくなる) N4 Verb to pass away 千葉県 (ちばけん) N4 Noun Chiba Prefecture 柏市 (かしわし) N4 Noun Kashiwa City 高校 (こうこう) N5 Noun high school 1年 (いちねん) N5 Noun first year 発表 (はっぴょう) N3 Noun announcement 幼い (おさない) N4 Adjective young 知る (しる) N5 Verb to know 人 (ひと) N5 Noun person 一様 (いちよう) N2 Adjective uniform 動揺 (どうよう) N2 Noun agitation 隠せる (かくせる) N2 Verb to hide 様子 (ようす) N4 Noun state 同じ (おなじ) N5 Adjective same 集合住宅 (しゅうごうじゅうたく) N2 Noun apartment complex 住む (すむ) N5 Verb to live 40代 (よんじゅうだい) N2 Noun 40s 女性 (じょせい) N5 Noun woman 4人暮らし (よにんぐらし) N2 Noun living with four people 兄 (あに) N5 Noun older brother 小学校 (しょうがっこう) N5 Noun elementary school 高学年 (こうがくねん) N3 Noun upper grades 今 (いま) N5 Noun now 家 (いえ) N5 Noun house 転居 (てんきょ) N3 Noun moving 登校班 (とうこうはん) N2 Noun school commuting group 加わる (くわわる) N4 Verb to join 母親 (ははおや) N5 Noun mother 学校 (がっこう) N5 Noun school 送る (おくる) N5 Verb to send 守る (まもる) N5 Verb to protect 印象 (いんしょう) N3 Noun impression 以前 (いぜん) N4 Noun before 自宅前 (じたくまえ) N2 Noun in front of one&amp;rsquo;s house 座る (すわる) N5 Verb to sit お菓子 (おかし) N5 Noun snack あげる N5 Verb to give 親 (おや) N5 Noun parent 来る (くる) N5 Verb to come 仲 (なか) N5 Noun relationship 良い (いい) N5 Adjective good 家族 (かぞく) N5 Noun family あいさつ N5 Noun greeting する N5 Verb to do しっかり N4 Adverb firmly 事件 (じけん) N4 Noun incident 本当に (ほんとうに) N5 Adverb really 信じられない (しんじられない) N3 Adjective unbelievable 想像 (そうぞう) N3 Noun imagination 離れる (はなれる) N5 Verb to separate 驚く (おどろく) N5 Verb to be surprised 別の (べつの) N4 Adjective another 幼い (おさない) N4 Adjective young 頃 (ころ) N5 Noun time 家 (いえ) N5 Noun house 兄 (あに) N5 Noun older brother 一緒 (いっしょ) N5 Adverb together カブトムシ N5 Noun rhinoceros beetle 育てる (そだてる) N5 Verb to raise 姿 (すがた) N5 Noun figure 母親 (ははおや) N5 Noun mother どこかへ N5 Adverb somewhere 送る (おくる) N5 Verb to send 私服 (しふく) N3 Noun civilian clothes 事件 (じけん) N4 Noun incident 巻き込む (まきこむ) N3 Verb to involve 本当に (ほんとうに) N5 Adverb really ショック N4 Noun shock 通る (とおる) N5 Verb to pass 中学校 (ちゅうがっこう) N5 Noun middle school 同級生 (どうきゅうせい) N4 Noun classmate 一人 (ひとり) N5 Noun one person 中学時代 (ちゅうがくじだい) N3 Noun middle school days 不登校 (ふとうこう) N3 Noun truancy 気味 (ぎみ) N4 Noun tendency 週 (しゅう) N5 Noun week 通学 (つうがく) N3 Noun commuting to school 明るい (あかるい) N5 Adjective bright 接する (せっする) N3 Verb to interact 元 (もと) N5 Noun former クラスメート N5 Noun classmate 遭う (あう) N5 Verb to encounter 聞く (きく) N5 Verb to hear びっくり N5 Noun surprise 肩 (かた) N5 Noun shoulder 落とす (おとす) N5 Verb to drop 福岡 (ふくおか) N4 Noun Fukuoka 龍一郎 (りゅういちろう) N4 Noun Ryuichiro 谷 (たに) N5 Noun valley 瞳児 (ひとみじ) N4 Noun Hitomiji Grammar and Sentence Structure &amp;ldquo;坂巻さんを幼いころから知る人たちは、事件を知って一様に動揺を隠せない様子だった。&amp;rdquo;</description></item><item><title>傷害事件で男性に無罪判決　被害者「供述はうそ」　岡山地裁倉敷支部</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/injury-case-male-acquitted-victim-claims-testimony-is-a-lie-okayama-district-court-kurashiki-branch/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/injury-case-male-acquitted-victim-claims-testimony-is-a-lie-okayama-district-court-kurashiki-branch/</guid><description>裁判 Link to the original article
岡山県おかやまけん倉敷市くらしきし内をを走行中そうこうちゅうの自動車じどうしゃ内でで2021年ねん7月がつ、部下ぶかを殴なぐって大おおけがを負おわせたなどとして、傷害しょうがいの罪つみに問とわれた同市内どうしないの塗装業とそうぎょうの男性だんせい（32）に対たいし、岡山地裁おかやまちさい倉敷支部くらしきしぶ（横沢慶太裁判官よこさわけいたさいばんかん）は20日にち、無罪むざい（求刑きゅうけい罰金ばっきん30万まん円）を言いい渡わたした。 男性だんせいは21年ねん7月がつ26日にち朝あさ、走行そうこうしていた車内しゃないで男性部下だんせいぶかを手ての甲こうで殴なぐり、眼底骨折がんていこんせつの約やく3カ月かげつの大おおけがを負おわせたなどとして逮捕たいほされ、昨年さくねん5月がつに倉敷区検くらしきくけんが在宅ざいたくで略式起訴りゃくしききそしていた。 男性だんせいは同月どうげつ、倉敷くらしき簡裁かんさいから罰金ばっきん30万円まんえんの略式りゃくしき命令めいれいを受うけたが、正式せいしき裁判さいばんを申もうし立たてた。簡裁かんさいでの公判こうはんで男性だんせいは、それまで認みとめていた起訴きそ内容ないようについて、否ひ認にんに転てんじたという。そのため、事件じけんは地裁ちさい倉敷くらしき支部しぶに移送いそうされた。「逮捕たいほされ、早はやく身柄みがらを解放かいほうされたかった」という理由りゆうで当初とうしょは認みとめていたという。 公判こうはんでは、被害者ひがいしゃとされていた男性部下だんせいぶかが出廷しゅっていし「別べつの知人ちじんの男おとこに暴行ぼうこうを受うけた。男性だんせいに日頃ひごろから不満ふまんがあり、嘘うそをついた」という趣旨しゅしの証言しょうげんをしたという。さらに、この別べつの男おとこが暴行ぼうこうしているのを見みたという目撃証言もくげきしょうげんも存在そんざい。暴行ぼうこうしたと指摘してきされた男おとこは、証人尋問しょうにんじんもんに出廷しゅっていするよう求もとめられたが、現あらわれなかったという。 判決はんけつは、被害状況ひがいじょうきょうを説明せつめいした部下ぶかの供述きょうじゅつと、自白じはくしていた男性だんせいの捜査段階そうさだんかいの供述きょうじゅつについて、いずれも「信用しんようできない」と否定ひていした。ほかの証拠しょうこなどからも男性だんせいによる暴行ぼうこうを推測すいそくできない、とした。 無罪むざい判決はんけつを受うけ、男性だんせいは「無罪むざいはうれしいうれしい。逮捕たいほするならちゃんと証拠しょうこを集あつめてからにしてほしかった」。岡山おかやま地検ちけんの松本まつもと朗次ろうじ席検事せきけんじは「判決はんけつ内容ないようを精査せいさし、上級庁じょうきゅうちょうとも協議きょうぎの上うえ、適切てきせつに対応たいおうしたい」とのコメントコメントを出だした。（上山うえやま崎ざき雅泰まさやす） Vocabulary Word (Furigana) JLPT Level Part of Speech Meaning 走行する (そうこうする) N3 Verb to drive 殴る (なぐる) N3 Verb to hit 負わせる (おわせる) N3 Verb to inflict 言い渡す (いいわたす) N3 Verb to pronounce 逮捕する (たいほする) N3 Verb to arrest 認める (みとめる) N3 Verb to admit 略式起訴する (りゃくしききそする) N3 Verb to prosecute summarily 略式命令を受ける (りゃくしきめいれいをうける) N3 Verb to receive a summary order 転じる (てんじる) N3 Verb to change 移送する (いそうする) N3 Verb to transfer 解放する (かいほうする) N3 Verb to release 出廷する (しゅっていする) N3 Verb to appear in court 指摘する (してきする) N3 Verb to point out 精査する (せいさする) N3 Verb to examine thoroughly 対応する (たいおうする) N3 Verb to respond 証拠を集める (しょうこをあつめる) N3 Verb to gather evidence 説明する (せつめいする) N3 Verb to explain 否定する (ひていする) N3 Verb to deny 推認する (すいにんする) N3 Verb to infer 精査する (せいさする) N3 Verb to examine thoroughly 協議する (きょうぎする) N3 Verb to discuss 求刑する (きゅうけいする) N2 Verb to demand a sentence 言い渡す (いいわたす) N2 Verb to pronounce 逮捕する (たいほする) N2 Verb to arrest 負わせる (おわせる) N2 Verb to inflict 略式起訴する (りゃくしききそする) N2 Verb to prosecute summarily 略式命令を受ける (りゃくしきめいれいをうける) N2 Verb to receive a summary order 転じる (てんじる) N2 Verb to change 移送する (いそうする) N2 Verb to transfer 解放する (かいほうする) N2 Verb to release 出廷する (しゅっていする) N2 Verb to appear in court 指摘する (してきする) N2 Verb to point out 精査する (せいさする) N2 Verb to examine thoroughly Grammar and Sentence Structure 男性は同月、倉敷簡裁から罰金30万円の略式命令を受けたが、正式裁判を申し立てた。</description></item><item><title>「月6千円程度が妥当」　介護職の賃上げめぐり、武見厚労相</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/approximately-6-000-yen-per-month-is-reasonable-minister-of-health-labour-and-welfare-takami-regarding-wage-increases-for-caregivers/</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/approximately-6-000-yen-per-month-is-reasonable-minister-of-health-labour-and-welfare-takami-regarding-wage-increases-for-caregivers/</guid><description>小規模多機能型居宅介護施設「ひつじ雲」を視察後、記者団の質問に答える武見敬三厚生労働相=2023年10月19日、川崎市、藤谷和広撮影 Link to the original article
月内げつないに政府せいふがまとめる経済対策けいざいたいさくに盛り込むもりこむ方針ほうしんの介護職かいごしょくらの賃上げちんあげについて、武見敬三たけみけいぞう厚生労働相こうせいろうどうしょうは19日にち、「（賃上げちんあげ額は月つき）6千せん円程度ていどが妥当だとう」との認識にんしきを示しめした。川崎市かわさきしの介護施設かいごしせつを視察しさつ後、記者団きしゃだんの質問しつもんに答こたえた。 介護かいご分野ぶんやでは、他た産業さんぎょうの相次あいつぐ賃上ちんあげによって人材じんざい流出りゅうしゅつが起おき、人手不足ひとでぶそくが深刻化しんこくかしている。今年ことしの春闘しゅんとうでは、全産業ぜんさんぎょう平均へいきんで3・6%の賃上ちんあげがあった一方いっぽう、介護かいごや医療いりょうなどの分野ぶんやでは1%台だいにとどまった。政府せいふは緊急きんきゅうの処遇しょぐう改善かいぜん策さくが必要ひつようと判断はんだんし、経済対策けいざいたいさくに介護職かいごしょくや看護補助者かんごほじょしゃの賃上ちんあげを盛もり込こむ方針ほうしん。月つき6千せん円引ひき上あげる案あんを軸じくに最終さいしゅう調整ちょうせいしている。 武見たけみ氏は、賃上ちんあげ幅について問とわれ、財政当局ざいせいとうきょくとも調整ちょうせいしているとしたうえで、「6千せん円程度ていどが妥当だとうな線せんになってくるのではないか」と発言はつげん。「本当ほんとうのことを言いえばもっと多おおいに越こしたことはない。通常つうじょうの労働者ろうどうしゃの平均へいきん賃金ちんぎんと同等どうとうになるように努力どりょくし続つづける」とも述のべた。 賃上ちんあげをめぐっては、業界ぎょうかい団体だんたいから、深刻しんこくな労働力ろうどうりょく不足ふそくを止とめるためには「月つき6千せん円ではでは不十分ふじゅうぶん」との声こえが上あがっている。（藤谷ふじたに和広かずひろ） Vocabulary Word (Furigana) JLPT Level Part of Speech Meaning 月内 (げつない) N1 Noun within the month 政府 (せいふ) N3 Noun government まとめる N3 Verb (Ichidan) to summarize 経済対策 (けいざいたいさく) N2 Noun economic measures 盛り込む (もりこむ) N2 Verb (Godan) to include 方針 (ほうしん) N3 Noun policy 介護職 (かいごしょく) N3 Noun caregiving profession 賃上げ (ちんあげ) N3 Noun wage increase ついて N3 Particle about 武見敬三 (たけみけいぞう) N/A Proper Noun Keizo Takemi (name) 厚生労働相 (こうせいろうどうしょう) N/A Proper Noun Minister of Health, Labour and Welfare 19日 (じゅうくにち) N/A Noun 19th day 認識 (にんしき) N3 Noun recognition 示す (しめす) N3 Verb (Godan) to indicate 川崎市 (かわさきし) N/A Proper Noun Kawasaki City 介護施設 (かいごしせつ) N3 Noun caregiving facility 視察 (しさつ) N3 Noun inspection 後 (ご) N3 Noun after 記者団 (きしゃだん) N/A Noun press corps 質問 (しつもん) N3 Noun question 答える (こたえる) N3 Verb (Ichidan) to answer 分野 (ぶんや) N3 Noun field 他 (ほか) N3 Noun other 産業 (さんぎょう) N3 Noun industry 相次ぐ (あいつぐ) N2 Verb (Godan) to follow one another 人材流出 (じんざいりゅうしゅつ) N/A Noun talent outflow 起きる (おきる) N5 Verb (Godan) to occur 人手不足 (ひとでぶそく) N3 Noun labor shortage 深刻化 (しんこくか) N/A Noun intensification 今年 (ことし) N5 Noun this year 春闘 (しゅんとう) N/A Noun annual spring labor offensive 全産業平均 (ぜんさんぎょうへいきん) N/A Noun average of all industries 3・6% (さんてんろっぱーせん) N/A Noun 3.</description></item><item><title>旧ジャニーズ白波瀬氏が退職　補償対応で「引き続き協力してもらう」</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/former-johnny-s-talent-manager-shiranami-sei-resigns-continued-cooperation-is-requested-for-compensation-support/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/former-johnny-s-talent-manager-shiranami-sei-resigns-continued-cooperation-is-requested-for-compensation-support/</guid><description>「SMILE―UP.」（旧ジャニーズ事務所）のビル=東京都港区 Link to the original article
故ジャニージャニー喜多川氏しによる性加害せいかがい問題で、旧ジャニーズジャニーズ事務所（現・SMILE―UP.スマイルアップ）の副社長ふくしゃちょうを引責いんせき辞任し、その後嘱託職員しょくたくしょくいんとして在籍ざいせきしていた白波瀬傑しらなみせいけつ氏が、15日付ひづけで嘱託職員しょくたくしょくいんとしての契約けいやくも終了しゅうりょうし、事務所じむしょを退職たいしょくしていた。18日にちに事務所じむしょが朝日新聞あさひしんぶんの取材しゅざいに明あきらかにした。白波瀬しらなみ氏は現在げんざい、関連会社かんれんがいしゃも含ふくめ契約関係けいやくかんけいになく、グループ会社ぐるーぷがいしゃに就職しゅうしょくした事実じじつもないと説明せつめい。一方で、被害ひがいに遭あったとして補償ほしょうを求もとめる人ひとの在籍ざいせき確認かくにんなどを行おこなうにあたり、事務所じむしょは「引ひき続つづき、協力きょうりょくしてもらう予定よてい」としている。 事務所じむしょによると、白波瀬氏しらなみせしは、副社長ふくしゃちょうを引責辞任ひきせきじにんした後、嘱託社員しょくたくしゃいんとして、役員やくいんとしての業務ぎょうむや広報こうほうやメディアめでぃあ関係の業務ぎょうむの引継ひきつぎを行おこなっていたという。 同社どうしゃが設置せっちした再発防止さいはつぼうし特別チームちーむの調査ちょうさ報告書ほうこくしょで、白波瀬しらなみせさんは、ジャニーじゃにーさんの姉あねで、経営けいえいの実権じっけんを握にぎっていた故ゆえメリー喜多川めりーきたがわさんや、前社長ぜんしゃちょうの藤島ジュリー景子ふじしまじゅりーけいこさんらと共ともに、ジャニーじゃにーさんに対たいする監視かんし・監督かんとく義務ぎむを全まったく果はたさず、性加害せいかがいの継続けいぞくを許ゆるす要因よういんになったなどと指摘してきされていた。 ただ、同社どうしゃが9月がつ7日にちと10月がつ2日にちに開ひらいた会見かいけんには欠席けっせき。説明せつめいを求もとめる声こえが上あがっていた。2日にちの会見かいけんで東山紀之社長ひがしやまきのしゃちょうも白波瀬氏しらなみせいについて「説明責任せつめいせきにんはあると思おもう」と述のべている。 調査ちょうさ報告書ほうこくしょによると、白波瀬しらなみせ氏は、メリーめりー氏に誘さそわれ、1975年ねんに「渡辺わたなべプロダクション」からジャニーズじゃにーず事務所に入社にゅうしゃ。82年ねんに創設そうせつされた宣伝部せんでんぶで宣伝せんでんを担当たんとう。メリーめりー氏の指示しじで、取材対応しゅざいたいおうなどを行おこなっていたという。96年ねんに取締役とりしまりやくに就任しゅうにん。2019年ねんに副社長ふくしゃちょうに就任しゅうにんした。 Vocabulary Word (Furigana) JLPT Level Part of Speech Meaning 引責辞任 (いんせきじにん) N1 Noun resignation to take responsibility 嘱託職員 (しょくたくしょくいん) N1 Noun contract employee 在籍 (ざいせき) N2 Noun enrollment 退職 (たいしょく) N3 Noun retirement 明らか (あきらか) N3 な-adjective clear 関連 (かんれん) N3 Noun relation 会社 (かいしゃ) N5 Noun company 就職 (しゅうしょく) N4 Noun employment 事実 (じじつ) N3 Noun fact 説明 (せつめい) N4 Noun explanation 被害 (ひがい) N3 Noun damage 求める (もとめる) N4 Godan verb to seek 在籍確認 (ざいせきかくにん) N1 Noun confirmation of enrollment 協力 (きょうりょく) N3 Noun cooperation 引継ぎ (ひきつぎ) N3 Noun handover 設置 (せっち) N2 Noun establishment 再発防止 (さいはつぼうし) N1 Noun prevention of recurrence 特別 (とくべつ) N4 な-adjective special チーム (ちーむ) N5 Noun team 調査 (ちょうさ) N3 Noun investigation 報告書 (ほうこくしょ) N3 Noun report 監視 (かんし) N3 Noun monitoring 監督 (かんとく) N3 Noun supervision 義務 (ぎむ) N3 Noun obligation 継続 (けいぞく) N3 Noun continuation 指摘 (してき) N3 Noun pointing out 欠席 (けっせき) N3 Noun absence 説明責任 (せつめいせきにん) N1 Noun responsibility to explain 入社 (にゅうしゃ) N4 Noun joining a company 宣伝 (せんでん) N3 Noun publicity 取締役 (とりしまりやく) N1 Noun director Grammar and Sentence Structure 白波瀬氏は現在、関連会社も含め契約関係になく、グループ会社に就職した事実もないと説明。</description></item><item><title>フリースクールは「国家の根幹を崩しかねない」　東近江市長が発言</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/the-mayor-of-higashiomi-city-says-that-freestyle-schools-could-undermine-the-foundation-of-the-nation/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/the-mayor-of-higashiomi-city-says-that-freestyle-schools-could-undermine-the-foundation-of-the-nation/</guid><description>小椋正清・東近江市長 Link to the original article
不登校ふとうこう対策たいさくについて議論ぎろんする滋賀県しがけんの首長会議しゅちょうかいぎが17日にちにあり、この中なかで出席者しゅっせきしゃの1人にんの小椋正清おぐらまさきよ・東近江市ひがしおうみし長ちょうが「フリースクールふりーすくーるは国家こっかの根幹こんかんを崩くずしてしまうことになりかねない。よっぽど慎重しんちょうに考かんがえないといけない」と発言はつげんした。 この日ひの首長会議しゅちょうかいぎでは、県けんが年度ねんど内にないまとめる予定よていの不登校ふとうこう対策のの基本理念きほんりねんについて議論ぎろんされ、報道陣ほうどうじんに公開こうかいされた。 小椋市長おぐらしちょうは「文部科学省もんぶかがくしょうがフリースクールふりーすくーるの存在そんざいを認みとめたことにがくぜんがくぜんとしている。大半たいはんの善良ぜんりょうな市民しみんは、嫌いやがる子供こどもに無理むりしてでも義務教育ぎむきょういくを受うけさせようとしている」と述のべた。 また、フリースクールふりーすくーるへの財政支援ざいせいしえんについて「ごく少数しょうすうの人ひとに対たいして、負担ふたんをみなさい、というのはフリースクールふりーすくーるに行いきたいという雪崩現象なだれげんしょうが起おこる怖こわさを感かんじる」とも発言はつげんした。 2016年ねんに成立した教育機会確保法きょういくきかいかくほうでは、フリースクールふりーすくーるなど学校以外がっこういがいの「多様たようで適切てきせつな学習活動がくしゅうかつどうの重要性じゅうようせい」が明記めいきされ、国くにや自治体じちたいに対たいし必要ひつような財政支援ざいせいしえんに努つとめるよう求もとめている。ただ、滋賀県しがけん内ないでフリースクールふりーすくーるなどの民間施設みんかんしせつの利用者りようしゃ向けけに補助制度ほじょせいどなどを設もうけているのは彦根市ひこねしや甲賀市こうかしなどで、ばらつきばらつきがある。 首長会議しゅちょうかいぎ後に、報道陣ほうどうじんに発言はつげんの真意しんいを問とわれた小椋市長おぐらしちょうは「不登校ふとうこうは大半たいはんは親おやの責任せきにん。財政支援ざいせいしえんを国くにが言いうべきではない。（フリースクールふりーすくーるの）存在そんざいを認みとめるかどうかの論議ろんぎをもっとすべきだ」と述のべた。 小椋おぐら氏は元もと県警けんけい警察官けいさつかんで、県けんの防災ぼうさい危機きき管理かんり監かんなどを務つとめた後ご、13年ねん2月がつに同どう市長しちょうに初当選しょとうせん。17年ねん、21年ねんと2期き連続れんぞくで無投票むとうひょう当選とうせんしている。 東近江市ひがしおうみしは滋賀県しがけん東部とうぶに位置いちし、05年ねんに旧きゅう八日市市ようかいちしや永源寺町えいげんじちょうなどが合併がっぺいして誕生たんじょう。JR能登川駅のとがわえきの周辺しゅうへんはベッドタウンべっどたうんになっている。人口じんこうは約やく11万まん2千人せんにん。（林はやし利香りか） Vocabulary Word (Furigana) JLPT Level Part of Speech Meaning 不登校 (ふとうこう) N3 Noun truancy 対策 (たいさく) N3 Noun countermeasure 首長 (しゅちょう) N3 Noun chief executive 会議 (かいぎ) N4 Noun meeting 出席者 (しゅっせきしゃ) N3 Noun attendee 小椋 (おぐら) Proper Noun N/A Ogura (surname) 正清 (まさきよ) Proper Noun N/A Masakiyo (given name) 東近江 (ひがしおうみ) Proper Noun N/A Higashiomi (city name) 市長 (しちょう) N4 Noun mayor フリースクール N/A Noun free school 国家 (こっか) N3 Noun nation 根幹 (こんかん) N3 Noun foundation 崩す (くずす) N3 Godan verb to destroy 慎重 (しんちょう) N3 な-adjective cautious 考える (かんがえる) N4 Ichidan verb to think 文部科学省 (もんぶかがくしょう) Proper Noun N/A Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology 存在 (そんざい) N3 Noun existence 認める (みとめる) N4 Ichidan verb to recognize 善良 (ぜんりょう) N3 な-adjective good 市民 (しみん) N4 Noun citizen 無理 (むり) N4 Noun impossible 義務教育 (ぎむきょういく) N3 Noun compulsory education 受ける (うける) N4 Ichidan verb to receive 述べる (のべる) N4 Ichidan verb to state 財政支援 (ざいせいしえん) N3 Noun financial support ごく少数 (ごくしょうすう) N3 Noun very few 負担 (ふたん) N3 Noun burden 雪崩現象 (なだれげんしょう) N3 Noun avalanche phenomenon 起こる (おこる) N4 Godan verb to occur 怖さ (こわさ) N4 Noun fear 言う (いう) N5 Godan verb to say 認める (みとめる) N4 Ichidan verb to recognize 論議 (ろんぎ) N3 Noun discussion 責任 (せきにん) N4 Noun responsibility 言う (いう) N5 Godan verb to say Grammar and Sentence Structure 「大半の善良な市民は、嫌がる子どもに無理してでも義務教育を受けさせようとしている」と述べた。 1.</description></item><item><title>谷村新司さん死去、アリスのメンバーが談話　「来年のツアーに…」</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/singer-shinsuke-kazamura-passes-away-members-of-alice-release-statement-for-next-year-s-tour/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/singer-shinsuke-kazamura-passes-away-members-of-alice-release-statement-for-next-year-s-tour/</guid><description>「今、これまでで最高のアリスを見せられているんじゃないかな」。2019年当時、そう語っていた谷村新司さん Link to the original article
シンガーしんがー・ソングライターそんぐらいたーの谷村新司たにむらしんじさんが死去しきょした。74歳さいだった。 谷村たにむらさんの死去しきょを受うけけ、「アリスありす」のメンバーめんばーの堀内孝雄ほりうちたかおさんと矢沢透やざわとおるさんが、谷村たにむらさんの公式こうしきのX（旧きゅうツイッター）を通つうじてコメントを出だした。全文ぜんぶんは次つぎのとおり（原文げんぶんママ）。 チンペイちんぺいさん 突然とつぜんの別わかれに驚おどろきを隠かくせません。 来年らいねんのツアーつあーに向むけて回復かいふくに向むかっていると伺うかがっていただけに、とても残念ざんねんです。 僕ぼくにとってのチンペイちんぺいさんは、50年来ねんらいの親友しんゆうであり、「アリスありす」のリーダーりーだーであり、そして良よきライバルらいばるでした。 学生時代に、「プロぷろにならないかと？一緒にアリスありすをやろう」と、誘ってくれたとき、心こころの底そこから嬉うれしかった。 チンペイちんぺいさんが、あの時誘さそってくれなかったら、今いまの僕ぼくはありません。ずっと一緒いっしょに音楽活動おんがくかつどうができたことが幸しあわせでした。 また、いつか空そらのほとりほとりで一緒いっしょにライブらいぶをやろうね。もうちょっと待まっていてね、キンきんちゃんと、もう少すこしだけ頑張がんばるね。 心こころから、ありがとうありがとう。安やすらかに。ご冥福めいふくをお祈いのり申もうし上あげます。 堀内ほりうち孝雄たかお 東京とうきょうに住すむ僕ぼくと大阪おおさかに住すむ谷村たにむらと、何なにの因果いんがか運命うんめいの出会であいか 堀内ほりうちを紹介しょうかいされ3人アリスありすとして歩あるみ始はじめました 時ときには争いがみ合あい、時ときには抱だき合あい 幾多いくたの苦難くなんも喜びよろこびも共有きょうゆうし、無我夢中むがむちゅうで駆かけ抜ぬけた そして気きが付つけば51年ねんという長ながきに渡わたって谷村たにむらと関かかわるとは… あの日ひからは想像そうぞうもしませんでした。 若わかさの灰汁あくも抜ぬけ「これからは本当ほんとうに音楽おんがくを楽たのしんでやっていこうね」と新あたらしいアリスありすの始はじまりに胸躍むなおどらせていた矢先やさきのことでした。 谷村たにむらなら大丈夫、谷村たにむらならきっと戻もどってくる、根拠こんきょのない確信かくしんめいたものを感かんじておりました。 でも谷村たにむらは戻もどってきませんでした！ もうもういないいないんです。悲かなしいというより悔くやしいんです。 谷村たにむらはもう僕ぼくたちのみんなの心こころの中なかにしか住すむ場所ばしょがないのです。 思おもい出だせば必かならず胸むねにやってきます、どうか谷村たにむらを忘わすれないで下ください。 今まで谷村たにむらをアリスありすを応援してくださってありがとうございました。 矢沢やざわ透とおる 日本テレビ系の「24にじゅうよじかんテレビ」のテーマ曲「サライさらい」を、1992年の同番組内で谷村新司たにむらしんじさんと2人で作るなど、親交しんこうのあった歌手かしゅ・俳優はいゆうの加山雄三かやまゆうぞうさんが公式こうしきサイトでコメントを公表こうひょうした。全文は次の通り。 I'm sorry, but it seems like you haven't provided any words or phrases for me to annotate. Could you please provide a word or phrase in Japanese that you would like me to annotate? 谷村君たにむらくんが亡なくなったこと、先さきほど知しりました。ショックと悲かなしみで正直しょうじき混乱こんらんしています。 ちんぺいちんぺいとは「サライサライ」をはじめたくさんの思い出があります。ヤンチャーズ楽しかったよな。たくさんの場所で一緒に歌ったよな！陶芸とうげいに誘ってくれた兄弟子せんぱいでもあるし、いつもちんぺいには「加山かやまさん勝負しょうぶじゃないんだから！」って言われてたっけ。 ほんとほんとの兄弟きょうだいのように慕したってくれて一緒いっしょにいる時ときは本当ほんとうにいつも楽たのしかったよ。その兄想おもいの弟おとうとが先さきに逝いってしまった。 今、気持きもちをまとめてくれと言いわれても、彼かれに伝つたえたいことはたくさんあって、言いい切きれないよ。一言ひとことだけ彼かれに伝つたえるなら、やっぱり ありがとうありがとう この感謝かんしゃの言葉ことばしか見当みあたりません。 永遠の「サライ」さらいを谷村たにむらくんと共に… 加山雄三かやま ゆうぞう Vocabulary Word (Furigana) JLPT Level Part of Speech Meaning 死去 (しきょ) N3 Noun death 公式 (こうしき) N3 Noun official ツイッター N3 Noun Twitter 通じる (つうじる) N3 Godan verb to reach, to be understood コメント N3 Noun comment 驚き (おどろき) N3 Noun surprise 隠す (かくす) N3 Godan verb to hide, to conceal 回復 (かいふく) N3 Noun recovery 残念 (ざんねん) N3 な-adjective regrettable, disappointing 親友 (しんゆう) N3 Noun close friend リーダー N3 Noun leader 良き (よき) N3 い-adjective good ライバル N3 Noun rival 学生時代 (がくせいじだい) N3 Noun student days プロ N3 Noun professional 一緒に (いっしょに) N3 Adverb together 誘う (さそう) N3 Godan verb to invite 心の底 (こころのそこ) N3 Noun deep in one&amp;rsquo;s heart 嬉しい (うれしい) N3 い-adjective happy ずっと N3 Adverb continuously, for a long time 音楽活動 (おんがくかつどう) N3 Noun musical activities 幸せ (しあわせ) N3 な-adjective happiness 空 (そら) N3 Noun sky ほとり N3 Noun riverside ライブ N3 Noun live performance 待つ (まつ) N3 Godan verb to wait 頑張る (がんばる) N3 Godan verb to do one&amp;rsquo;s best 心から (こころから) N3 Adverb sincerely 安らか (やすらか) N3 な-adjective peaceful 冥福 (めいふく) N3 Noun repose of the soul お祈り (おいのり) N3 Noun prayer 公表 (こうひょう) N3 Noun announcement 知る (しる) N4 Godan verb to know 混乱 (こんらん) N4 Noun confusion 歌手 (かしゅ) N4 Noun singer 俳優 (はいゆう) N4 Noun actor 公式サイト (こうしきさいと) N4 Noun official website 兄弟 (きょうだい) N4 Noun siblings 兄弟子 (あにでし) N4 Noun senior (in a profession) 伝える (つたえる) N4 Ichidan verb to convey, to tell 感謝 (かんしゃ) N4 Noun gratitude 共に (ともに) N4 Adverb together 逝く (いく) N4 Godan verb to pass away 慕う (したう) N4 Godan verb to yearn for, to long for 楽しい (たのしい) N5 い-adjective enjoyable 歌う (うたう) N5 Godan verb to sing 誘う (さそう) N5 Godan verb to invite 言う (いう) N5 Godan verb to say 見当たる (みあたる) N5 Godan verb to be found 共に (ともに) N5 Adverb together 伝える (つたえる) N5 Ichidan verb to convey, to tell ありがとう N5 Phrase thank you Grammar and Sentence Structure &amp;ldquo;僕にとってのチンペイさんは、50年来の親友であり、「アリス」のリーダーであり、そして良きライバルでした。&amp;rdquo; Grammatical points: The sentence uses the particle &amp;ldquo;にとって&amp;rdquo; to indicate a subjective perspective or personal opinion.</description></item><item><title>札幌の３４年五輪招致絶望的</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/desperate-situation-for-sapporo-s-bid-for-the-34th-olympics/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/desperate-situation-for-sapporo-s-bid-for-the-34th-olympics/</guid><description>インドのムンバイで開かれた国際オリンピック委員会（ＩＯＣ）総会＝１５日（ＩＯＣ提供・共同） Link to the original article
【むんばいきょうどう】国際オリンピック委員会（ＩＯＣアイオーシー）は１５日、インドインドのムンバイムンバイで開ひらいた総会そうかいで２０３０年ねんと３４年ねんの冬季五輪とうきごりん開催地かいさいちを同時決定どうじけっていすることを正式決定せいしきけっていした。３０年ねん大会の招致しょうちを断念だんねんした札幌市さっぽろしは、３４年ねん大会の開催かいさいも絶望的ぜつぼうてきとなった。 ３０さんじゅう年はスウェーデンスウェーデンやフランスフランスなどが候補こうほで、３４さんじゅうよん年は米べいソルトレークシティーソルトレークシティーが有力ゆうりょくされる。１１月じゅういちがつ末まつからの理事会りじかいで候補地こうほちを絞り込しめりこみ、来夏らいなつの総会そうかい（パリパリ）で決定けっていする方針ほうしん。 夏季かき五輪ごりんではＩＯＣアイオーシーが２４にじゅうよん年ねんパリパリ、２８にじゅうはち年ねんロサンゼルスロサンゼルス両りょう大会たいかいを同時どうじ決定けっていで１７じゅうなな年ねんに選えらんでいる。 総会そうかいでは２５年ねんでの退任たいにんが決きまっているバッハばっは会長かいちょう（６９）の任期にんき延長えんちょうを求もとめる声こえがＩＯＣ委員いいんから相次あいついだ。 総会そうかいは１７日にちまで３日間にちかん開かれ、１６日にちは２８年ねん五輪の追加競技ついかきょうぎとして野球やきゅう・ソフトボールそふとぼーるやラクロスらくろすなど５競技きょうぎの決定けっていを諮はかる。（共同きょうどう） Vocabulary Word (Furigana) JLPT Level Part of Speech Meaning 開催 (かいさい) N3 Noun holding (an event) 決定 (けってい) N3 Noun decision 断念 (だんねん) N3 Noun giving up 絶望的 (ぜつぼうてき) N3 な-adjective hopeless 候補 (こうほ) N3 Noun candidate 有力 (ゆうりょく) N3 な-adjective influential 有力視 (ゆうりょくし) N3 Noun being considered influential 絞り込む (しぼりこむ) N3 Godan verb to narrow down 決定する (けっていする) N3 Suru verb to decide 求める (もとめる) N3 Godan verb to request 相次ぐ (あいつぐ) N3 Godan verb to follow one after another 開く (ひらく) N4 Godan verb to open 任期 (にんき) N4 Noun term of office 延長 (えんちょう) N4 Noun extension 開かれる (ひらかれる) N4 Ichidan verb to be held 決まる (きまる) N4 Godan verb to be decided 求める (もとめる) N4 Godan verb to seek 決定する (けっていする) N4 Suru verb to determine 追加 (ついか) N4 Noun addition 競技 (きょうぎ) N4 Noun sport 諮る (はかる) N4 Godan verb to consult 開く (ひらく) N5 Godan verb to open 決まる (きまる) N5 Godan verb to be decided 求める (もとめる) N5 Godan verb to seek 決定する (けっていする) N5 Suru verb to determine 追加 (ついか) N5 Noun addition 競技 (きょうぎ) N5 Noun sport 諮る (はかる) N5 Godan verb to consult 総会 (そうかい) N1 Noun general meeting 候補地 (こうほち) N1 Noun candidate site 絞り込む (しぼりこむ) N1 Godan verb to narrow down 決定する (けっていする) N1 Suru verb to decide Grammar and Sentence Structure ３０年大会の招致を断念した札幌市は、３４年大会の開催も絶望的となった。</description></item><item><title>鈴木宗男氏、北海道の維新議員らと面談　今後の所属「各自の判断で」</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/mr-munenari-suzuki-meets-with-members-of-the-ishin-party-in-hokkaido-future-affiliation-to-be-determined-by-each-individual-s-judgment/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/mr-munenari-suzuki-meets-with-members-of-the-ishin-party-in-hokkaido-future-affiliation-to-be-determined-by-each-individual-s-judgment/</guid><description>日本維新の会からの離党やロシア訪問について支持者らに講演する鈴木宗男参議院議員=2023年10月14日、札幌市中央区、松尾一郎撮影 Link to the original article
日本にほん維新いしんの会かいを離党りとうした鈴木宗男すずきむねお参議院議員さんぎいんぎいんは14日にち、自みずからが北海道ほっかいどう総支部そうしぶ代表だいひょうとして擁立ようりつに関かかわった維新いしん所属しょぞくの道議どうぎや市議しぎらと面談めんだんし、今後こんごの所属政党しょぞくせいとうなどについては各かく議員ぎいんらの判断はんだんを尊重そんちょうする考かんがえを伝つたえた。維新いしん側がわが方針ほうしんを決きめるまで、多おおくの議員ぎいんらは、維新いしんと、鈴木氏すずきしが代表だいひょうをつとめる地域政党ちいきせいとう「新党大地しんとうだいち」に重複ちょうふくして関係かんけいを続つづける見込みこみ。 道内どうないの維新所属いしんしょぞく議員ぎいんは道議どうぎ1人にん、札幌市議さっぽろしぎ5人にん、千歳市議ちとせしぎ1人にん。鈴木すずきさんによると、議員ぎいんと、次期じき衆院選しゅういんせんで維新いしんから道どう2区くと3区くで立候補りっこうほする予定よていの2人にんと面談めんだんし、「個人こじんの判断はんだんで私わたしは結構けっこうだ」と伝つたえたという。1区くの立候補予定者りっこうほよていしゃとは面談めんだんしなかったという。 鈴木すずき氏らによると、維新いしん側は、鈴木すずき氏の後任こうにんに当あたる道総支部代表どうそうしぶだいひょうをまもなく選任せんにんする見込みこみだという。（松尾一郎まつおいちろう） Vocabulary Word (Furigana) JLPT Level Part of Speech Meaning 離党 (りとう) N3 Noun leaving a political party 鈴木 (すずき) Proper Noun Noun Suzuki (surname) 宗男 (むねお) Proper Noun Noun Muneo (given name) 参議院 (さんぎいん) N3 Noun House of Councillors 議員 (ぎいん) N4 Noun member of a legislative body 面談 (めんだん) N3 Noun interview, discussion 所属 (しょぞく) N3 Noun affiliation, membership 擁立 (ようりつ) N2 Noun supporting, backing 関わる (かかわる) N4 Verb (Godan) to be involved in 今後 (こんご) N3 Noun from now on, in the future 政党 (せいとう) N3 Noun political party 各 (かく) N3 Noun each, every 判断 (はんだん) N3 Noun judgement, decision 尊重 (そんちょう) N3 Noun respect, esteem 考える (かんがえる) N4 Verb (Ichidan) to think, to consider 維新 (いしん) N3 Noun restoration, renewal 方針 (ほうしん) N3 Noun policy, plan 決める (きめる) N4 Verb (Ichidan) to decide, to determine 議員 (ぎいん) N4 Noun member of a legislative body 重複 (ちょうふく) N3 Noun duplication, overlap 関係 (かんけい) N4 Noun relationship, connection 続ける (つづける) N4 Verb (Ichidan) to continue, to keep up 見込み (みこみ) N3 Noun expectation, prospect 道内 (どうない) N3 Noun within the prefecture 道議 (どうぎ) N3 Noun prefectural assembly member 市議 (しぎ) N3 Noun city council member 予定 (よてい) N4 Noun plan, schedule 立候補 (りっこうほ) N3 Noun candidacy 衆院選 (しゅういんせん) N3 Noun general election for the House of Representatives 代表 (だいひょう) N4 Noun representative, delegate 選任 (せんにん) N3 Noun appointment, selection Grammar and Sentence Structure 鈴木氏によると、議員と、次期衆院選で維新から道2区と3区で立候補する予定の2人と面談し、「個人の判断で私は結構だ」と伝えたという。</description></item><item><title>「協力すれば起訴はないと言われた」　元市議が改めて主張し、結審</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/the-former-city-councilor-reiterated-his-claim-that-he-was-told-there-would-be-no-prosecution-if-he-cooperated-and-the-trial-concluded/</link><pubDate>Fri, 13 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/the-former-city-councilor-reiterated-his-claim-that-he-was-told-there-would-be-no-prosecution-if-he-cooperated-and-the-trial-concluded/</guid><description>広島地裁=広島市中区 Link to the original article
2019年ねんさんいんせんのだいきぼかいしゅうじけんで、かわいかつゆきょうげんほうしょう（60）=こうしょくせんきょほういはんざいでじっけいかくてい=からげんきん30まんえんをうけとったとして、どうほういはん（ひばいしゅう）のつみにとわれたもとひろしましぎ、きどつねやす（つねやす）ひこく（68）のこうはんが13にち、ひろしまちさいでけっしんした。けんさつがわはばっきん15まんえんとついちょうきん30まんえんをきゅうけい。べんごがわは「いほうなしほうとりひきがあった」として、あらためてこうそきかむざいとうったえた。 弁護べんご側がわは8月がつに記者会見きしゃかいけんを開ひらき、取とり調しらべべの録音ろくおんデータでーたの一部いちぶを公表こうひょう。木戸きど被告ひこくは東京とうきょう地検ちけん特捜部とくそうぶの検事けんじから「議員ぎいんを続つづけていただきたい。否認ひにんにしたくない」などと説明せつめいを受うけ、不起訴ふきそを示唆しさされて供述きょうじゅつを誘導ゆうどうされたと主張しゅちょうした。 検察けんさつ側がわはこの日ひの論告ろんこくで、木戸きど被告ひこくが「検事けんじから、起訴きそされないとは確約かくやくできないと言いわれた」と公判こうはんで述のべたとし、「違法いほうな司法しほう取引とりひきがあったとは認みとめられない」と訴うったえた。 一方いっぽう、木戸きど被告ひこくは最終陳述さいしゅうちんじゅつで「取とり調しらべで事実じじつを述のべているのに内容ないようを否定ひていされた。家宅捜索かたくそうさくをほのめかされ、協力きょうりょくすれば起訴きそはないと繰くり返かえし言いわれた」と述のべ、被買収ひばいしゅうの認識にんしきも否定ひていした。 木戸きど被告ひこくは、河井かわい元もと法相ほうしょうの妻つま案里あんり氏し（50）=同どう法ほう違反いはん罪ざいで有罪ゆうざい確定かくてい=の選挙せんきょ運動うんどう報酬ほうしゅうと知しりながら、19年ねん4月がつに現金げんきん30万まん円えんを受うけ取とった罪ざいに問とわれている。判決はんけつは26日にちの予定よてい。（大野おおの晴香はるか、根本ねもと快かい） Vocabulary Word JLPT Level Part of Speech Meaning 参院選 (さんいんせん) N3 Noun House of Councillors election 大規模 (だいきぼ) N3 Na-adjective large-scale 買収 (ばいしゅう) N3 Noun acquisition, bribery 事件 (じけん) N3 Noun incident, case 元 (もと) N4 Noun former 法相 (ほうしょう) N3 Noun Minister of Justice 公職選挙法 (こうしょくせんきょほう) N2 Noun Public Offices Election Act 違反 (いはん) N3 Noun violation 罪 (つみ) N4 Noun crime 実刑 (じっけい) N3 Noun actual imprisonment 確定 (かくてい) N3 Noun finalization 現金 (げんきん) N4 Noun cash 受け取る (うけとる) N4 Godan verb to receive 同法違反 (どうほういはん) N2 Noun violation of the same law 被買収 (ひばいしゅう) N3 Noun being bribed 公判 (こうはん) N3 Noun public trial 広島地裁 (ひろしまちさい) N3 Noun Hiroshima District Court 結審 (けっしん) N3 Noun conclusion of a trial 検察側 (けんさつがわ) N3 Noun prosecution side 罰金 (ばっきん) N3 Noun fine 追徴金 (ついちょうきん) N3 Noun additional tax 求刑 (きゅうけい) N3 Noun demand for punishment 弁護側 (べんごがわ) N3 Noun defense side 司法取引 (しほうとりひき) N1 Noun plea bargain 公訴棄却 (こうそききゃく) N1 Noun dismissal of charges 無罪 (むざい) N3 Noun innocence 訴える (うったえる) N3 Godan verb to sue, to accuse 記者会見 (きしゃかいけん) N3 Noun press conference 取り調べ (とりしらべ) N3 Noun interrogation 録音データ (ろくおんでーた) N3 Noun recorded data 公表 (こうひょう) N3 Noun announcement 示唆 (しさ) N3 Noun suggestion 不起訴 (ふきそ) N3 Noun non-indictment 示唆する (しさする) N3 Suru verb to suggest 誘導する (ゆうどうする) N3 Suru verb to lead, to guide 論告 (ろんこく) N3 Noun closing argument 認める (みとめる) N4 Godan verb to admit 最終陳述 (さいしゅうちんじゅつ) N3 Noun final statement 否定する (ひていする) N3 Suru verb to deny 家宅捜索 (かたくそうさく) N3 Noun home search 協力する (きょうりょくする) N4 Suru verb to cooperate 起訴 (きそ) N3 Noun indictment 繰り返し (くりかえし) N4 Noun repetition 認識 (にんしき) N3 Noun recognition Grammar and Sentence Structure 弁護側は「違法な司法取引があった」として、改めて公訴棄却か無罪と訴えた。</description></item><item><title>子ども放置禁止条例案に反対署名2万9千超　さいたまPTA協が提出</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/over-29-000-signatures-against-the-proposed-ordinance-banning-child-neglect-submitted-by-the-saitama-pta-council/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/over-29-000-signatures-against-the-proposed-ordinance-banning-child-neglect-submitted-by-the-saitama-pta-council/</guid><description>10日、改正案の取り下げ表明を受け、さいたま市PTA協議会のメンバーらは浦和駅前に立ち、社会全体で虐待をなくそうと呼びかけた=さいたま市 Link to the original article
子こどもの自宅じたくなどへの放置ほうちを禁きんじた埼玉県さいたまけん虐待ぎゃくたい禁止きんし条例改正案かいせいあんについて、反対はんたいの署名しょめい活動をしていたさいたま市さいたましPTA協議会きょうぎかい（市P協ししきょう）は12日にち、県議会けんぎかい議長ぎちょうや自民党じみんとう県議団けんぎだん長ちょうなどに、集あつまった署名しょめい2万まん9千せん筆ひつ超をメールで提出ていしゅつした。 市し協きょうは、改正かいせい案が県議会けんぎかい福祉ふくし保健ほけん医療いりょう委員会いいんかいで可決かけつされた6日にちに、「ほとんどの保護者ほごしゃが条例じょうれい違反いはんになる」「地域社会ちいきしゃかいの分断ぶんだんを促うながす」などとしてオンラインおんらいん署名しょめいの活動かつどうを始はじめ、街頭がいとうでも署名しょめいを呼よびかけていた。 改正案かいせいあんをめぐっては、提出ていしゅつした自民じみん県議団けんぎだんが子こどもだけの登下校とうげこうや短時間たんじかんの留守番るすばんも「虐待ぎゃくたい」にあたるとの考かんがえを示しめし、県内けんない外がいから批判ひはんが噴出ふんしゅつ。10日にちに田村琢実団長たむらたくみだんちょうが取とり下さげを表明ひょうめいした。県議団けんぎだんは11日にち、議長ぎちょうあてに撤回てっかい請求書せいきゅうしょを出だした。 市しP協きょうは今回のメールで、改正案取と下げげについて「保ほ護ご者しゃや子こどもたちの声こえを聞きいてもらうことができたと安あん堵ど（あんど）している」とした上で、養よう護ご者しゃが「安あん全ぜん配はい慮りょ義務む」を果はたたせるような支しえ援えんの拡かく充じゅうを要よう望ぼう。保ほ育いく所じょや学がく童どう保ほ育いく、ベビーシッターの制せい度ど、児じ童どう相そう談だん所しょ職しょく員いんの拡かく充じゅうなどを挙あげ、「子こどもを守まもるための具ぐ体たい的てきな施し策さくを検けん討とうし、実じつ現げんしていただきたい」と求もとめた。 改正案かいせいあんの撤回てっかいは、13日に本会議ほんかいぎでの採決さいけつを経へて正式せいしきに決きまる見通みとおし。（小林未来こばやしみく、黒田壮吉くろだそうきち） Vocabulary Word JLPT Level Part of Speech Meaning 禁じる (きんじる) N3 verb to prohibit 改正案 (かいせいあん) N3 noun amendment proposal 提出する (ていしゅつする) N3 verb to submit 署名活動 (しょめいかつどう) N3 noun signature campaign 反対 (はんたい) N3 noun opposition 署名 (しょめい) N3 noun signature 集まる (あつまる) N3 verb to gather 提示する (ていじする) N3 verb to present 可決する (かけつする) N3 verb to approve 違反 (いはん) N3 noun violation 分断 (ぶんだん) N3 noun division 促す (うながす) N3 verb to urge 噴出する (ふんしゅつする) N3 verb to spout 取り下げる (とりさげる) N3 verb to withdraw 表明する (ひょうめいする) N3 verb to declare 撤回する (てっかいする) N3 verb to retract 要望 (ようぼう) N3 noun request 安堵する (あんどする) N3 verb to be relieved 聞く (きく) N5 verb to listen 安全 (あんぜん) N4 noun safety 配慮 (はいりょ) N4 noun consideration 果たす (はたす) N4 verb to fulfill 支援 (しえん) N4 noun support 拡充 (かくじゅう) N4 noun expansion 挙げる (あげる) N4 verb to raise 実現する (じつげんする) N4 verb to realize 決まる (きまる) N4 verb to be decided 見通し (みとおし) N4 noun outlook 職員 (しょくいん) N4 noun staff 検討する (けんとうする) N3 verb to consider 決める (きめる) N4 verb to decide Grammar and Sentence Structure 「改正案をめぐっては、提出した自民県議団が子どもだけの登下校や短時間の留守番も「虐待」にあたるとの考えを示し、県内外から批判が噴出。」 Grammatical points: The verb &amp;ldquo;示し&amp;rdquo; is in the 連体形 (attributive form) of the verb &amp;ldquo;示す&amp;rdquo; (to show), which modifies the noun &amp;ldquo;考え&amp;rdquo; (thought).</description></item><item><title>父親と長男の頭に複数の打撃痕、強い殺意か　秋田・民家敷地の3遺体</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/multiple-strike-marks-on-the-heads-of-the-father-and-eldest-son-strong-murderous-intent-three-bodies-found-on-the-premises-of-a-private-residence-in-akita/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/multiple-strike-marks-on-the-heads-of-the-father-and-eldest-son-strong-murderous-intent-three-bodies-found-on-the-premises-of-a-private-residence-in-akita/</guid><description>現場検証に入る秋田県警の捜査員ら=2023年10月11日午前9時11分、秋田県由利本荘市、室矢英樹撮影 Link to the original article
秋田県あきたけん由利本荘市ゆりほんじょうしの無職むしょく斎藤真一さいとうしんいちさん（66）方ほうで9日、真一しんいちさんら3人の遺体いたいが見みつかった火災かさいで、出火元しゅっかもとの民家みんかに隣接りんせつする別棟べつとうで倒たおれていた真一しんいちさんと長男ちょうなんの会社員かいしゃいん孝彦たかひこさん（38）の頭部とうぶに複数ふくすうの打撃痕だげきこんがあり、骨ほねが折おれていたことが、捜査関係者そうさかんけいしゃへの取材しゅざいでわかった。県警けんけいは何者なにものかが強つよい殺意さついを持もって、2人の頭あたまを繰くり返かえし殴なぐった事件じけんの可能性かのうせいがあるとみて調査ちょうさしている。 県警けんけいによると、真一しんいちさんと孝彦たかひこさん親子おやこは別棟べつとうの空あき家1階いっかいの廊下ろうかで倒たおれていた。司法解剖しほうかいぼうの結果けっか、2人の頭部とうぶには外傷がいしょうが数かずカ所しょあり、骨ほねが折おれ、出血しゅっけつしていた。鈍器どんき状じょうのもので殴なぐられ、死亡しぼうした可能性かのうせいが高たかいという。 真一しんいちさん方かたの2階かいで見みつかった遺体いたいは男性だんせいで、無職むしょくの次男じなん（35）の自室じしつの近ちかくで倒たおれていた。司法解剖しほうかいぼうの結果けっか、首くびの動脈どうみゃくが切きれたことによる失血死しっけつしで、上半身じょうはんしんの一部いちぶが焼やけていたことも判明はんめいした。県警けんけいは、この遺体いたいが連絡れんらくが取とれていない次男じなんとみて確認かくにんを進すすめている。 一家いっかは5人家族にんかぞくで、妻つまと四男よんなんは8日にちごぜん、市内しないの親類宅しんるいたくに外出がいしゅつ。その際さい、亡なくなった3人にんに変かわった様子ようすはなかったという。 県警けんけいは11日から、出火元しゅっかもとの真一しんいちさん方かたで現場検証げんばけんしょうを始はじめた。真一しんいちさんと孝彦たかひこさんが殴なぐられた際さいに使つかわれたと見みられる凶器きょうき類るいを特定とくていできておらず、出火原因しゅっかげんいんとともに詳くわしく調しらべている。（室矢英樹むろやひでき、阿部浩明あべひろあき） Vocabulary Word (Furigana) JLPT Level Part of Speech Meaning 無職 (むしょく) N3 Noun unemployed 斎藤 (さいとう) Proper Noun - Saito (surname) 真一 (しんいち) Proper Noun - Shinichi (given name) 方 (かた) N3 Noun person 見つかる (みつかる) N4 Godan verb to be found 遺体 (いたい) N3 Noun dead body 火災 (かさい) N3 Noun fire 出火 (しゅっか) N2 Noun outbreak of fire 元 (もと) N3 Noun origin 民家 (みんか) N3 Noun private house 隣接 (りんせつ) N2 Noun adjacency 別棟 (べつとう) N2 Noun separate building 倒れる (たおれる) N4 Ichidan verb to fall 頭部 (とうぶ) N3 Noun head 複数 (ふくすう) N3 Noun multiple 打撃痕 (だげきこん) N1 Noun bruise 骨 (ほね) N4 Noun bone 折れる (おれる) N4 Ichidan verb to break 捜査 (そうさ) N3 Noun investigation 関係者 (かんけいしゃ) N3 Noun person concerned 取材 (しゅざい) N2 Noun coverage 県警 (けんけい) N2 Noun prefectural police 何者 (なにもの) N2 Noun someone 強い (つよい) N5 い-adjective strong 殺意 (さつい) N1 Noun intent to kill 持つ (もつ) N5 Godan verb to hold 繰り返す (くりかえす) N4 Godan verb to repeat 事件 (じけん) N4 Noun incident 可能性 (かのうせい) N3 Noun possibility 調べる (しらべる) N4 Ichidan verb to investigate 結果 (けっか) N4 Noun result 鈍器 (どんき) N1 Noun blunt instrument 死亡 (しぼう) N3 Noun death 高い (たかい) N5 い-adjective high Grammar and Sentence Structure &amp;ldquo;真一さんら 3 人の遺体が見つかった火災で、出火元の民家に隣接する別棟で倒れていた真一さんと長男の会社員孝彦さん（38）の頭部に複数の打撃痕があり、骨が折れていたことが、捜査関係者への取材でわかった。&amp;rdquo; Explanation:</description></item><item><title>「留守番も虐待」条例改正案、取り下げへ　自民党埼玉県議団が表明</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/amendment-proposal-for-leaving-children-home-alone-is-also-abuse-ordinance-to-be-withdrawn-announced-by-the-liberal-democratic-party-saitama-prefectural-members/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/amendment-proposal-for-leaving-children-home-alone-is-also-abuse-ordinance-to-be-withdrawn-announced-by-the-liberal-democratic-party-saitama-prefectural-members/</guid><description>埼玉県庁=さいたま市浦和区 Link to the original article
子ども（こども）childを自宅や車内などに放置ほうちすることを禁止きんしする埼玉県さいたまけん虐待禁止きんし条例改正案かいせいあんについて、提出ていしゅつした自民党じみんとう県議団は10日にち、改正案かいせいあんを取とり下さげることを決きめた。同県議団けんぎだんはこれまでに、子どもこどもだけの登下校とうげこうや短時間たんじかんの留守番るすばんなども「虐待ぎゃくたい」にあたるとの見解けんかいを示しめし、批判ひはんを呼よんでいた。 自民じみん県議団けんぎだんは 10日にち午後に記者会見きしゃかいけんを開ひらき、田村琢実たむらたくみ団長の名前なまえで書面しょめんを配布はいふ。「私わたしの言葉足ことばたらずにより、県民けんみんの皆様みなさまはもとより全国的ぜんこくてきに不安ふあんと心配しんぱいの声こえが広ひろがり、多おおくの県民けんみん・団体だんたいなどより、県議団けんぎだんに対たいし様々さまざまなご意見いけんを頂戴ちょうだい（ちょうだいちょうだい）した」と説明せつめい。条例じょうれい運用うんようにあたっては趣旨しゅしが十分じゅうぶん理解りかいされ、社会しゃかい全体ぜんたいで子供こどもの安全あんぜんを守まもる機運きうんにつながることが重要じゅうようだとして「こうした観点かんてんから、本ほん議案ぎあんについては取とり下さげさせて頂いたきます」とした。 改正案かいせいあんは、全国ぜんこくで相次あいつぐ置おき去ざりによる子こどもの死亡しぼう事故じこを受うけ、同どう県議団けんぎだんが4日にち、県議会けんぎかいに提出ていしゅつした。6日にちの県議会けんぎかい福祉ふくし保健ほけん医療いりょう委員会いいんかいで自民じみん、公明こうみょう両党りょうとう県議団けんぎだんの賛成さんせいにより可決かけつされ、13日にちの議会ぎかい最終日さいしゅうびに採決さいけつされる予定よていだった。 改正案の内容は、罰則ばっそくは設けないが、成人せいじんの養護者ようごしゃが小学3年生以下しょうがくさんねんせいいかの子どもこどもを放置ほうちすることを禁止きんしし、4～6年生ねんせいについては努力どりょく義務ぎむとし、県民けんみんには通報つうほうを義務ぎむづけるというもの。 禁止行為について、委員会で提案者ていあんしゃを代表だいひょうして答弁とうべんした自民県議じみんけんぎは、子どもこどもだけでの登下校とうげこうや短時間たんじかんの留守番るすばんも「放置ほうち」にあたりあたり、虐待ぎゃくたいとみなすとの考えかんがえを示しめした。他会派たかいはからは「保護者ほごしゃを追おい詰つめる」などと批判ひはんの声こえが上あがった。 田村氏たむらしは6日に、将来的しょうらいてきに罰則ばっそくを設けるもうける可能性かのうせいについて「今後こんご子こどもを放置ほうちするような状況じょうきょうがたくさん出でてくるようなことがあれば、再考さいこうする必要ひつようがある」と述のべていた。 県内けんないでは保護者ほごしゃらの反発はんぱつが高たかまり、さいたま市PTA協議会さいたましPTAきょうぎかい（市P協しきょう）は6日に反対はんたいの署名活動しょめいかつどうを始はじめた。（西田有里にしだゆうり） Vocabulary Word (Furigana) JLPT Level Part of Speech Meaning 自宅 (じたく) N3 Noun home 車内 (しゃない) N1 Noun inside a car 放置 (ほうち) N2 Noun neglect, abandonment 禁止 (きんし) N4 Noun prohibition 埼玉県 (さいたまけん) Proper Noun Noun Saitama Prefecture 虐待 (ぎゃくたい) N3 Noun child abuse 改正 (かいせい) N2 Noun amendment 提出 (ていしゅつ) N3 Noun submission 自民党 (じみんとう) Proper Noun Noun Liberal Democratic Party (LDP) 県議団 (けんぎだん) Proper Noun Noun prefectural assembly group 記者会見 (きしゃかいけん) N3 Noun press conference 名前 (なまえ) N4 Noun name 配布 (はいふ) N2 Noun distribution 言葉 (ことば) N4 Noun words, language 不安 (ふあん) N3 Noun anxiety 心配 (しんぱい) N4 Noun worry 広がり (ひろがり) N2 Noun spread, expansion 乏しい (とぼしい) N3 い-Adjective scarce, lacking 県民 (けんみん) N2 Noun prefectural residents 意見 (いけん) N4 Noun opinion, view 頂戴 (ちょうだい) N3 Verb receive, get (humble form) 条例 (じょうれい) N3 Noun regulation, ordinance 批判 (ひはん) N3 Noun criticism 趣旨 (しゅし) N1 Noun main point, gist 理解 (りかい) N3 Noun understanding 保護者 (ほごしゃ) N3 Noun guardian 罰則 (ばっそく) N2 Noun penalties 設ける (もうける) N3 Godan verb establish, set up 努力 (どりょく) N4 Noun effort, endeavor 重要 (じゅうよう) N3 な-Adjective important 際 (さい) N3 Noun occasion, time 出てくる (でてくる) N4 Ichidan verb come out, appear 反発 (はんぱつ) N3 Noun opposition, resistance 署名活動 (しょめいかつどう) N3 Noun petition, signature campaign Grammar and Sentence Structure 改正案は、全国で相次ぐ置き去りによる子どもの死亡事故を受け、同県議団が 4 日、県議会に提出した。</description></item><item><title>だんじりの練習中　引き手の男性、ガードレールに挟まれて死亡</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/during-danjiri-practice-a-male-puller-was-fatally-trapped-between-the-guardrail/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/during-danjiri-practice-a-male-puller-was-fatally-trapped-between-the-guardrail/</guid><description>大阪府 Link to the original article
大阪市おおさかし生野区いくのく桃谷ももたに2丁目ちょうめの路上ろじょうで8日にちごご6時じ10分ふんごろ、だんじりを先頭せんとうでひいていた職業不詳しょくぎょうふしょう、佐さ古こ吉よし隆たかさん（52）=大阪市おおさかし生野区いくのく=が、だんじりとガードレールがーどれーるの間あいだに挟はさまれた。佐さ古こさんは病院びょういんに搬送はんそうされたが、9日にちあさに出血性しゅっけつせいショックしょっくで死亡しぼうした。約やく30人にんがだんじりをひいていたが、ほかにけが人ひとはなかった。 生野署いくのしょによると、だんじりだんじりが道路どうろを左折さてつする際さい、停止ていししようとしたがしきれずにガードレールガードレールに衝突しょうとつしたとみられる。地区ちくの祭りまつりに備そなえた練習れんしゅうだった。事故じこ当時じは雨あめが降ふっており、路面ろめんがぬれていたという。署しょは当時とうじの詳くわしい状況じょうきょうや事故じこ原因げんいんを調しらべている。 Vocabulary Word (Furigana) JLPT Level Part of Speech Meaning 引く (ひく) N5 verb to pull 先頭 (せんとう) N3 noun front, lead 佐古 (さこ) N/A noun proper noun for a person&amp;rsquo;s name 吉 (よし) N/A noun good luck 隆 (たかし) N/A noun proper noun for a person&amp;rsquo;s name する N5 verb to do 挟まる (はさまる) N4 verb to be caught between 病院 (びょういん) N4 noun hospital 搬送する (はんそうする) N3 verb to transport 出血性 (しゅっけつせい) N/A noun hemorrhagic ショック N5 noun shock 死亡 (しぼう) N2 noun death 約 (やく) N3 noun approximately 人 (ひと) N5 noun person けが N5 noun injury 大阪 (おおさか) N/A noun proper noun for a place 生野 (いくの) N/A noun proper noun for a place 区 (く) N4 noun district 桃谷 (ももや) N/A noun proper noun for a place 丁目 (ちょうめ) N3 noun city block 路上 (ろじょう) N/A noun road surface ８日 (ようか) N/A noun 8th 午後 (ごご) N4 noun afternoon ６時 (ろくじ) N5 noun 6 o&amp;rsquo;clock １０分 (じゅっぷん) N5 noun 10 minutes ごろ N5 noun around (a time) だんじり N/A noun proper noun for a festival float 際 (さい) N2 noun occasion, moment 停止する (ていしする) N3 verb to stop しきる N1 verb to finish, to complete 衝突する (しょうとつする) N3 verb to collide みる N5 verb to see 降る (ふる) N5 verb to fall (rain, snow) ぬれる N4 verb to get wet 調べる N4 verb to investigate 雨 (あめ) N5 noun rain 地区 (ちく) N3 noun district 祭り (まつり) N4 noun festival 備える (そなえる) N3 verb to prepare 練習 (れんしゅう) N4 noun practice 当時 (とうじ) N2 noun that time, then 詳しい (くわしい) N3 adjective (い) detailed 状況 (じょうきょう) N3 noun situation 原因 (げんいん) N4 noun cause, reason 集める (あつめる) N3 verb to gather, to collect Grammar and Sentence Structure &amp;ldquo;だんじりを先頭で引いていた職業不詳、佐古吉隆さん（52）=大阪市生野区=が、だんじりとガードレールの間に挟まれた。&amp;rdquo;</description></item><item><title>隣接する納骨堂には練炭なし、住職の行動把握か　足立区の納骨堂殺人</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/in-the-adjacent-columbarium-without-charcoal-briquettes-is-the-action-of-the-chief-priest-being-monitored-homicide-at-the-columbarium-in-adachi-ward/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/in-the-adjacent-columbarium-without-charcoal-briquettes-is-the-action-of-the-chief-priest-being-monitored-homicide-at-the-columbarium-in-adachi-ward/</guid><description>地下納骨堂のイメージ Link to the original article
東京とうきょう都と足立あだち区くの「源証げんしょう（げんしょう）寺じ」で7月がつ、地下納骨堂ちかなっこうどうに練炭れんたんが置おかれ、住職じゅしょくが一酸化炭素中毒いっさんかたんそちゅうどくで殺害さつがいされた事件じけんで、納骨堂なっこうどうは南北なんぼくで2部屋へやあり、練炭れんたんは南みなみ側がわだけに置おかれていたことが捜査そうさ関係者かんけいしゃへの取材しゅざいでわかった。事件じけん当時とうじ、納骨なっこつなどで使つかわれるのは南みなみ側がわが中心ちゅうしんだったといい、警視庁けいしちょうは、殺人さつじん容疑ようぎで逮捕たいほした墓石ぼせき販売はんばい会社がいしゃ代表だいひょうらが住職じゅしょくの行動こうどうや寺てらの構造こうぞうを把握はあくして事件じけんを計画けいかくしたとみている。 捜査1課などによると、千葉県ちばけんの「鵠祥堂こくしょうどう」代表取締役だいひょうとりしまりやくの斎藤竜太さいとうりゅうた（50）と役員やくいんの青木淳子あおきじゅんこ（63）の両容疑者りょうようぎしゃは共謀きょうぼうして7月22日深夜しんや、源証寺げんしょうじに侵入しんにゅう。焼却炉にガソリン入いりペットボトルぺっとぼとる十数本を入いれると共ともに、納骨堂のうこんどう内に練炭れんたん28個こを設置せっちして着火ちゃっかし、翌23日朝あさ、納骨堂のうこんどうに入はいった住職じゅしょくの大谷忍昌おおたにしのまささん（当時とうじ70）を一酸化炭素いっさんかたんそ中毒ちゅうどくで殺害さつがいした疑うたがいがある。 捜査関係者かんけいしゃによると、地下の納骨堂のうこつどうは南北なんぼくに隣接りんせつして2カ所あり、地上部分ちじょうぶぶんの入り口いりくちも別々べつべつで、隣り合となりあっていた。練炭れんたんは南側みなみがわの床ゆかに置おかれていたといういう。納骨堂内のうこつどうないには壁かべに4段だんの棚たながあり、骨壺こつつぼが置おかれていた。 大谷さんは7月23日なながつにじゅうさんにち朝、練炭れんたんを見つけて南側みなみがわの納骨堂のうこつどうに入ろうとし、一酸化炭素中毒いっさんかたんそちゅうどくで意識いしきを失うしなって倒たおれたと同課どうかはみている。北側きたがわの納骨堂のうこつどうに置おかれたのは古ふるい骨壺ほねつぼなどで、作業さぎょうすることは少すくなかったという。北側きたがわに不審ふしんな点てんはなかった。 納骨堂のうこつどうから約やく15メートルめーとる離はなれた焼却炉しょうきゃくろ内ないには、ガソリンがそりん入いりのペットボトルぺっとぼとる十数本ほんが置おかれていた。焼却炉しょうきゃくろを使つかうのは大谷さんおおたにさんが主おもで、納骨堂のうこつどう内ないの作業さぎょうで出でたゴミごみなど燃もやしていたという。 捜査そうさ1課かは、容疑者ようぎしゃ2人にんがこうした大谷おおたにさんの行動こうどうパターンを事前じぜんに把握はあくしていたと見みている。納骨堂のうこんどう内ででの一酸化炭素いっさんかたんそ中毒ちゅうどくか、ゴミ焼却しょうきゃく時じに大量たいりょうのガソリンがそりんを爆発的ばくはつてきに燃焼ねんしょうさせるいずれかの方法ほうほうで、大谷おおたにさんを殺害さつがいしようとした可能性かのうせいがあると見みている。 鵠祥堂こくしょうどうは源証寺げんしょうじ近くの霊園れいえん「足立セメタリーパークあだちせめたりーぱーく」の開発かいはつに関わりかかわり、販売はんばいなどに関するかんする契約を2020年ねん3月がつに締結ていけつした。霊園の運営うんえいを巡めぐって大谷おおたにさんと斎藤さいとう容疑者らの間あいだに、対象たいしょうとする宗派しゅうはに関してかんして意見の対立たいりつがあったといい、同どう課かは事件じけんとの関連かんれんを調べしらべている。（増山ますやま祐史ゆうじ、遠藤えんどう美波みなみ、長妻ながつま昭明あきあき） Vocabulary Word JLPT Level Part of Speech Meaning 置く (おく) N5 verb (godan) to place, to put 使う (つかう) N4 verb (godan) to use 入れる (いれる) N3 verb (ichidan) to put in, to insert 侵入する (しんにゅうする) N1 verb (suru) to invade, to trespass 着火する (ちゃっかする) N2 verb (suru) to ignite, to set on fire 購買 (こうばい) N1 noun purchase, buy 入り口 (いりぐち) N4 noun entrance 計画する (けいかくする) N3 verb (suru) to plan 担当する (たんとうする) N2 verb (suru) to be in charge of 知る (しる) N4 verb (godan) to know, to be aware of 把握する (はあくする) N2 verb (suru) to grasp, to understand 見つける (みつける) N4 verb (ichidan) to find, to discover 殺害する (さつがいする) N2 verb (suru) to murder, to kill 収蔵する (しゅうぞうする) N3 verb (suru) to store, to keep 設置する (せっちする) N2 verb (suru) to install, to set up 残す (のこす) N3 verb (godan) to leave behind, to remain 作業する (さぎょうする) N3 verb (suru) to work, to do a task 出る (でる) N4 verb (godan) to come out, to leave 問題 (もんだい) N4 noun problem, question 事件 (じけん) N4 noun incident, event 容疑者 (ようぎしゃ) N3 noun suspect 点 (てん) N4 noun point, spot 対立 (たいりつ) N3 noun conflict, opposition 関連 (かんれん) N2 noun relation, connection 開発 (かいはつ) N3 noun development 運営 (うんえい) N3 noun operation, management 意見 (いけん) N3 noun opinion, view 寺 (てら) N4 noun temple 内 (うち) N5 noun inside 十数 (じゅうすう) N3 noun several, a dozen Grammar and Sentence Structure Sentence 1: 捜査 1 課などによると、千葉県の「鵠祥（こくしょう）堂」代表取締役の斎藤竜太（50）と役員の青木淳子（63）の両容疑者は共謀して 7 月 22 日深夜、源証寺に侵入。</description></item><item><title>「世界ふしぎ発見！」レギュラー放送終了へ　草野さん「天職だった」</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/the-regular-broadcast-of-sekai-fushigi-hakken-to-come-to-an-end.-mr.-kusano-says-it-was-my-calling./</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/the-regular-broadcast-of-sekai-fushigi-hakken-to-come-to-an-end.-mr.-kusano-says-it-was-my-calling./</guid><description>回答者から名答、珍答の理由を絶妙な話術で引き出す元司会の草野仁さん=2000年8月5日、東京都赤坂のTBS Link to the original article
TBSは6日、37さんじゅうなな年半はんにわたって続つづいてきたクイズ番組ばんぐみ「日立世界ひたちせかいふしぎ発見はっけん！」のレギュラー放送ほうそうを来年らいねん3月がつで終お了するすると発表はっぴょうした。4月がついかんは特番とくばんとして放送ほうそうする予定よてい。世界せかいの不思議ふしぎを歴史れきしとともに解とき明あかすクイズ番組ばんぐみで、1986年ねん4月がつに放送ほうそうを開始かいし。現在げんざいクイズマスターの形かたちで出演しゅつえんする草野仁くさのじんさん（79）が、今年ことし4月がつに石井亮次いしいりょうじさん（46）に交代こうたいするまで司会しかいを務つとめていた。黒柳徹子やなぎてつこさんらレギュラー出演しゅつえん者は、特番とくばんも出演しゅつえんする予定よていだという。 草野さんは「最初さいしょは苦戦くせんの連続れんぞくでした。毎週まいしゅう芸能界げいのうかいの第一線だいいっせんで活躍かつやくされている豪華ごうかな方々かたがたをゲストげすとにお迎むかえして番組ばんぐみを差配さばいしていく重圧じゅうあつはとても大おおきいものでした。徐々じょじょに慣なれていき、ゲストの皆様みなさまを捌さばいていくことの楽たのしみをおぼえるようになり、ついにはこの仕事しごとが天職てんしょくであったなと思おもうようになりました」などとコメントを寄よせた。 番組開始かいし時からから出演しゅつえんする黒くろ柳徹子さん（90）は「学校がっこう時代じだい、ちゃんと勉強べんきょうしてこなかった歴史れきしが、仕事しごとで出来できるんですから、こんなに有難ありがたいことはありませんでした」、石井いしいさんは「ここから半年はんとし、さらに気合きあいを入いれて臨のぞみます！」などとコメントした。 Vocabulary Word JLPT Level Part of Speech Meaning 発表する (はっぴょうする) N3 verb (irregular) to announce 続く (つづく) N3 verb (godan) to continue 終了する (しゅうりょうする) N3 verb (irregular) to end 特番 (とくばん) N3 noun special program 解き明かす (ときあかす) N3 verb (godan) to solve/reveal 放送する (ほうそうする) N3 verb (irregular) to broadcast 出演する (しゅつえんする) N3 verb (irregular) to appear (on stage/screen) 司会を務める (しかいをつとめる) N3 verb phrase to serve as a host 連続する (れんぞくする) N3 verb (irregular) to occur consecutively 大きい (おおきい) N4 い-adjective big 出来る (できる) N4 verb (ichidan) can/do/make 見る (みる) N4 verb (ichidan) to watch 言う (いう) N4 verb (godan) to say 寄せる (よせる) N4 verb (ichidan) to send 覚える (おぼえる) N4 verb (ichidan) to remember 思う (おもう) N4 verb (godan) to think 務める (つとめる) N4 verb (ichidan) to serve 楽しむ (たのしむ) N4 verb (godan) to enjoy 捌く (さばく) N4 verb (godan) to deal with 入れる (いれる) N4 verb (ichidan) to put in 集める (あつめる) N4 verb (ichidan) to collect 横浜 (よこはま) Proper Noun noun Yokohama (city in Japan) 重圧 (じゅうあつ) N3 noun pressure 慣れる (なれる) N4 verb (ichidan) to get used to 覚える (おぼえる) N4 verb (ichidan) to remember 半年 (はんとし) N4 noun half a year 入れる (いれる) N4 verb (ichidan) to put in 気合 (きあい) N4 noun fighting spirit 臨む (のぞむ) N4 verb (godan) to face/approach 若手 (わかて) N4 noun young person お年寄り(おとしより) N4 noun elderly person 豪華 (ごうか) N3 な-adjective gorgeous/amazing Grammar and Sentence Structure Sentence 1: 「最初は苦戦の連続でした。毎週芸能界の第一線で活躍されている豪華な方々をゲストにお迎えして番組を差配していく重圧はとてつもなく大きいものでした。</description></item><item><title>「生活習慣病＝自己責任」ではありません　人はなぜ病気になるのか</title><link>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/lifestyle-diseases-are-not-solely-the-individual-s-responsibility-why-do-people-get-sick/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digicosmos86.github.io/maiasahi/post/lifestyle-diseases-are-not-solely-the-individual-s-responsibility-why-do-people-get-sick/</guid><description>内科医・酒井健司の医心電信 Link to the original article
糖尿病とうにょうびょうは不摂生ふせっせいや運動不足うんどうぶそくのせいであり自己責任じこせきにんの病気びょうきだという誤あやまったイメージいめーじがあります。「ダイアベティスだいあべてぃす」への呼称こしょうの変更へんこうが提案ていあんされた目的もくてきの一ひとつはそうした誤解ごかいや偏見へんけんを取とり除のぞくことです。ならば、同様どうように「生活習慣病せいかつしゅうかんびょう」という呼よび方かたも考かんがえ直なおしてみるのはいかがでしょうか。 生活習慣病せいかつしゅうかんびょうは、不適切ふてきせつな食事しょくじ・運動不足うんどうぶそく・喫煙きつえん・飲酒いんしゅなどの生活習慣せいかつしゅうかんが原因げんいんとなる疾患しっかんの総称そうしょうです。糖尿病とうにょうびょうや高血圧こうけつあつや脂質異常症しつしついじょうしょう、脳血管障害のうけっかんしょうがいや心疾患しんしっかん、がんなどが生活習慣病せいかつしゅうかんびょうだとされています。以前いぜんは「成人病せいじんびょう」と呼よばれていましたが、必かならずしも成人せいじんだけが発症はっしょうする病気びょうきではありません。生活習慣病せいかつしゅうかんびょうという呼称こしょうは聖路加国際病院せいろかこくさいびょういんの日野原重明ひのはらしげあきせんせいらが長年ながねん提案ていあんしていて、1996年ねんには行政用語ぎょうせいようごとして採用さいようされました。 生活習慣病せいかつしゅうかんびょうという呼称こしょうは、さまざまな病気びょうきが生活習慣せいかつしゅうかんと関連かんれんしていることをわかりやすく明確めいかくに示しめしています。その結果けっか、多おおくの人ひとが健康的けんこうてきな生活習慣せいかつしゅうかんの重要性じゅうようせいを理解りかいし、予防意識よぼういしきが高たかまって病気びょうきを未然みぜんに防ふせぐことが期待きたいできます。これは生活習慣病せいかつしゅうかんびょうという呼称こしょうのプラスぷらすの側面そくめんです。 一方いっぽうで、病気びょうきに対たいする偏見へんけんを招まねくというマイナスまいなすの側面がわめんもあります。生活習慣せいかつしゅうかんは病気びょうきの原因げんいんの一ひとつに過すぎません。どんなに健康的けんこうてきな生活習慣せいかつしゅうかんを送おくっていても病気びょうきになるときはなりますし、逆ぎゃくに不健康ふけんこうな生活せいかつをしていても病気びょうきにならない人ひとはなりません。生活習慣病せいかつしゅうかんびょうと呼よぶことで、病気びょうきにかかった人ひとはみな不健康ふけんこうな生活習慣せいかつしゅうかんを送おくっていたという誤解ごかいを招まねきかねません。こうした誤解ごかいは、「生活習慣病せいかつしゅうかんびょうにかかるのは自己責任じこせきにんであり医療費いりょうひの自己負担じこふたんの割合わりあいを増ふやすべき」といった議論ぎろんを招まねき、「自業自得じごうじとくの人工透析じんこうとうせき患者かんじゃなんて、全員ぜんいん実費じっぴ負担ふたんにさせよ」といった暴論ぼうろんに行いき着つくおそれがあります。 「全員ぜんいん」ではないにせよ不健康ふけんこうな生活せいかつのせいで病気びょうきになった人ひとはいるのは事実じじつだ」という反論はんろんが予想よそうされます。その通とおりですが、だからといって生活習慣病せいかつびょうは自己責任じこせきにんだと断だんずるのは誤あやまりです。貧困ひんこんや劣悪れつあくな労働環境ろうどうかんきょうといった、個人こじんの努力どりょくではいかんともしがたい社会経済的しゃかいけいざいてきな要因よういんが不健康ふけんこうな生活習慣せいかつしゅうかんと関連かんれんしていることはよく知しられています。現代げんだいにおいて、肥満ひまんや糖尿病とうにょうびょうはぜいたく病びょうではありません。健康けんこう的な生活せいかつをしたくてもできない人ひとたちがいるのです。 生活習慣病せいかつしゅうかんびょうという呼称こしょうを変更へんこうしたところで、偏見へんけんや誤解ごかいがすぐになくなるわけではありません。生活習慣せいかつしゅうかんが病気びょうきの原因げんいんになりうることを周知しゅうちするというプラスぷらすの側面そくめんを重視じゅうしするという考え方かんがえかたもあるでしょう。ですが、マイナスまいなすの側面そくめんも忘わすれないようにしましょう。不健康ふけんこうな生活習慣せいかつしゅうかんにペナルティーぺなるてぃーを与あたえるのではなく、すべての人ひとが健康的けんこうてきな生活せいかつを選択せんたくできる社会しゃかいのほうが望のぞましいと私わたしは考かんがえます。（酒井健司さかいけんじ） Vocabulary Word JLPT Level Part of Speech Meaning 不摂生 (ふせっせい) N3 Noun unhealthy lifestyle 運動不足 (うんどうぶそく) N3 Noun lack of exercise 自己責任 (じこせきにん) N3 Noun personal responsibility 病気 (びょうき) N4 Noun illness 誤った (あやまった) N4 Adjective incorrect イメージ N4 Noun image 提案 (ていあん) N4 Noun proposal 偏見 (へんけん) N4 Noun prejudice 偏った (かたよった) N4 Adjective biased 呼称 (こしょう) N4 Noun appellation 変更 (へんこう) N4 Noun change 考え直す (かんがえなおす) N4 Godan verb reconsider 生活習慣病 (せいかつしゅうかんびょう) N4 Noun lifestyle-related disease 食事 (しょくじ) N4 Noun meal 適切 (てきせつ) N4 Na-adjective appropriate 飲酒 (いんしゅ) N4 Noun drinking alcohol 疾患 (しっかん) N4 Noun disease 総称 (そうしょう) N4 Noun general term 高血圧 (こうけつあつ) N3 Noun high blood pressure 脂質異常症 (しつしついじょうしょう) N3 Noun dyslipidemia 脳血管障害 (のうけっかんしょうがい) N3 Noun cerebrovascular disorder 必ずしも (かならずしも) N3 Adverb not always 成人 (せいじん) N3 Noun adult 発症 (はっしょう) N3 Noun onset 行政用語 (ぎょうせいようご) N3 Noun administrative language 予防意識 (よぼういしき) N3 Noun awareness of prevention 未然に (みぜんに) N2 Adverb before it happens 防ぐ (ふせぐ) N2 Godan verb prevent 負担割合 (ふたんわりあい) N2 Noun burden ratio 暴論 (ぼうろん) N2 Noun fallacious argument 社会経済的 (しゃかいけいざいてき) N1 Na-adjective socio-economic 要因 (よういん) N1 Noun factor 肥満 (ひまん) N1 Noun obesity Grammar and Sentence Structure 「生活習慣病という呼称は聖路加国際病院の日野原重明先生らが長年提案していて、1996年には行政用語として採用されました。」 Grammatical points: This sentence includes a relative clause and a passive verb.</description></item></channel></rss>